<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-110">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 28</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-01 18:51:37.544143+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">110</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">110</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">110</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">111</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 28</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 28</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-04-01T18:51:37.544143+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-04-01T18:51:37.544143+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=110 status=live modified=2021-04-01 18:51:37.544143+00 | translation moa=111 status=live modified=2016-06-07 11:03:03.493815+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus hoc scriptum uisuris uel audituris <cl type="intitulatio">Alexand<ex>er</ex> de striuelin</cl> . <cl type="salutation">Salutem eternam in domino</cl></cl>. <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Noueritis quod</cl> <lb/> cum venerabilis in Christo pater D<ex>aui</ex>d dei gratia Episcopus Sancti Andree de consensu prioris ⁊ conuentus eiusdem <lb/> loci propter diuini cultus augmentum . ⁊ ad instanciam meam capelle mee de
                     Laurencistun <lb/> cantariam concescisset  ne matrix Ecclesia de Eglisgirge ex tali concessione
                     aliquam paciatur <lb/> iacturam  promisi fideliter quod ego et heredes mei faciemus dicte capelle
                     honeste exspensis propriis <lb/> deseruiri ⁊ omnes obuenciones siue oblaciones ad dictam capellam prouenientes
                     faciemus in<lb/>tegre ad dictam matricem Ecclesiam de Eglisgirge deferri . eam in omnibus
                     indempnem con<lb/>seruantes . capellanus eciam quicunque dicte capelle deseruiet  priusquam ibi
                     celebret sacramentum <lb/> fidelitatis dicte matrici Ecclesie prestabit. Et ad recognicionem subiectionis
                     ego et heredes mei sin<lb/>gulis annis in perpetuum . In nundinis de munros vnam libram cere persoluemus.
                     Quod si ego uel <lb/> heredes mei uel capellanus qui in dicta capella ministrauerit contra aliquod
                     predictorum venerimus  promitto firmiter <lb/> pro me ⁊ heredibus meis quod usque ad condignam satisfaccionem a celebracionem
                     diuinorum in predicta capella <lb/> cessabitur .</cl> <cl type="sealing">In cuius rei testimonium vna cum sigillo Archidiaconi sancti Andr<ex>ee</ex> presenti scripto sigillum meum <lb/> apposui</cl> Datum apud Ormest<ex>un</ex> Nonas decembris . Anno gracie . m . cc . xliii .</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all who shall view or hear this deed, <cl type="intitulatio">Alexander of Stirling</cl> <cl type="salutation">wishes eternal salvation in the Lord</cl></cl>: <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">May you all know that</cl> since the venerable father in Christ, David by the grace of God bishop of St
                     Andrews, by the consent of the prior and religious
                     community of the same place and for the augmentation of
                     divine worship, and at my urging, granted to my chapel at
                     Lauriston a chantry: lest the mother church of Egglisgrig
                     should suffer any loss from such a grant, I promised
                     faithfully that I and my heirs would cause its own
                     expenses properly to be paid to the said chapel, and we
                     would cause all obventions or offerings coming in to the
                     said chapel to be transferred entirely to the said mother
                     church of Egglisgrig, keeping it without injury or loss in
                     all things, the chaplain also, whoever it be, that shall
                     minister at the said chapel, before he celebrate the
                     sacrament there shall take an oath of fealty to the said
                     mother church, and as acknowledgement of submission, I and
                     my heirs shall pay out one pound of wax each year on the
                     Fair of Montrose in perpetuity. But if I or my heirs, or
                     the chaplain who ministers in the said chapel, should act
                     against any of the aforesaid things, I firmly promise for
                     myself and my heirs that until appropriate satisfaction
                     [has been made] there shall be no celebration of divine
                     service in the aforesaid chapel.</cl> <cl type="sealing">In testimony whereof together with the seal of the Archdeacon of St Andrews I
                  have applied my seal to the present deed.</cl> Given at Ormiston on the Nones of December [5 December] in the year of grace
                  1243.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>