<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-223">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of NRS GD45/13/247</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 09:35:37.563782+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">223</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">223</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">223</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">222</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/247</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>NRS GD45/13/247</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-04-05T09:35:37.563782+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-04-05T09:35:37.563782+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=223 status=live modified=2021-04-05 09:35:37.563782+00 | translation moa=222 status=live modified=2021-04-05 09:35:34.111333+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription"><p>C Y R O G R A P H U M</p> <p><cl type="narration">Hec est conuentio facta Inter Dominum . W . abatem ⁊ conuentum sancte crucis de
                  Edinburg ex una parte ⁊ Walterum<lb/> Magistrum ⁊ fratres de Torphean . ex altera parte de contouersia que uertebatur
                     inter eos ⁊ coram iudicibus delegatis diu<lb/> uentilabatur super decimis ⁊ ouentionibus de Ogilfas . quod predicti abbas ⁊
                     conuentus consensu ⁊ autoritate iudicum<lb/> delegatorum in presencia domini . W . de Bosch’ . domini regis cancellarii ⁊
                     aliorum prudentum uiros . pro bono pacis concesserunt<lb/> predictis fratribus omnes decimationes ⁊ ouentiones ecclesiasticas quas ipsi
                     habebant ⁊ percipere solebant de terra de Ogilfas .<lb/> Predicti uero fratres tenebunt ⁊ inperpetuum possidebunt prenominatas decimas
                     libere ⁊ quiete plenarie ⁊ honorifice reddendo inde<lb/> abbati ⁊ conuentui sancte crucis de Edenburg singulis annis quatuor Marcas
                     argenti . duas ad pentecost’ ⁊ duas ad festum<lb/> sancti martini.</cl> <cl type="sealing">Ut autem hec conuentio rata ⁊ inconcussa permaneat in perpetuum signa iudicum de
                  predicta causa delegatorum<lb/> ⁊ capituli conuentus sancti andree ⁊ capituli domus hospitalis lundon’ .
                     presenti scripto in testimonium ⁊ confirmationem<lb/> huius conuentionis apponuntur ne in irritum possit reuocari.</cl></p></div>
      <div type="translation"><p>C Y R O G R A P H</p> <p><cl type="narration">This is the agreement made between the lord abbot, W., and the convent of
                  Holyrood in Edinburgh on the one side and Walter the Master,
                  and the brethren of Torphichen on the other side, concerning
                  the dispute which arose between them and was aired for a long
                  while before judges delegate, over the teinds and revenues
                  from Ogilface, that the aforesaid abbot and convent, with the
                  consent and authority of the judges delegate, in the presence
                  of the lord William del Bois, chancellor of the lord king,
                  and other judicious men, for the sake of good peace, granted
                  to the aforesaid brethen all the teinds and ecclesiastical
                  revenues that they themselves used to have and were
                  accustomed to receive from the land of Ogilface. The
                  aforesaid brethren, however, shall hold and in perpetuity
                  possess the aforenamed teinds freely and quietly, fully and
                  honourably, by rendering thereupon to the abbot and convent
                  of Holyrood in Edinburgh each year four merks of silver, two
                  at Pentecost and two at the feast of Saint Martin.</cl> <cl type="sealing">In order that this agreement remain sure and unbroken in perpetuity the seals of
                  the judges delegate of the aforesaid case and the chapter of
                  the convent of St Andrews and the chapter of the hospital of
                  London [Clerkenwell?] are set to the present document in
                  testimony and confirmation of this agreement lest it could be
                  revoked as being invalid.</cl></p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>