<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-234">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of NRS GD45/13/252</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 08:18:19.816552+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">234</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">234</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">234</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">235</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/252</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>NRS GD45/13/252</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-04-06T08:18:19.816552+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-04-06T08:18:19.816552+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=234 status=live modified=2021-04-06 08:18:19.816552+00 | translation moa=235 status=live modified=2021-04-06 08:18:18.00307+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus Sancte Matris Ecclesie filiis et fidelibus <cl type="intitulatio">Edgarus filius Dofnaldi .</cl> <cl type="salutation">Salutem</cl>.</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Sciant omnes tam presentes quam futuri</cl> me Consensu filii ⁊ heredis mei<lb/> fergus dedisse ⁊ concessisse et hac presenti mea Carta confirmasse deo ⁊
                     ecclesie Sancte crucis de Edenburc ⁊ Canonicis ibidem deo
                     ser<lb/>uientibus et seruituris ecclesiam de Dalgarenoc cum tota terra ad eandem
                     ecclesiam pertinente ⁊ cum communi pastura predicte uille
                     ⁊ omnibus<lb/> aliis rectitudinibus ⁊ pertinenciis suis tam in decimis quam in aliis
                     ouencionibus ad eandem ecclesiam iuste pertinentibus
                     tenendum sibi in liberam puram<lb/> ⁊ perpetuam elemosinam pro salute animarum dominorum meorum Regum Scott’ ⁊ pro
                     animabus patris mei ⁊ matris mee ⁊ omnium antecessorum ⁊
                     suc<lb/>cessorum meorum. <cl type="holding">Quare volo ut predicti Canonici prefatam ecclesiam cum terra ⁊ omnibus
                     libertatibus suis ita libere quiete plenarie ⁊ honorifice<lb/> in perpetuum teneant ⁊ possideant Sicut aliqua ecclesia in toto regno scott’
                        liberius datur quiecius ⁊ plenius tenetur ⁊ possidetur
                        saluo personatu .G.<lb/> persone ⁊ perpetua uicaria Enoc</cl>.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">Hiis test<ex>ibus</ex> fergus filio domini edgari . Martino persona de Du<ex>m</ex>f’ . Enoc clerico . Ioh<ex>ann</ex>e filio Radulfi decani<lb/> de Du<ex>m</ex>fr’ . Gillec<ex>ris</ex>t Iudice . Gille conel ⁊ Dofnalt fili<ex>is</ex> edgari ⁊ multis aliis boni testimonii viris</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all sons and faithful people of Holy Mother Church, <cl type="intitulatio">Edgar son of Donald</cl> <cl type="salutation">sends Greeting:</cl></cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Let all people, both present and future, know</cl> that, with the consent of my son and heir, Fergus, I have given and granted, and
                     by this present charter made firm, to God and to the
                     church of Holyrood in Edinburgh, and to the canons serving
                     God there now and in the future, the church of Dalgarnock
                     with all the land pertaining to the same church, and with
                     common pasture of the foresaid toun, and all its other
                     revenues and pertinents, in teinds as well as in other
                     obventions, justly belonging to the same church, for them
                     to hold in free, pure and perpetual alms, for the
                     salvation of the souls of my lords the kings of Scots, and
                     for the souls of my father and my mother and of all my
                     ancestors and successors. <cl type="holding">Wherefore I will that the foresaid canons hold and possess the forementioned
                     church with its land and all its liberties so freely,
                     quietly, fully and honourably in perpetuity as any church
                     in the whole of the kingdom of the Scots is freely given,
                     is quietly and fully held and possessed, reserving the
                     parsonage of G. the parson, and the perpetual vicarage of
                     Enoch</cl>.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">With these witnesses, Fergus son of the lord Edgar, Martin the parson of
                  Dumfries, Enoch the clerk, John son of Ralph the dean of
                  Dumfries, Gilchrist the judex, Gilla Conaill and Donald sons
                  of Edgar, and many other men of good testimony.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>