<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-294">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of NRS GD55/36</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-07-20 12:11:18.52272+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">294</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">294</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">294</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">295</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/36</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>NRS GD55/36</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-07-20T12:11:18.52272+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-07-20T12:11:18.52272+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=294 status=live modified=2021-07-20 12:11:18.52272+00 | translation moa=295 status=live modified=2021-04-06 11:31:18.310406+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus Sancte matris Ecclesie filiis presentibus et futuris <cl type="intitulatio"><persName>Raderic</persName> Mac<persName>Gillescop</persName> . et <persName>Cristiana</persName> sponsa eius filia <persName>Rogeri</persName><lb/> de Scalebroc</cl> <cl type="salutation">Salutem</cl> .</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Sciatis nos</cl> concessisse et hac nostra Carta confirmasse deo et Ecclesie de Melr’ et monachis<lb/> ibidem deo seruientibus in liberam et puram et perpetuam elemosinam donationem <persName>Rogeri</persName> de Scaleb<ex>ro</ex>c quam fecit eidem<lb/> ecclesie et monachis predictis de piscatura de Don super harenam et una salina
                     cum terris et toftis et Omnibus<lb/> aisiamentis que continentur in Carta predicti <persName>Rogeri</persName> <cl type="holding">tenenda et possidenda in perpetuum ita libere et quiete plenarie<lb/> et honorifice sicut aliqua elemosina liberius et quietius plenius et
                        honorificentius tenetur uel possidetur et sicut Carta
                        predicti<lb/> <persName>Rogeri</persName> testatur</cl> .</cl> <cl type="warrandice">Et nos et heredes nostri manutenebimus et warrantizabimus eis omnia predicta et
                  adquietabimus ea<lb/> erga omnes homines de omni seruitio in perpetuum .</cl> <cl type="disposition">Concessimus etiam eisdem monachis et hac Carta confirmauimus<lb/> totam terram de Drumteisuiene et de Alesburc et de Authenephur . quantum ad nos
                     pertinet <cl type="holding">tenendam et possi<lb/>dendam in perpetuum ita libere et quiete et honorifice sicut carta predicti <persName>Rogeri</persName> et confirmatio domini nostri <persName>Dun<ex>ecani</ex></persName> . testan<lb/>tur</cl> .</cl> <cl type="witnesses">Teste eodem <persName>Dun<ex>ecano</ex></persName> . <persName>Will<ex>elmo</ex></persName> . vicec<ex>omite</ex> . de nouo Castello super Ar . <persName>Waltero</persName> clerico Regis <persName>Ioh<ex>ann</ex>e</persName> clerico . <persName>Ioh<ex>anne</ex></persName> fratre<lb/> <persName>Vdardi</persName> <persName>Gilleb’</persName> mac <persName>Kenedi</persName> . <persName>Ewein</persName> mac <persName>Alewi<supplied>n</supplied></persName> . <persName>Gillenem</persName> mac<persName>colem’</persName> .</cl> <cl type="sealing">Et quia sigillum proprium non<lb/> habuimus Dominus <persName>Dunec<ex>anus</ex></persName> . rogatu nostro sigillum suum pro nobis huic carte nostre apposuit .</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, present and future, <cl type="intitulatio">Rory mac Gillespie and Christiana his spouse, the daughter of Roger of
                     Skelbrooke</cl>, <cl type="salutation">send Greeting</cl>:</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Know us</cl> to have granted, and by this our charter to have made firm, to God and to the
                     Church of Melrose and to the monks serving God in that
                     place, in free and pure and perpetual alms, the donation
                     of Roger of Skelbrooke which he made to the same church
                     and monks aforesaid, of a fishery on the Doon above <ex>Harenam</ex>, and one saltpan, with lands and tofts and all easements that are contained in
                     the charter of the aforesaid Roger, <cl type="holding">to be held and possessed for all time in this wise freely and quietly, fully and
                     honourably, just as any alms is freely and quietly, fully
                     and honourably held possessed, and just as the charter of
                     the aforesaid Roger bears witness</cl>.</cl> <cl type="warrandice">And we and our heirs shall maintain and warrant all things aforesaid to them and
                  we shall acquit them in respect of all men from every service
                  for all time.</cl> <cl type="disposition">We have also granted to the same monks, and by this charter have made firm, the
                  whole land of <ex>Drumteisuiene</ex> and of <ex>Alesburc</ex> and of <ex>Authenephur</ex>, so much as belongs to us, <cl type="holding">to be held and possessed for all time, in this wise freely and quietly and
                     honourably, just as the charter of the aforesaid Robert
                     and the confirmation of our lord Duncan bear witness.</cl></cl> <cl type="witnesses">As witness, the same Duncan, William the sheriff of Newcastle-upon-Ayr, Walter
                  the king’s clerk, John the clerk, John the brother of Udard,
                  Gilbert mac Kennedy, Ewen mac Alewine, Gilla na Náem mac
                  Colmán.</cl> <cl type="sealing">And since we did not have our own seal, the lord Duncan, at our request, has set
                  his seal to this charter for us.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>