<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-465">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of NRS GD55/178</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:46:55.519153+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">465</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">470</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">465</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">466</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/178</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>NRS GD55/178</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-04-06T15:46:55.519153+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-04-06T15:46:55.519153+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=465 status=live modified=2021-04-06 15:46:54.03281+00 | translation moa=466 status=live modified=2021-04-06 15:46:55.519153+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Sciant presentes et futuri quod</cl> <cl type="intitulatio">ego Robertus de Bernam</cl> dedi . concessi et Hac pre<lb/>senti carta mea confirmaui deo et beate Marie de Melr<ex>os</ex> et monachis ibidem deo<lb/> seruientibus in liberam et perpetuam elemosinam illud Rete in Berwyc<ex>es</ex>trem' super twed’<lb/> quod Magister Dauid frater meus tunc camerarius domini Regis emit de Radulfo de
                     Hauuill’<lb/> falconario domini Regis . et dedit illud Rogero fratri meo et heredibus suis .
                     uel suis assig<lb/>natis De quo quidem reti idem Rogerus dotauit christianam filiam Ade marescalli
                     uxo<lb/>rem suam in uita sua . post cuius decessum idem rete iure hereditario me con<lb/>tingit . <cl type="holding">Tenendum et habendum dictis monachis inperpetuum adeo libere et quiete . plene<lb/> et honorifice  sicut carta predicti Radulfi de Hauuil' dicto magistro dauid
                        inde ple<lb/>nius confecta  testatur .</cl> <cl type="warrandice">Ego uero et heredes mei dictum rete dictis monachis omnino<lb/> ut dictum est contra omnes warantizabimus ac defendemus</cl> .</cl> <cl type="sealing">In cuius rei testi<lb/>monium ego pro me et heredibus meis huic scripto sigillum meum apponi fe<lb/>ci .</cl> <cl type="witnesses">Teste communia de Berwyc’ .</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Let present and future know that</cl> <cl type="intitulatio">I, Robert de Bernham</cl>, have given, granted and by this my present charter made firm to God and
                     Blessed Mary at Melrose and to the monks serving God in
                     that place, in free and everlasting alms, the net in
                     Berwickstream upon the Tweed, which Master David my
                     brother, then chamberlain of the lord king, purchased from
                     Ralph de Hauville, falconer of the lord king, and gave it
                     to Roger my brother and to his heirs or his assignees.
                     From this net the same Roger endowed Christiana daughter
                     of Adam the Marshal, his wife, for her lifetime, after
                     whose death the net shall belong to me by reight of
                     heritage. <cl type="holding">For the said monks to hold and have as freely and quitely, fully and honourably,
                     as the charter of the said Ralph de Hauville, made more
                     fully thereupon for the said Master David, bears witness.</cl> <cl type="warrandice">I and my heirs shall entirely warrant and defend the said net to the said monks
                     against all people.</cl></cl> <cl type="sealing">In testimony of this matter I, for myself and for my heirs, have applied my seal
                  to this written deed.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">As witness, the community of Berwick.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>