<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-499">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of NRS GD55/234</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-12 13:45:36.011+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">499</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">506</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">499</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">500</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/234</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>NRS GD55/234</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="approved">
      <change when="2023-06-12T13:45:36.011+00:00" status="approved">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2023-06-12T13:45:36.011+00:00" status="approved">transcription moa=499 status=reviewed modified=2023-06-12 13:45:36.011+00 | translation moa=500 status=reviewed modified=2023-06-12 13:45:35.983215+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus Christi fidelibus tam presentibus quam futuris ad quos presens Scriptum
                  peruenerit <cl type="intitulatio">Magister Willelmus de Grenelau filius Rolandi<lb/> filius Willelmi</cl> <cl type="salutation">salutem in domino</cl> .</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">vniuersitati vestre notum facio</cl> me diuine pietatis intuitu et pro salute anime mee et pro salute<lb/> animarum omnium predecessorum et successorum meorum dedisse et concessisse et
                     hac carta mea confirmasse deo et ecclesie beate Marie de<lb/> Melros et monachis ibidem deo et matri sue seruientibus et inperpetuum
                     seruituris tres carucatas terre quas habui in territorio<lb/> ville de halsingtun cum omnibus pertinenciis suis illas scilicet quas domina
                     Matildis mater Domini Roberti de Muscampo dedit<lb/> Willelmo filio Iohannis de honum cum Gilia filia dicte Matildis in liberum
                     Maritagium <cl type="holding">Tenendas et habendas dictis Monachis<lb/> de Melros cum omnibus libertatibus aisiamentis et Iuribus ad eas pertinentibus
                        inperpetuum in liberam puram et perpetuam elemosinam<lb/> nullum omnino seculare seruicium pro eis alicui faciendo preter oraciones et
                        suffragia et alia beneficia deo placentia que<lb/> dicti monachi promiserunt in fide quam deo debent et ordini suo se facturos pro
                        me inperpetuum</cl></cl> <cl type="warrandice">Et ego et heredes mei<lb/> manutenebimus predictis Monachis hanc elemosinam et warantizabimus contra omnes
                     homines et adquietabimus eam de omni<lb/> seruicio inperpetuum</cl> <cl type="sealing">In cuius Rei testimonium sigillum meum presentibus est appensum</cl> <cl type="witnesses">hiis testibus Radulpho de Bonekil<lb/> Iohanne de letham Iohanne pepedi Dauid de Buredon halano de harcar’ Iohanne
                     filio Simonis Iohanne de lembeden’<lb/> Roberto filio suo . Rolando filio Iohannis . et multis aliis .</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all Christ's faithful as well present as future to whom the present writing
                  shall come, <cl type="intitulatio">Master William of Greenlaw son of Roland</cl> <cl type="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</cl>.</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">I make known to your whole community that</cl> moved by divine love and for the salvation of my soul and for the salvation of
                     the souls of all my predecessors and successors I have
                     given and granted and by this my charter made firm to God
                     and to the church of Blessed Mary at Melrose and to the
                     monks in that place serving God and their Mother and who
                     in perpetuity will serve there three ploughgates of land
                     that I had in the territory of the toun of Hassington with
                     all its pertinents; that is, those that the lady Matilda,
                     mother of the lord Robert de Muschamp, gave to William,
                     son of John of Hownam, with Gilia, daughter of the said
                     Matilda, in free marriage; <cl type="holding">for the said monks to hold and have with all liberties, easements, and rights
                     belonging to it for ever, in free, pure, and everlasting
                     alms; by performing no secular service whatever for them
                     to anyone, except for prayers and sugffrages and other
                     spiritual goods which the said monks promised in faith, as
                     much as they owe to God and their own Order, that they
                     would perform for me for ever.</cl></cl> <cl type="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain to the said monks this alms, and we shall
                  warrant it against all men, and we shall acquit it in respect
                  of every service for ever.</cl> <cl type="sealing">In testimony of this thing my seal has been applied to these presents.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">With these witnesses: Ralph of Bunkle; John of Latham; John of Papedy; David of
                  Burradon; Alan of Harcarse; John son of Simon; John of
                  Lambden; Robert his son; Roland son of John; and many others.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>