<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-632">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.34</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:25:23.460551+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">632</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">642</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">632</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">633</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.34</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>BL Cotton Ch. xviii.34</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-04-05T08:25:23.460551+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-04-05T08:25:23.460551+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=632 status=live modified=2021-04-05 08:25:23.460551+00 | translation moa=633 status=live modified=2021-04-05 08:25:19.239185+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription"><p>C Y R O G R A P H V M</p> <p><cl type="narration">Hec est composicio facta inter ecclesiam de cupro et ecclesiam de blare in
                  presencia magistrorum <persName>Ranulfi</persName> archidiaconi . et<lb/> <persName>laurencii</persName> officialis de Sancto andrea tociusque synodi apud perth. Scilicet quod monachi
                     de cupro persoluent ecclesie de<lb/> blare unam petram cere pro omnibus decimis pertinentibus ad terras de lethcassi
                     et de parthesin . quas habent idem mo<lb/>nachi . persoluetur autem predicta cera prefate ecclesie de blare ad lumen
                     eiusdem ecclesie . singulis annis ad festum Sancti<lb/> Martini</cl> . <cl type="sealing">Et ut hec composicio rata et inconcussa permaneat in posterum  prenominatus <persName>Ran’</persName> archidiaconus et supradictus <persName>lau<lb/>rencius</persName> officialis quibus uices suas commisit dominus <persName>Will<ex>elmu</ex>s</persName> episcopus de Sancto andrea  illam sigillorum suorum munimine roborauerunt</cl> .<lb/> <cl type="witnesses">Teste synodo</cl> apud perth  Kalendis . Maii .</p></div>
      <div type="translation"><p>C Y R O G R A P H</p> <p><cl type="narration">This is the agreement made between the church of Cupar and the church of Blair
                  in the presence of Masters Ranulf the archdeacon and Laurence
                  the official of St Andrews and the whole synod at Perth. That
                  is, that the monks of Cupar should pay to the church of Blair
                  one stone of wax in return for all the teinds belonging to
                  the lands of ‘Lethcassi’ and of Persey, which the same monks
                  have. The aforesaid wax should be paid, however, to the
                  church of Blair for the light of the same church, each year
                  at the feast of Saint Martin</cl>. <cl type="sealing">And so that this agreement remain firm and unshaken in the future, the
                  aforenamed Ranulf the archdeacon and the above-said Laurence
                  the official, to whom the the lord William, bishop of St
                  Andrews, has entrusted his duties, have validated it with the
                  corroboration of their own seals.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">Witnessed by the synod</cl> at Perth on the kalends of May. </p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>