<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-676">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of BL Add. Ch. 76748</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:48:49.231109+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">676</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">686</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">676</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">677</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Add. Ch. 76748</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>BL Add. Ch. 76748</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-04-05T08:48:49.231109+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-04-05T08:48:49.231109+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=676 status=live modified=2021-04-05 08:48:47.27971+00 | translation moa=677 status=live modified=2021-04-05 08:48:49.231109+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus has literas visuris uel audituris <cl type="intitulatio"><persName>Alwinus</persName> filius <persName>Duncani</persName> de fofrekin</cl> <cl type="salutation">Salutem</cl></cl> <cl type="notification">Sciatis</cl> <cl type="disposition">me dedisse et concessisse et hac<lb/> carta mea confirmasse <persName>Malbrido Marrenah</persName> et heredibus suis terram illam que fuit in lite inter me et dominum <persName>laurentium</persName> filium <persName>orm</persName><lb/> per rectas diuisas <cl type="boundaries">ab illi mec ewin usque ad modlahin et ex alia parte inter Gahnakarbet et aldi
                     nalar</cl> <cl type="holding">ad tenendum<lb/> de me et heredibus meis ille et heredes sui libere et quiete ab omni seruicio et
                        consuetudine et exactione et forinseco et ab aliquo<lb/> ausilio</cl> . et predictus <persName>Malbrid</persName> habebit comunam pasturam et multuram suam liberam eundo ubicumque . uoluerit et
                     predictus <persName>Malbrid</persName><lb/> habebit merchet et blodwit et vnlah libere quantum ad terram illam pertinet . et
                     predictus malbrid reddet annuatim<lb/> et heredes sui mihi et heredibus meis octo solidos argenti . quatuor solidos .
                     ad pentecosten et quatuor solidos ad festum sancti Martini</cl><lb/> <cl type="witnesses">Test<ex>ibus</ex> <persName>Waldeuo</persName> filio <persName>merleswain</persName> et herede suo . <persName>Duncano</persName> filio <persName>ade</persName> et herede suo <persName>Will<ex>elm</ex>o</persName> persona de Kilconcat . <persName>Toma</persName> de<lb/> lundin et herede suo . <persName>Malcolmo</persName> Iudice . et Multis aliis .</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all intending to view or hear these letters, <cl type="intitulatio">Alwin son of Duncan of Foffarty</cl> <cl type="salutation">[sends] greeting</cl>.</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Know</cl> me to have given, conceded, and by this my charter to have made firm, to
                     Maelbrigte Marrenah and his heirs that land which is in
                     dispute between me and the lord Laurence son of Orm, by
                     the right marches, <cl type="boundaries">from 'Illi mec Ewin' to 'Modlahin' and, from the other side, between
                     'Gahnakarbet' and 'Aldi Nalar';</cl> <cl type="holding">to be held of me and my heirs by him and his heirs free and quit from all
                     service, custom, exaction, forinsec, and from any aid;</cl> and the aforesaid Maelbrigte shall have his own free common pasture and multure
                     going wherever he wishes, and the aforesaid Maelbrigte
                     will have merchet, blodwite, and unlaw, freely, as much as
                     pertains to that land; and the aforesaid Maelbrigte and
                     his heirs shall annually render to me and my heirs eight
                     shillings of silver, four shillings at Pentecost and four
                     shillings at Martinmas.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">As witnesses: Waldef son of Merlswain, and his heir; Duncan son of Adam, and his
                  heir; William the parson of Kilconquhar; Thomas of Lundin,
                  and his heir; Malcolm the judex; and many others.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>