<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-678">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of BL Add. Ch. 76750</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:50:03.945869+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">678</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">688</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">678</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">679</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Add. Ch. 76750</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>BL Add. Ch. 76750</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-04-05T08:50:03.945869+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-04-05T08:50:03.945869+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=678 status=live modified=2021-04-05 08:50:03.945869+00 | translation moa=679 status=live modified=2021-04-05 08:50:02.175966+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus sancte Matris ecclesie filiis <cl type="intitulatio"><persName>Robertus</persName> de Quinci</cl> <cl type="salutation">salutem</cl></cl> . <cl type="notification">Sciant presentes et futuri</cl> <cl type="disposition">me dedisse et concessisse et hac mea karta<lb/> confirmasse deo et ecclesie sancte crucis de Edenburh et Canonicis ibidem deo
                     seruientibus unam Carucatam terre et decem<lb/> acras interritorio de trauernent uersus Phaeside pro excambio illius Carucate
                     terre de prestun quam Canonici predicti uersis me<lb/> et Monachos de Neubotle Calumpniauerunt ita quod prenominati Canonici me et
                     heredes meos et predictos Monachos<lb/> super illa Calumpnia predicte terre de prestun quietos clamauerunt pro predicto
                     excambio . Hinc est quod ego <persName>Robertus</persName> de<lb/> Quinci dedi et concessi et hac karta mea confirmaui predictis Canonicis
                     prenominatam terram cum decem acris terre <cl type="holding">te<lb/>nendam in puram elemosinam et perpetuam de me et heredibus meis cum communi
                        pastura hominium meorum de<lb/> trauernent ad tantum terre pertinenti et cum libero exitu ad predictam communem
                        pasturam adeo libere et quiete et<lb/> honorifice sicut liberius et quietius et honorificentius aliqua elemosina in
                        Regno Regis scocie tenetur uel possidetur</cl> .</cl><lb/> <cl type="witnesses">His test<ex>ibus</ex> <persName>Symone</persName> Canonico de bethleem <persName>Will<ex>elm</ex>o</persName> Capellano de trauernent <persName>Ricardo Ridel</persName> <persName>Radulfo</persName> de Graam<lb/> pagano de hetleia . <persName>Will<ex>elm</ex>o</persName> de Graam <persName>Sim<ex>one</ex></persName> de tunderley . <persName>Dauid</persName> de lassewade <persName>Alvredo</persName> de cranestun <lb/> <persName>Alano</persName> et <persName>stephano</persName> de Phaeside . <persName>Laurentio</persName> et <persName>Roberto</persName> de boneire . et <persName>Bartholomeo</persName> burgensibus de<lb/> edenesburch . <persName>Gileberto</persName> clerico . <persName>Michaele flandrensi</persName> . et Aliis multis .</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all Holy Mother Church's sons, <cl type="intitulatio">Robert de Quincy</cl> <cl type="salutation">[sends] greeting</cl>.</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Let present and future know</cl> me to have given, conceded, and by this my charter made firm, to God, the church
                     of the Holyrood at Edinburgh, and to the canons serving
                     God in that place, one ploughgate of land and ten acres in
                     the territory of Tranent, in the direction of Fa'side, for
                     the exchange of that ploughgate of land at Preston which
                     the canons aforesaid claimed against me and the monks of
                     Newbattle, so that the aforenamed canons quitclaimed me
                     and my heirs and the aforesaid monks over that claim of
                     the aforesaid land of Preston in return for the aforesaid
                     exchange. That is why I, Robert de Quincy, gave, conceded,
                     and by this my charter made firm, to the aforesaid canons
                     the aforenamed land with ten acres of land, <cl type="holding">to be held in pure and everlasting alms of me and my heirs, with my men of
                     Tranent's common pasture pertaining to so much land, and
                     with free right of egress towards the aforesaid common
                     pasture; as freely, quitly, and honourably as any alms is
                     most freely, quitly, honourably held and possessed in the
                     kingdom of the king of Scotland</cl>.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">With these as witnesses: Simon, canon of Bethlehem; William, chaplain of
                  Tranent; Richard Ridel; Ralph of Graham; Payn of Hedley;
                  William of Graham; Simon of Thunderley; David of Lasswade;
                  Alured of Cranston; Alan and Stephen of Falside; Laurence and
                  Robert de Bonaire, and Bartholomew, burgesses of Edinburgh;
                  Gilbert the clerk; Michael Fleming; and many others.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>