<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-69">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 676</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 20:44:43.340057+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">69</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">69</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">69</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">70</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 676</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 676</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="approved">
      <change when="2022-10-31T20:44:43.340057+00:00" status="approved">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2022-10-31T20:44:43.340057+00:00" status="approved">transcription moa=69 status=reviewed modified=2022-10-31 20:44:43.32557+00 | translation moa=70 status=reviewed modified=2022-10-31 20:44:43.340057+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address"><cl type="intitulatio">Will<ex>elmu</ex>s de Lindesey</cl> . Omnibus sancte matris ecclesie filiis <cl type="salutation">salutem</cl> .</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Notum sit omnibus videntibus uel audientibus <lb/> has literas</cl> me quantum ad me spectat sicut ad dominum fundi . dedisse et hac Carta mea
                     confirmasse . deo et sancto <lb/> Cuthberto et monachis eiusdem sancti in Dunelmo seruientibus Ecclesiam de
                     Erceldona cum vna Carucata terre <lb/> et omnibus aliis pertinenciis suis in puram et perpetuam elemosinam . <cl type="holding">Quare volo quod iidem monachi predictam <lb/> ecclesiam et omnia <supplied>a</supplied>diacencia illi libere et quiete et integre possideant in perpetuum . Et multuram
                        suam <lb/> omnino quietam habeant</cl> . <cl type="warrandice">qui<supplied>cu</supplied>mque predictam ecclesiam de ipsis tenuerit promisi autem quod pro posse meo hanc <lb/> elemosina ad opus et utilitatem eclesie Dunelm’ manutenebo .</cl> </cl><cl type="witnesses">T<supplied>es</supplied>t'</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">William of Lindsay to all sons of Holy Mother Church sends <cl type="salutation">greeting</cl>. </cl><cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Let it be known to all who see or hear these letters</cl> that inasmuch as it pertains to me just as to the possessor I have given and by
                     this my charter made firm, to God, Saint Cuthbert, and to
                     the monks of the same saint serving God in Durham, the
                     Church of Earlston with one ploughgate of land and all its
                     other pertinents in pure and perpetual alms. <cl type="holding">Wherefore I will that the same monks should possess the aforesaid church and all
                     that belongs to it so freely, quitely and wholly for ever.
                     And they should have its multure entirely quit.</cl> <cl type="warrandice">And whosoever might hold the aforesaid church of them I have promised however
                     that according to my ability I shall maintain this alms
                     for the benefit and use of the church of Durham</cl>.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">As witness<ex>es</ex></cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>