<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-726">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of NRS GD55/293</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:21:22.229929+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">726</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">738</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">726</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">727</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/293</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>NRS GD55/293</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-04-07T08:21:22.229929+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-04-07T08:21:22.229929+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=726 status=live modified=2021-04-07 08:21:22.229929+00 | translation moa=727 status=live modified=2021-04-07 08:21:17.107951+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus sancte Matris Ecclesie filiis presentibus et futuris litteras istas
                  uisuris uel audituris <cl type="intitulatio">Adam de Hetun’<lb/> et Helena uxor eius</cl> <cl type="salutation">salutem in domino</cl> .</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Nouerit vniuersitas uestra</cl> quod nos coram Magistro Hugone Archidiac<ex>ono</ex> Glasgu<lb/>ensi . et Magistro Waltero decano de Teuidal’ et Domino Ada de bagath et multis
                     aliis uiris discretis clericis et laicis<lb/> affidauimus et tactis sacrosanctis iurauimus quod nos nunquam contra domum de
                     Melros de terris quas eidem domui uendidimus<lb/> in territorio de Molle querelam mouebimus . Nec alicui contra eandem domum de
                     predictis terris querelam mouere uolenti<lb/> consenciemus .</cl> <cl type="sealing">Ad maiorem uero huius rei securitatem hoc scriptum apposicione sigillorum
                  predicti Archidiaconi . et predicti decani .<lb/> et domini Ade de bagath’ vna cum apposictione sigilli nostri roborauimus .</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church present and future who shall view or hear
                  these letters <cl type="intitulatio">Adam of Heiton and Helen his wife</cl> <cl type="salutation">send greeting in the Lord</cl>.</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Your whole community should know</cl> that we have pledged our faith and sworn on holy relics in front of Master Hugh
                     the archdeacon of Glasgow and Master Walter the dean of
                     Tweeddale and the lord Adam of Bathgate and many other
                     distinguished men, clerk and lay, that we shall never move
                     a plaint against the monastic house of Melrose about the
                     lands that we sold to the same house; nor shall we give
                     willing consent to move a plaint against the same house
                     about the aforesaid lands.</cl> <cl type="sealing">For the greater security of this matter we have verified this writing by the
                  application of the seals of the aforesaid archdeacon and the
                  aforesaid dean and the lord Adam of Bathgate together with
                  the application of our own seal.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>