<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-730">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of NRS GD55/291</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-03-13 15:02:37.201135+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">730</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">742</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">730</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">731</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/291</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>NRS GD55/291</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="approved">
      <change when="2023-03-13T15:02:37.201135+00:00" status="approved">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2023-03-13T15:02:37.201135+00:00" status="approved">transcription moa=730 status=reviewed modified=2023-03-13 15:02:37.201135+00 | translation moa=731 status=reviewed modified=2023-03-13 15:02:37.184839+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="notification">Sciant omnes presentes et futuri quod</cl> <cl type="intitulatio">ego Will<ex>elmu</ex>s de Ridall’ miles</cl> <cl type="disposition">concessi et hac mea carta confirmaui deo et ecclesie beate<lb/> Marie de Melr<ex>os</ex> et monachis ibidem deo seruientibus totam terram per suas rectas diuisas . quam
                     Adam filius Ade de Dunelmo uen<lb/>didit eisdem monachis in territorio de Westlilliscliue . <cl type="holding">tenendam et habendam in liberam et perpetuam elemosinam cum omnibus<lb/> libertatibus et communibus asiamentis dicte uille de Weslill’ . adeo libere .
                        quiete . plene et pacifice sicut carta quam habent de<lb/> dicto Adam testatur</cl> . <cl type="warrandice">Ego uero et heredes mei totam dictam terram cum omnibus suis pertinenciis dictis
                     monachis contra omnes in<lb/>perpetuum warentizabimus ac defendemus</cl> .</cl> <cl type="sealing">In cuius rei testimonium ego pro me et heredibus meis presenti scripto sigillum<lb/> meum apponi feci .</cl> <cl type="witnesses">Testibus . Will<ex>elm</ex>o filio Alex’ de Westlill’ . Roberto de Banget’ . Will<ex>elm</ex>o de Bernardeby . et aliis .</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="notification">Let all people present and future know that</cl> <cl type="intitulatio">I William of Ryedale knight</cl> <cl type="disposition">have granted and by this my charter made firm to God and to the church of
                  Blessed Mary at Melrose and to the monks serving God in that
                  place the thowl land by its correct boundaries which Adam son
                  of Adam of Durham sold to the same monks in the territory of
                  West Lilliesleaf, <cl type="holding">to hold and to have in free and everlasting alms with all liberties and common
                     easements of the said toun of West Lilliesleaf as freely,
                     quitely, fully and peaceably as the charter which they
                     have from the said Adam bears witness.</cl> <cl type="warrandice">I and my heirs shall warrant and defend the said land with all its pertinents
                     for the said monks against all people for ever.</cl></cl> <cl type="sealing">In testimony of this matter I for myself and my heirs have caused my seal to be
                  applied to the present writing.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">As witnesses: William son of Alexander of West Lilliesleaf; Robert of Bathgate;
                  William of Bernoldby; and others .</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>