<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-770">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5963</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 21:10:50.709885+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">770</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">784</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">770</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">771</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5963</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5963</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="approved">
      <change when="2022-10-31T21:10:50.709885+00:00" status="approved">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2022-10-31T21:10:50.709885+00:00" status="approved">transcription moa=770 status=reviewed modified=2022-10-31 21:10:50.701297+00 | translation moa=771 status=reviewed modified=2022-10-31 21:10:50.709885+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">. Omnibus hoc scriptum visuris uel Audituris <cl type="intitulatio">Will<ex>elmu</ex>s filius Will<ex>elm</ex>i de scremerstona</cl><lb/> <cl type="salutation">salutem</cl>.</cl> <cl type="notification">Nouerit vniuersitas vestra</cl> <cl type="disposition">me ratum et gratum habuisse et hac presenti car<lb/>ta mea confirmasse Deo et sancto Cvhtberto priori et monachiis de Coldingham<lb/> Ibidem deo seruientibus et in perpetuum seruituris Donacionem et concessionem
                     Totius<lb/> terre quam Will<ex>elmu</ex>s de scremerstona pater meus habuit In villa et territorio de pren<lb/>dergest’ ex dono Roberti fili Roberti de prendergest sine alico retinemento<lb/> videlicet sex bouatas terre cum pertinentiis In territorio de prendergest illas
                     sili<lb/>cet Duas bouatas terre cum Tofto et Crofto quas Robertus Wynd tenuit. et illas<lb/> Duas bouatas terre quas Will<ex>elmu</ex>s filius Galfridi tenuit. et Illas Duas bouatas<lb/> terre quas Galfridus filius Waldeui tenuit. et Toftum et Croftum que aldanus<lb/> filius Waldeui tenuit. et Toftum et Croftum que Ricardus filius angnetis<lb/> tenuit. Quas dictas terras cum Domibus. Toftis et Croftis et cum omnibus suis<lb/> pertinentiis habuit ex dono Roberti fili Roberti de prendergest In villa et<lb/> territorio de prendergest’. <cl type="holding">Habendum et Tenendum dictis priori et conuentui de<lb/> Coldingham et eorum successoribus inperpetuum adeo libere. quiete et honorifice
                        In<lb/> omnibus sicut carta predicti Willelmi patris mei prefatis priori et Conuentui
                        de<lb/> Coldingham de prioratis terris cum omnibus pertinentiis confecta plenius<lb/> et melius testatur.</cl> <cl type="warrandice">Et ego Will<ex>elmu</ex>s filius Will<ex>elm</ex>i de scremerstona et heredes mei<lb/> prescriptam donacionem et Concessionem omnium predictarum terrarum de
                        prendergest’<lb/> cum omnibus suis pertinentiis infra villam et extra sepedictis priori et
                        monachis<lb/> de Coldingham et eorum successoribus contra omnes homines et feminas in
                        perpetuum<lb/> warantizabimus. adquietabimus. et defendemus</cl>.</cl> <cl type="sealing">In Cuius rei Testimonium<lb/> huic scripto sigillum meum appossui.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">Hiis Testibus domino Will<ex>elm</ex>o de lindesei<lb/> domino Will<ex>elm</ex>o de Mordingtona . domino Alano de swintona. alano filio suo. Thom<ex>a</ex><lb/> de Nesbyt<lb/> Ada filio suo. Roberto filio Gregorii de Coldingh<ex>am</ex>. Dauid de lumes<lb/>den. Gilberto de lumesden. Ada filio Ioh<ex>ann</ex>is de Eytona. Bertramo de Ristona. Ioh<ex>ann</ex>e<lb/> filio Ingerami. Roberto filio Reginaldi. patricio scoto. et ALIIS.</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all who shall view or hear this writing, <cl type="intitulatio">William, son of William of Scremerston,</cl> <cl type="salutation">sends greeting.</cl></cl> <cl type="notification">Know me, all of you</cl>, <cl type="disposition">to have ratified and made firm by this my present charter, to God and to Saint
                  Cuthbert, to the prior and monks of Coldingham serving God in
                  that place now and in the future, for ever, the donation and
                  grant of the whole of the land which my father, William of
                  Scremerston, had in the toun and territory of Prenderguest
                  out of the gift of Robert son of Robert of Prenderguest,
                  without any withholding; namely, six oxgangs of land with
                  pertinents in the territory of Prenderguest; that is, two
                  oxgangs of land with the toft and croft which Robert Wynd
                  held; and the two oxgangs which William son of Geoffrey held;
                  and the two oxgangs of land which Geoffrey son of Waldef
                  held; and the toft and croft which Haldan son of Waldef held;
                  and the toft and croft which Richard son of Agnes held. These
                  said lands, with dwellings, tofts, and crofts, and with all
                  their pertinents, I had out of the gift of Robert, son of
                  Robert of Prenderguest, in the toun and territory of
                  Prenderguest. <cl type="holding">For the said prior and convent of Coldingham and their successors to hold and to
                     have for ever, as freely, quitely, and honourably in all
                     things as the charter of the aforesaid William, my father,
                     drawn up for the prior and convent of Coldingham
                     concerning the lands of the priory with all pertinents,
                     fully and well bears witness.</cl> <cl type="warrandice">And I, William, son of William of Scremerston, and my heirs, shall warrant,
                     acquit, and defend the aforewritten donation and grant of
                     all the aforesaid lands of Prenderguest with all their
                     pertinents, within the toun and outside, for the
                     oft-mentioned prior and monks of Coldingham and their
                     successors against all men and women for ever.</cl></cl> <cl type="sealing">In testimony of this matter, I have applied my seal to this writing.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord William of Lindsay, the lord William of
                  Mordington, the lord Alan of Swinton, Alan his son, Thomas of
                  Nisbet, Adam his son, Robert son of Gregory of Coldingham,
                  David of Lumesden, Gilbert of Lumesden, Adam son of John of
                  Ayton, Bertram of Reston, John son of Ingram, Robert son of
                  Reginald, Patrick Scott, and others.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>