<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-784">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5956</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.792513+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">784</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">798</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">784</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">785</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5956</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5956</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="approved">
      <change when="2022-11-01T13:36:57.792513+00:00" status="approved">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2022-11-01T13:36:57.792513+00:00" status="approved">transcription moa=784 status=reviewed modified=2022-11-01 13:36:57.781324+00 | translation moa=785 status=reviewed modified=2022-11-01 13:36:57.792513+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">. Omnibus Christi fidelibus hoc scriptum visuris uel Audituris. <cl type="intitulatio">Bertramus de Ristona</cl> <cl type="salutation">salutem</cl>.</cl> <cl type="notification">Nou[er]it<lb/> vniuersitas uestra</cl> <cl type="disposition">me Concessisse. et hac presenti carta mea Confirmasse vendicionem. quietam
                  clamacionem.<lb/> et abiuractionem omnium terrarum quam Ricardus filius Henrici Cisoris de Dunelm’
                     vendidit domino<lb/> Ricardo Priori et Conuentui de Coldingham in villa et in territorio parue
                     Ristone cum omnibus pertinent<lb/>iis et exactis infra villam et extra sine aliquo Retinemento sicut planius et
                     plenius continetur<lb/> in carta confecta Quam dicti Prior et Conuentus habent de prefato Ricardo <cl type="holding">Habendam et Tenen<lb/>dam sepedictis priori et Conuentui de Coldingham et eorum successoribus in
                        perptuum libere. quiete. et honori<lb/>ffice in omnibus faciendo omne forinsecum seruicium pertinens ad dominum Regem
                        et ad dominum de Col<lb/>dingham quantum pertinet ad dimidiam carucatam terre in eadem villa. Reddendo
                        inde annuatim mihi<lb/> et heredibus meis duos solidos tantum pro omnibus que de dicta terra exigi
                        poterunt. ad duos term<lb/>inos anni. silicet duodecim denarios ad festum sancti Iohannis Baptiste. et
                        duodecim denarios ad festum<lb/> sancti Martini in hyeme.</cl></cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all Christ's faithful who shall view or hear this writing, <cl type="intitulatio">Bertram of Reston</cl> <cl type="salutation">sends greeting</cl>.</cl> <cl type="notification">Know me, all of you,</cl> <cl type="disposition">to have granted, and by this my present charter to have made firm, the sale,
                  quitclaim, and abjuration of all the lands which Richard son
                  of Henry Scissor of Durham sold to the lord Richard the
                  Prior, and the Convent of Coldingham, in the toun and in the
                  territory of Little Reston, with all pertinents and exactions
                  inside the toun and outside, without any withholding, just as
                  it is plainly and fully contained in the charter drawn up,
                  which the said Prior and Convent had from the aforementioned
                  Richard. <cl type="holding">For the oft-mentioned Prior and Convent of Coldingham, and their successors, to
                     have and to hold for ever; freely, quitely, and honourably
                     in all things; performing all forinsec service pertaining
                     to the lord King and to the lord of Coldingham, as much as
                     pertains to half a ploughgate of land in the same toun;
                     rendering thereupon to me and my heirs annually two
                     shillings only in return for all things which can be
                     exacted from the said land; at two terms of the year, that
                     is, twelve pence at the feast of Saint John the Baptist,
                     and twelve pence at the feast of Saint Martin in the
                     winter.</cl></cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>