<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-788">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5954</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.837177+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">788</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">802</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">788</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">789</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5954</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5954</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="approved">
      <change when="2022-11-01T13:36:57.837177+00:00" status="approved">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2022-11-01T13:36:57.837177+00:00" status="approved">transcription moa=788 status=reviewed modified=2022-11-01 13:36:57.825856+00 | translation moa=789 status=reviewed modified=2022-11-01 13:36:57.837177+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus Christi fidelibus Has literas visuris uel Audituris <cl type="intitulatio">Bertramus de parua Ristona</cl> <cl type="salutation">salutem</cl>.</cl> <cl type="notification">Nouerit vniueritas uestra</cl> <cl type="disposition">me intuitu caritatis et pro salute anime mee Antece<lb/>ssorum et successorum meorum Dedisse. et Concesisse . et hac presenti carta mea
                     Confirmasse Deo et sancto Cvhtberto priori et monachis de
                     Coldingh<ex>am</ex> ibidem deo seruientibus et in<lb/>perpetuum seruituris vnam dimidiam carucatam terre In Campo et Territorio parue
                     Ristone in liberam. puram. et perpetuam elemosinam silicet
                     Duas accras terre et dimidiam In Tofto et Crofto in quo
                     sedi Aliquando tempore patris mei. et Totam terram meam ad
                     Ralfesaccres et Thorn. et vnam accram terre propinquiorem
                     prati Rogeri<lb/> et Ricardi fili Iosep Hunderhecsyde extendentem se uersus occidentem. et Totam
                     terram meam iacentem in mora ad australi parte de
                     Blackechest’. et Totam<lb/> terram meam ad Blakechloeshefed excepta terra tantum Dauid de Drilton’. et Totam
                     terram meam in Blackelawesflat. et omnem terram meam in
                     Wilkedenflat<lb/> excepta terra tantum Dauid de Drilton’. et Totam terram meam in orientali parte
                     de Stublisyde . et Totum Dominicum meum iacens in Duabus
                     partibus in Hebr<lb/>andes castel. et vnam accram terre ad Grengate uersus occidentem. et Totam
                     terram meam in Thyrstlislad quam Patricius filius Wtredi
                     de me quondam tenuit. et<lb/> omnem friscam meam desuper iacentem. et Totam terram meam quam Ada Cocus quondam
                     de me tenuit exceptis quatuor accriis terre quas Prior
                     Dunelmensis<lb/> habet de Eadem terra in Eadem villa. et Totam terram meam in Tepermer. et
                     quatuor accras terre et dimidiam in occidentali parte ad
                     Morcroc. Omnes<lb/> istas terras superecriptas Dedi et hac presenti carta mea Confirmaui prefatis
                     priori et monachis de Coldingh<ex>am</ex> pro vna dimidia carucata terre in liberam. puram.<lb/> et perpetuam elemosinam. Renuncians in hoc facto pro me et heredibus meiis omni
                     Iuris Ausilio canonici et ciuilis quod Dicti prior et
                     monachi de Coldingh<ex>am</ex><lb/> nullo tempore pro hac pura. et perpetua elemosina in foro laicali trahantur nec
                     vexentur. In moris et maricis. In pratis et pasturis. In
                     petariis et turbariis. In<lb/> viis et semitis. et In omnibus aliis assiamentis ad Eandem pertinentibus terram
                     infra villam et extra. <cl type="holding">Habend<ex>as</ex> et Tenend<ex>as</ex> Dictis priori et monachis de Coldin<lb/>gh<ex>am</ex> de me et heredibus meiis inperpetuum adeo libere. quiete. et honorifice In
                        omnibus sicut aliqua elemosina infra Regnum Scocie
                        liberius aut quiecius tenetur<lb/> uel possidetur.</cl> <cl type="warrandice">Ego uero Bertramus et heredes mei predictam dimidiam carucatam terre cum Dicto
                     tofto et Crofto et cum omnibus supradictis particulis
                     terre<lb/> et cum omnibus suis pertinenciis infra villam et extra sepedictis priori et
                        monachis de Coldingham contra omnes homines et feminas
                        in perpetuum warantizabimus. adquie<lb/>tabimus. et deffendemus.</cl></cl> <cl type="sealing">In Cuius Rei Testimonium huic scripto sigillum meum appossui.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">Hiis Testibus Domino Will<ex>elm</ex>o de Mordington<ex>a</ex>. Domino Alano de<lb/> Swyntona. Thoma de Nesbyt. Dauid de Lumesden. Roberto filio Gregorii de Coldingh<ex>am</ex>. Ada de Prendergest’. Patricio Scoto. Ada filio Iohannis de Super<lb/>ioriaytona. Gregorio de Bethyoc. Gilberto de Lumesden. Roberto filio Reginaldi.
                     Rogero filio Ade de magna Ristona et ALIIS.</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all Christ's faithful who shall view or hear these letters, <cl type="intitulatio">Bertram of Little Reston</cl> <cl type="salutation">sends greeting</cl>.</cl> <cl type="notification">Know me, all of you,</cl> <cl type="disposition">out of charity and for the salvation of my own soul, and of my ancestors' and
                  successors' <ex>souls</ex>, to have given, and granted, and to have made firm by this my present charter,
                     to God and to St Cuthbert, to the prior, and to the monks
                     of Coldingham serving God in that place now and in the
                     future, for ever, a half-ploughgate of land in the
                     cultivated fields and territory of Little Reston, in pure
                     and everlasting alms; that is, two-and-a-half acres of
                     land in the toft and croft in which I settled at some time
                     in my father's day; and all my land at <ex>Ralfesaccres</ex> and <ex>Thorn</ex>; and one acre of land nearest the meadow belonging to Roger and Richard, sons
                     of Joseph Hunderhecsyde, extending westwards; and all my
                     land lying in the moor, from the south side of <ex>Blackechest'</ex>; and all my land at <ex>Blackechloeshefed</ex>, saving only the land of David of Drilton; and all my land in <ex>Blackelawesflat</ex>; and all my land in <ex>Wilkedenflat</ex>, saving only that of David of Drilton; and all my land on the eastern side of <ex>Stublisyde</ex>; and my whole demesne lying on the two sides of <ex>Hebrandes Castle</ex>; and one acre of land at <ex>Grengate</ex> towards the west; and my whole land in <ex>Thyrslislad</ex> which Patrick son of Uhtred once held of me, and all my uncultivated <ex>land</ex> lying thereon; and my whole land which Adam Cook once held of me, except for
                     four acres of land which the Prior of Durham had of the
                     same in the same toun; and all my land in <ex>Tepermer</ex>; and four-and-a-half acres of land on the western side at Morcroc. All these
                     lands written above I have given and made firm by this, my
                     present charter, to the aforementioned prior and monks of
                     Coldingham, in return for a half-ploughgate of land, in
                     free, pure, and everlasting alms, renouncing by this
                     action, for my own part and for my heirs, every aid of
                     canon and civil law, in order that the said prior and
                     monks of Coldingham at no time for this pure and
                     everlasting alms may be brought to a lay court nor be
                     harassed; in moors and marshes, in meadows and pastures,
                     in peataries and turbaries, in roads and paths, and in all
                     other easements pertaining to the same land, within the
                     toun and outside it; <cl type="holding">for the said prior and monks of Coldingham to have and to hold of me and my
                     heirs for ever, as freely, quitely, and honourably in all
                     things as any alms within the kingdom of Scotland is
                     freely or quitely held or possessed.</cl> <cl type="warrandice">And I, Bertram, and my heirs, the aforesaid half-ploughgate of land, with the
                     said toft and croft, and with all the above-said portions
                     of land, and with all their pertinents within the toun and
                     outside it, to the oft-mentioned prior and monks of
                     Coldingham shall warrant, acquiet, and defend against all
                     men and women for ever.</cl></cl> <cl type="sealing">In testimony of this matter, I have applied my seal to this writing.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord William of Mordington; the lord Alan of Swinton;
                  Thomas of Nisbet; David of Lumsdaine; Robert son of Gregory
                  of Coldingham; Adam of Prenderguest; Patrick Scot; Adam son
                  of John of Over Ayton; Gregory of Beoch; Gilbert of
                  Lumsdaine; Robert son of Reginald; Roger son of Adam of Great
                  Reston; and others.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>