<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-854">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of TNA DL 25/88</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-04 16:29:49.581153+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">854</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">876</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">854</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">855</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>The National Archives</repository>
            <idno>DL 25/88</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>TNA DL 25/88</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <change when="2021-04-04T16:29:49.581153+00:00" status="published">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2021-04-04T16:29:49.581153+00:00" status="published">transcription moa=854 status=live modified=2021-04-04 16:29:47.686203+00 | translation moa=855 status=live modified=2021-04-04 16:29:49.581153+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus hoc scriptum visurus uel audituris <cl type="intitulatio">Helena filia Rogeri quondam dicti porter</cl> <cl type="salutation">salutem in domino sempiternam</cl></cl><lb/> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Noueritis me</cl> in maxima necessitate mea vendidisse et concessisse domino meo domino Roberto de
                     Brus domino vallis Anan<lb/>die vnam grangiam cum acra super quam fundatur que quidem stat ex opposito
                     contra domum quondam<lb/> Patricii Scheltun ad capud ville de Anand per quod itur ad furcas pro quadam
                     summa pecunie quam dictus<lb/> dominus Robertus de Brus michi in maxima necessitate mea premanibus pacauit . de
                     qua quidem pecunia me teneo<lb/> contentam et pacatam . <cl type="holding">Tenendum et habendum dicto domino . Roberto de Brus et heredibus suis uel suis
                     assingnatis libere qui<lb/>ete pacifice et honorifice absque ulla calumpnia mei uel heredum meorum</cl> . Reddendo inde annuatim ipse uel here<lb/>des sui Luminari sancte Marie de Anand vnum denarium ad Natale domini pro omni
                     seruitio et seculari demanda . <cl type="warrandice">Ego<lb/> vero et heredes mei dictam grangiam cum acra super quam fundatur contra
                        quoscumque warantizabimus in perpetuum<lb/> et defendemus</cl> .</cl> <cl type="sealing">In cuius rei testimonium huic scripto sigillum meum apposui</cl> <cl type="witnesses">hiis testibus . Domino Roberto de Heriz<lb/> Radulfo de camera constabulario et multis aliis .</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all who shall view or hear this writing <cl type="intitulatio">Helen the daughter of the late Roger called Porter </cl><cl type="salutation">wishes eternal salvation in the Lord</cl>.</cl> <cl type="disposition">Know me in my great need to have sold and granted to my lord Robert de Brus the
                  lord of Annandale one grange with the acre upon which it is
                  built and which stands opposite the dwelling of a certain
                  Patrick of Shelton at the head of the toun of Annan on the
                  way to the gallows in return for which the said Robert de
                  Brus has paid to me a certain amount of money as an advance
                  in my great need and in respect of which money I remain
                  satisfied and paid. For the said lord Robert de Brus and his
                  heirs or his assigns to hold and to have freely, quitly,
                  peaceably, and honourably, without any claim on me or my
                  heirs. He or his heirs are annually to render for it one
                  penny at Christmas for the lighting of St Mary’s at Annan in
                  return for every service and secular demand. <cl type="warrandice">I and my heirs shall warrant and protect for ever against anyone the same grange
                     with the acre upon which it is built</cl>.</cl> <cl type="sealing">In testimony of this matter I have applied my seal to this writing.</cl> <cl type="witnesses">With these witnesses, the lord Robert de Heriz, Ralph de Camera the constable,
                  and many others.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>