<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="moa-972">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcription and Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 732</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Exported from Models of Authority data</resp>
          <name>tei_exporter</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 11:12:46.014679+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Models of Authority</publisher>
        <idno type="textcontentxml">972</idno>
        <idno type="textcontent">1000</idno>
        <idno type="transcription_textcontentxml">972</idno>
        <idno type="translation_textcontentxml">973</idno>
        <availability>
          <p>Status unknown. Exported for research and migration workflows.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 732</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 732</summary>
          </msContents>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="approved">
      <change when="2022-11-01T11:12:46.014679+00:00" status="approved">Exported by standalone tei_exporter.</change>
      <change when="2022-11-01T11:12:46.014679+00:00" status="approved">transcription moa=972 status=reviewed modified=2022-11-01 11:12:46.014679+00 | translation moa=973 status=reviewed modified=2022-11-01 11:12:46.003973+00</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="transcription">
        <p><cl type="address">Omnibus Christi fidelibus ad quos prefatas scriptum peruenerit  <cl type="intitulatio">Walterus Olifard</cl> <cl type="salutation">Salutem in domino</cl> .</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Nouerit Vniuersitas uestra</cl><lb/> me confirmasse Deo et Sancto Chudberto Et Sancte Ebbe Et Monachis Dunelmensibus
                     apud Coldingham Deo seruientibus donacionem<lb/> illam quam Clarebaldus de Esseby fecit deo et sancto Chudberto et sancte Ebbe et
                     monachis de Coldingham ibidem deo seruientibus de duabus
                     piscariis super Twedam . scilicet de vna piscaria sub
                     Gardino de fissewich’ . et alia apud Schipeswel .<lb/> sicut continetur in carta quam dictus Clarebaldus dedit dictis monachis de
                     dictis piscariis . quas ego dedi et concessi et<lb/> carta mea confirmaui dicto Clarebaldo et heredibus suis pro homagio et seruicio
                     suo</cl> <cl type="sealing">Et in huius confirmacionis<lb/> testimonium presenti scripto sigillum meum apposui .</cl></p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
        <p><cl type="address">To all Christ's faithful to whom the present writing shall have come, <cl type="intitulatio">Walter Oliphant</cl> <cl type="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</cl>.</cl> <cl type="disposition"><cl type="notification">Know all of you that</cl> I have confirmed to God, Saint Cuthbert, Saint Ebbe, and to the monks of Durham
                     serving God at Coldingham, the donation which Clarebald of
                     Ashby made to God, Saint Cuthbert, Saint Ebbe, and to the
                     monks of Coldingham serving God in that place, of two
                     fisheries on the Tweed, that is, one fishery below the
                     garden at Fishwick, and the other at Shipswell, as it is
                     comprised in the charter which the said Clarebald gave to
                     the said monks for the said fisheries, which I gave,
                     granted, and by my charter made firm to the said Clarebald
                     and his heirs in return for their homage and service.</cl> <cl type="sealing">And as witness of this confirmation I have applied my seal to the present
                  writing.</cl></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>