<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Add. Ch. 76697</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-04 14:26:58.109502+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Add. Ch. 76697</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William, by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts, officials, and
                     other worthy men of his entire land <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting. </seg></seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have conceded, and by this my charter to have made firm, to Orm son of
                  Hugh and his heirs the abbey of Abernethy with all its just
                  pertinents and rights justly pertaining to the same abbey of
                  Abernethy as it was in the year and on the day that King
                  David my grandfather was alive and dead; in wood and plain,
                  in meadows and pastures, moors and waters, roads and paths,
                  millponds and mills; except for 10 pounds’ worth of land that
                  I gave to Henry Revel with the daughter of the foresaid Orm. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For him and his heirs to hold of me and my heirs in feu and heritage, free and
                     quit from all services and customs except for common aid,
                     common army, and common work; with soke and sake, with
                     toll and team and infangthief, yet so that he shall not
                     have gallows nor pit except in two places, that is, at
                     Abernethy, and at Inverarity.</seg> With 20 pounds of silver to be rendered to me and my heirs from there, that is,
                     10 pounds at the feast of Saint John the Baptist, and 10
                     pounds at the feast of Saint Brigid. I also will that his
                     own men of Fife and Gowrie come to the pit at Abernethy;
                     for his other lands, however, let them come to the pit at
                     Inverarity</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Matthew bishop of Aberdeen; Andrew bishop of Caithness; Hugh my
                  chaplain; Earl Duncan; Earl Gilbert; Hugh Giffard; Ness son
                  of William; Geoffrey de Malville; Walter of Berkeley; William
                  de Mortimer; William of Lindsay.</seg> At Perth.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>