<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Add. Ch. 76747</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:45:08.001957+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Add. Ch. 76747</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Holy Mother Church's sons, those present as well as those to come after, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alan son of Ælfsige</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">[sends] greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all those to whose notice these letters might come know</seg> me to have conceded and to have given, and by this my present charter to have
                     made firm, to God and to the church of St Mary at Melrose,
                     and to the monks serving God in that same place, for the
                     sake of my father's soul and my mother's, and for the sake
                     of the souls of all my predecessors and successors, and
                     for the salvation of my own soul and of all my heirs' and
                     ancestors' [souls], in pure and everlasting alms one stone
                     of wax to provide light in front of the altar of St Mary
                     for ever. This stone of wax I and my heirs shall each year
                     give at Pentecost to God and the house of Melrose, that is
                     to say, namely in respect of the rent of that land which
                     Owen son of Gillemichael and his heirs hold of me and my
                     heirs in perpetual tenure in the toun of Thirlestane ...
                     whosoever afterwards ... shall have held.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these as witnesses: Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow; Simon, archdeacon of
                  Glasgow; Aldred, parson of Lauder; Roger le Cras; Ralph le
                  Cras; Peter de la Haig; Thomas of Warwick; William ... T. the
                  butler; William fitz Payn; Henry fitz Baldwin; William the
                  clerk.</seg> </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>