<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Add. Ch. 76699</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:44:23.549325+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Add. Ch. 76699</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Holy Mother Church's sons intending to examine the present writing, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Roger, by the grace of God a humble servant of the church of St Andrew,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">[sends] greeting in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know us, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have given and granted and by the present charter to have made firm to
                  William son of Adam of Nevay, at the presentation of the same
                  A<ex>dam</ex>, the church of [Meathie] Lour with all its just pertinents in free, pure, and
                     perpetual alms. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will and firmly instruct that the same William hold and possess the
                     aforenamed church freely, quitly, and honourably, just as
                     any parson most freely, quitly, and honourably holds and
                     possesses his church in our diocese.</seg> Reserving episcopal rights.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Henry, abbot of Arbroath; Thomas, prior of St Andrews; Archibald,
                  abbot of Scone; Hugh, prior of Restenneth; Master Ranulf,
                  official; Master Isaac; Master William of Lyne; Richard and
                  Richard, chaplains; John of London; Richard le Megre; William
                  Wyville; John of Bearford; Hugh the steward; Ralph, priest of
                  Glamis; Baldwin the Scot; John, dean of Angus; Simon, dean of
                  Perth; John, dean of Kinghorn; and a great many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>