<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Add. Ch. 76700</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-02-02 22:04:34.764905+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Add. Ch. 76700</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, king of the Scots,</seg> to all worthy men of his entire land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">us to have given, conceded, and by this our charter to have made firm, to Thomas
                  d'Aunay, Burntscarthgreen, Auchencrieff, and Dargavel, by
                  their own right boundaries by which William son of Derman
                  held those lands, that is, the land which William son of the
                  same William son of Derman has quitclaimed to us by staff and
                  baton in our court at Dumfries for himself and his heirs. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For the said Thomas d'Aunay and his own heirs to hold of us and our heirs in feu
                     and heritage, in lands and waters, in meadows and
                     pastures, in moors and marshes, in ponds and mills, and
                     with all other things belonging by right to the foresaid
                     lands, with gallows and ditch, with soke and sake, with
                     toll and team, and infangtheif, freely and quitely, fully
                     and honourably, by a quarter of the service of one knight.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: William del Bois, chancellor; Thomas of Stirling, archdeacon of
                  Glasgow; Roger Avenel; Robert son of Robert of Roos; John of
                  Maxwell; Peter de Valognes; William Bisset; William Avenel.</seg> At Ed[inburgh?] on the <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">29th day of September, in the tenth year of the lord king's reign</seg>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>