<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Add. Ch. 66569</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-07-20 09:56:38.271015+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Add. Ch. 66569</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ’s faithful people who shall view or hear this writing, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Patrick son of William</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">wishes everlasting salvation in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">May you all know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">the lord abbot and convent of Scone to have made satisfaction to me in respect
                  of all manner of debts in which they were obliged to me, by
                  written deeds as well as by any other contract, in respect of
                  the livestock and fermes of Blair, and all other agreements,
                  loans, or any other contracts; and to have renounced for
                  myself and my heirs all loans which I have or could have in
                  relation to them, in respect of any contract of the
                  aforesaid. Wherefore I will that if any instrument be found
                  concerning any contract entered into between us, and
                  especially in respect of Blair, it be of no value or force.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter I have applied my seal to this writing together with
                  the seal of the venerable father, Geoffrey, bishop of
                  Dunkeld.</seg> Given at Cargill on the Day of Saint Augustine, bishop of the English, in the
                  Year of Grace 1246. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: the lord Malcolm, precentor of Dunkeld; Master John of Everley,
                  canon of Dunkeld; the lord Peter of Cargill; William of
                  Clunie; Simon the clerk, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>