<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.18</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:30:25.769453+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.18</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William, by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to all worthy men of his entire land <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">[sends] greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">in my presence, and with bishops, barons, and many other worthy men of my realm
                  being present, on the Day of Saint Luke the Evangelist, by
                  the oaths of sworn men, perambulation was made and the
                  limitation of the boundaries fixed between the monks of
                  Melrose and the men of Wedale concerning the pasture of my
                  forest that my ancestors and I gave to the said monks of
                  Melrose in pure and everlasting alms. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">The aforesaid sworn men indeed swore an oath in front of me and my worthy men,
                     that my forest, which is the pasture of the aforesaid
                     monks of Melrose, extends to the road that leads to the
                     western side of the church of Wedale and as far as the
                     stream which is called Fasseburn</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will, grant and instruct that the said monks peaceably hold and
                     possess the whole pasture aforementioned with all its
                     easements and liberties as far as the boundaries
                     aforementioned in pure, free and everlasting alms, as
                     their own property and their successors', so that none
                     shall have common between them or with them within the
                     aforementioned boundaries of the said pasture, saving to
                     myself and my heirs wild beasts, birds and game within the
                     said forest</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses Richard bishop of St Andrews, Jocelin bishop of Glasgow, John of
                  Kelso, Osbert abbot of Jedburgh, Earl David, Richard de
                  Morville the constable and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>