<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.25</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:28:30.357351+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.25</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William de Morville, constable of Scotland</seg>, to all his own friends and worthy men, present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have given, conceded, and by this my present charter to have made firm, to
                  James of Loudon the land of Loudon, by these boundaries, that
                  is to say, from Polbaith to the boundaries of Strathaven, and
                  from the water which is called Irvine as far as the
                  boundaries of Eaglesham. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For him and his heirs to hold outside the forest, and quit of forest, of me and
                     my heirs in feu and heritage, in wood and plain, in
                     meadows and pastures, in roads and paths, in monastery and
                     mills, and in all other things rightfully pertaining to
                     the aforesaid land, freely, quitly, fully, wholly, and
                     honourably by the service of one knight</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Christina my spouse; Godfrey de Ros; Robert son of
                  Warnebald; Stephen son of Richard; William Mansell; Alan of
                  Thirlestane; Peter de la Haig; Henry de Sinclair; Ivo de
                  Vieuxpont; Duncan son of Earl Duncan; Richard fitz Gilbert;
                  Arthur of Ardrossan; Robert of Logan; Reginald de Ros; James
                  his brother; Richard de Morville; Richard de Néhou; Elias son
                  of Hugh; Alan de Sinclair; Thomas English; William son of
                  John; Herbert, and William his brother; Richard of Whitton;
                  John the clerk.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>