<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xv.21</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:50:44.667952+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xv.21</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">M<ex>alcolm</ex>, king of Scotland,</seg> to bishops, abbots, justices, earls, sheriffs, barons, officials, and all worthy
                     men of his entire kingdom and of the Honour of Huntingdon,
                     clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let those to come after as well as those present know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have given, conceded, and by this my charter to have made firm, to God,
                  Saint Mary, and the monks of the Cistercian Order who are at
                  the house of Sartis, in everlasting alms for the construction
                  of an abbey, for the salvation of my own soul and my
                  predecessors' and successors' [souls], the whole of Sawtry,
                  with all its pertinents in wood and plain, in meadows and
                  waters, and pastures and marshes, and all other property,
                  just as David the king, my grandfather of good memory, held
                  it, and just as Henry, king of England, has now returned to
                  me with my other rights of Huntingdon. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will and firmly command that the aforesaid monks have and hold it of
                     me and my heirs, just as my own alms; well, in peace,
                     honourably, quitly, and free from all temporal exaction
                     and service, just as other monks of the same order in my
                     kingdom most freely and quitly have and hold their alms.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these as witnesses: Herbert, bishop of Glasgow; Waldef, abbot of Melrose;
                  Arnold, abbot of Roxburgh; Osbert, abbot of Jedburgh; Walter
                  the chancellor; Adam the chaplain of Roxburgh; Nicholas the
                  clerk; William my brother; Walter fitz Alan; Richard de
                  Morville; Ranulf de Soulis; William de Morville; William de
                  Somerville; Liulf son of Maccus; Orm son of Eilaf; David
                  Oliphant; Robert Frebern; David de Boeville; H<ex>enry</ex> de Percy.</seg> At Roxburgh.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>