<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.13</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:16:22.509188+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.13</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W(illiam), by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, officials, and all worthy men of
                     his entire land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me, for the sake of my own soul and for the souls of my father and my mother,
                  and of my grandfather King David, and of my brothers and
                  sisters, and predecessors and successors, to have conceded
                  and given to God, to the church of St Mary at Melrose, and
                  the monks of Rievaulx serving God in that place, in
                  everlasting and free alms, the land of Melrose, and the land
                  of Eildon, and the land of Darnick, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to possess freely and honourably in perpetual tenure.</seg> In addition, know me to have given and conceded to them their easements
                     throughout my whole forest of Selkirk and of Traquhair,
                     that is to say, firewood, timber, and pannage, for their
                     own use wherever they will the better and more usefully be
                     able to find for themselves. In addition I give and make
                     firm the entire pasture by the River Gala towards them,
                     that is, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">from the eastern side, as the same river flows, as far as the limits of Wedale,
                     and from there by the right marches of Richard de
                     Morville's land, that is, from the Gala as far as the
                     Leader</seg>, and the whole usage of the wood within the aforenamed boundaries for their own
                     employment as might be necessary for them. Furthermore,
                     fishing also in the waters of the Tweed, anywhere inside
                     their boundaries, as much on my side of the river as on
                     their side. And in addition to the things mentioned above
                     I have given and conceded to them, as an augmentation,
                     Gattonside by these boundaries, namely, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">as the river fall into the Tweed, and so upwards to the Fauhope burn which falls
                     into the Leader, and so upwards by the same burn and thus
                     across the moor as far as the Rae burn which falls into
                     the Allan, and so following the same river Allan as far as
                     the Tweed.</seg> Besides all the aforenamed things I have given and conceded to them on the lower
                     side of Colmslie a place for building one cow-shed for one
                     hundred cows, and one cattle-fold. I have given and
                     conceded to them the fishery of Selkirk, and one net in
                     Berwick Stream from my two nets which I have in Berwick
                     Stream, so freely and quitly as I myself held for my own
                     use. All these aforementioned things I give and concede to
                     the monks of Melrose, and make firm by this my charter, in
                     everlasting and free alms, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">and I will and instruct that they may hold all the things mentioned above as
                     freely and quitly, fully and honourably as the charter of
                     my brother King Malcolm bears witness and affirms</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these as witnesses: Walter Bidun, chancellor; Earl Duncan; Richard de
                  Morville, constable; Richard Comyn, justice; Robert Avenel;
                  Walter of Berkeley, chamberlain; William de Somerville;
                  Walter Ryedale; Hugh the king's clerk; William the chaplain;
                  Robert the chaplain; Hugh the chancellor's clerk; Master
                  John; Earl Waldef; Walter son of Alan, steward; Alan his son;
                  Thomas de Muschamp; William de la Haye; Ralph Ruffus.</seg> At Roxburgh.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>