<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.4</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:33:03.580369+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.4</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to all sheriffs of his entire land <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">[sends] greeting</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">We command you, strictly ordering that, when the monks or brethren of Melrose
                  approach you complaining about any malefactors, who have by
                  stealth stolen or led away their work animals or livestock,
                  you should prosecute the pleas of the monks and brethren as
                  though it were our own plea, making the appeals and answers
                  against their malefactors according to the nature of their
                  plea, and on our behalf finding, if by chance there shall be
                  need, a champion for the same monks and brethren, until the
                  plea of the same be certainly concluded, by the scrutiny of
                  discerning men, or by mediating an agreement. When the plea
                  of the oft-mentioned monks or brethren shall have been
                  concluded, as it has already been said, and their malefactors
                  have been convicted or as good as convicted in their own
                  wickedness; we will that their working animals or livestock
                  which have been removed from the same shall fully be restored
                  to the monks or brethren from the property of their
                  malefactors. And the forfeitures and losses into which the
                  said malefactors or their pledges shall by their their
                  offences have fallen, are entirely devolved to our authority
                  according to what the law shall have decreed. We have
                  rightfully taken the brethren of Melrose, and the men of the
                  same, bearers of the presents, under our firm peace and
                  protection, strictly forbidding that anyone shall unlawfully
                  cause or attempt to cause them any injury, annoyance or harm,
                  on pain of our full forfeiture.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Thomas, earl of Atholl; John of Maxwell, chancellor; Ingram de
                  Balliol; Robert the chaplain; David the marischal; Donald of
                  Mar; Thomas de Normanville; William of Bunkle. At Melrose on
                  the nineteenth day of March, in the seventeenth year of the
                  reign of the lord king.</seg> </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>