<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.2</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:32:20.26286+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.2</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to all worthy men of his entire land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">[sends] greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">us, for the sake of divine love, to have given, conceded, and by our charter to
                  have made firm, to God, the church of St Mary at Melrose, and
                  to the abbot and monks serving God in that same place, a
                  quarter of Dunscore in Nithsdale, that is to say, that
                  quarter which is nearest the land of the canons of Dercongal,
                  by its right marches and with all its just pertinents; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the same monks to hold in free, pure, and perpetual alms, as freely and
                     quitly, fully and honourably, as any alms in our kingdom
                     from our own gift or of any of our ancestors is held and
                     possessed most freely and quitly, fully and honourably; so
                     that the aforesaid monks should have a pittance every year
                     on the eve of St Bartholomew the apostle from the rent of
                     the said land</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Master Matthew the chancellor; Walter Oliphant, justiciar of
                  Lothian; Walter fitz Alan, the steward; Patrick son of the
                  earl; Walter Comyn; Ingram de Balliol; Henry son of the Earl;
                  David the marischal; Thomas son of Ranulf; David Comyn.</seg> At Belford on the eighteenth day of March in the fifteenth year of the reign of
                  the lord king.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>