<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.12</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:39:21.073643+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.12</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">D<ex>avid</ex>, by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to bishops, abbots, earls, justices, barons, sheriffs, provosts, officials,
                     and all his sworn men, french and English, clerk and lay,
                     as well future as present, of his entire land, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have given and conceded, to God and the church of St Mary at Haddington,
                  Clerkington in perpetual alms, with its right marches on
                  either side of the water, just as William de Graham, Durand
                  the sheriff, Richard the clerk, Osbert the prior of
                  Edinburgh, Mael Bethad of Liberton, and Gillanders son of
                  Oggu, led the way and went around; afterwards, Thorald the
                  archdeacon set the bounds with me at Peebles, even also as it
                  was measured earlier. I concede to the aforesaid church one
                  full toft near the church in the toun of Haddington, and all
                  teinds and ecclesiastical revenues from the whole of
                  Haddingtonshire, as much from mills as from other properties. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">I will and strictly command that the aforesaid church may hold and have the
                     aforenamed land of Clerkington alone, and quit of me and
                     of the thane, and of all others who may have held the
                     aforesaid land of Haddington; of me and my heirs, and also
                     of their heirs; and also all other revenues and customs,
                     in teinds and alms, so freely, honourably, quitly, and
                     fully as any alms in my entire land can best, most fully,
                     honourably, and quitly be given and conceded.</seg> All these aforenamed alms I give, and by my charter make firm, for the sake of
                     my soul, and of my father's, and my mother's, and the
                     souls of my predecessors and successors.</seg> Henry my son agrees and consents. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">And witnessing this same matter: Robert, bishop of St Andrews; John, bishop of
                  Glasgow; Gregory, bishop of Dunkeld; Geoffrey, abbot of
                  Dunfermline; Denis, prior of Scone; Roger, prior of
                  Dunfermline; Robert de Sigillo; Duncan the earl; Hugh de
                  Morville; Malise the earl; Edward the constable; Leod of
                  Brechin; Ranulf de Soulis; Roger, Bishop Robert's nephew.</seg> At Perth on the 18th kalends of July [14 June].</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>