<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.11</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:37:29.468545+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.11</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">A(lexander), by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to all worthy men of his entire land <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">[sends] greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know us</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have given, conceded, and by this our charter to have made firm, to God,
                  blessed Mary at Melrose, and to the monks serving God in that
                  place now and for ever in the future, Burntscarthgreen,
                  Auchencrieff, and Dargavel; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the same monks to hold and to have for ever, of us and our heirs, by their
                     right marches and with all things rightfully belonging to
                     them, in wood and plain, in lands and waters, in meadows
                     and pastures, in moors and marshes, in ponds and mills,
                     and with all other things rightfully belonging to the said
                     lands, freely, quitly, fully, and honourably, performing
                     as much forinsec service in aids as pertains to the
                     quarter of one knight. From army service, however, and all
                     other forinsec service we entirely quitclaim them.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">We shall warrant the aforesaid lands to the aforesaid monks of Melrose for ever
                     against all men.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: P(atrick), earl of Dunbar; Walter Oliphant, justiciar of Lothian;
                  Walter Bisset; Bernard Fraser; David the marischal; William
                  of Brechin; Thomas de Normanville.</seg> At Selkirk on the sixteenth day of July, in the twenty-third year of the reign
                  of the lord king.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>