<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.28</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:52:49.865711+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.28</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all sons of Holy Mother Church know, those present as well as those to come
                  after, that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">when a dispute at law was initiated and deliberated for a long time in the
                  chapter-house of East Lothian between lord John the prior and
                  the community of St Andrews on the one side, and the master
                  and nuns of Haddington on the other, over various teinds,
                  great and small, claimed on either side, that is to say, when
                  the teinds of a ploughgate of land in the territory of
                  Athelstaneford which once belonged to the territory of Drem,
                  and the teinds of two oxgangs of land contained in the old
                  garden of Stevenson, and the teinds of that land which lies
                  between the old garden and the toun of Haddington, and the
                  teinds of half of that land next to the mill of Stevenson,
                  and the teinds of the crofts belonging to certain burgesses
                  of Haddington, which the master and nuns were then holding,
                  were claimed on the part of the prior and community of St
                  Andrews from the aforementioned nuns; and on the part of the
                  master and nuns of Haddington, the small teinds of Byres, and
                  the cottaries of Byres and of Barney were demanded in law;
                  and the dispute in law over the aforementioned claims on both
                  sides having been lawfully asserted, and the witnesses on
                  either side having been produced and examined, and evidence
                  having been published and inspected, and with allegations on
                  either side having been heard and understood, and having
                  inspected the instruments of the same, when nothing remained
                  except for the judgment to be rendered, at length after many
                  labours and undue troubles, the parties through their agents
                  lawfully constituted to settle and complete [the case] on
                  Saturday after St Peter’s Chains in the church of Lauder in
                  the year of grace 1245 before of Master Andrew of Aberdeen,
                  official of the lord bishop of St Andrews, they compeared
                  with the men of discretion present, the lord J<ex>ohn</ex>, abbot of Dryburgh, Master William of Greenlaw, Adam of Maxton, Henry of
                     Holtal, and other worthy men, clerk and lay, of religion
                     and secular, representing their own parties for the
                     restoration of peace, the suit initiated between the
                     parties, and for a long time pursued, was in this form
                     amicably settled, namely, that Peter the canon, agent of
                     the canons of St Andrews, remitted and quitclaimed in the
                     name of the said prior and canons of St Andrews to the
                     aforesaid nuns of Haddington all the teinds named above so
                     that the said nuns may in future receive and possess
                     undisturbed the aforementioned teinds for ever, and turn
                     them to their own use without any disagreement. In return
                     for this remission and quitclaim, the aforesaid master and
                     nuns have given to the oft-mentioned canons of St Andrews
                     a rent of twenty shillings in the teinds of Falside in the
                     parish of Crail. And since all the aforementioned garbal
                     teinds of Falside have been reckoned by the inspection of
                     worthy and faithful men from both sides, of the electors
                     and the jurors, that they were worth seventeen shillings
                     more than the rent of twenty shillings assigned to the
                     aforementioned canons, by joint approval and agreement of
                     either side it was laid down that the aforenamed canons
                     would pay to the aforenamed nuns seventeen shillings
                     annually at Easter for the remainder of the said teinds.
                     And so, the aforementioned canons shall forever possess,
                     and lawfully turn over to their own purposes, all the
                     garbal teinds. And in order that this restoration of peace
                     and gracious agreement may gain the validity of
                     everlasting endurance, and lest by the malice and
                     craftiness of wicked men the legal suit thus amicably
                     settled could again be revived, either side, the canons as
                     much as the nuns, have submitted themselves to the
                     jurisdiction of the one who is at the time bishop of St
                     Andrews, so that it be possible to compel by one single
                     warning through ecclesiastical censure the party
                     witholding the foregoing things or unwilling to abide by
                     this agreement to observe it faithfully for ever through
                     ecclesiastical censure.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And in addition, for greater security, and so that all uncertainty may be
                  removed, to the side of the document – produced in the manner
                  of a cyrograph – remaining in the possession of the canons of
                  St Andrews, the seal of the nuns of Haddington together with
                  the seal of the lord David, by the grace of God bishop of St
                  Andrews, and of Master Andrew, official of the said bishop,
                  have been applied; and to the side remaining in the
                  possession of the nuns the seal of the chapter of St Andrews,
                  and of the said bishop, and of the official, have been
                  attached.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witness the whole chapter of Lothian, before whom this agreement was read out
                  and approved by the parties.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>