<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.9</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:35:36.428615+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.9</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to all worthy men of his entire land <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">[sends] greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know us</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have conceded, and by this our charter to have made firm, in pure and
                  everlasting alms, to the abbot and convent of Melrose, that
                  all lands between Gala and Leader which they have held or in
                  possession of which they have been, and also all other lands
                  which they have held or in possession of which they have been
                  on the south side of the Tweed, which adjoin the lands of
                  Lessudden and the lands of the monks of Kelso, and whatever
                  is contained within the said lands which we have deforested
                  for them, as much below ground as above, they may hold and
                  have for ever in free forest, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="prohibition">strictly forbidding anyone, without the express permission of the abbot and
                     convent themselves, to cut wood, hunt, fish, or go
                     fowling, or attempt to do any other thing against the will
                     of same in the said lands, on pain of our full forefeiture
                     of ten pounds.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: G<ex>eoffrey</ex>, elect of Dunkeld; Laurence of Abernethy; Bernard Fraser; Thomas son of Ranulf;
                     William of Lindsay; David of Lindsay; Alexander of
                     Stirling.</seg> At Ancrum, on the third day of December in the twenty-second year of the reign
                  of the lord king. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>