<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.15</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:41:38.776452+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.15</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William, by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, officials, and all worthy men of
                     his entire land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have given, and by this my charter to have made firm, to God, St Mary, the
                  church of Melrose, and the monks serving God in that place,
                  for the soul of King David my grandfather, and for the soul
                  of Earl Henry my father, and of my mother, and for the soul
                  of King Malcolm, and for my own salvation, and of all my
                  predecessors' and successors' [salvation], that piece of land
                  at Blainslie which King David conceded to his foresters, and
                  I afterwards had conceded to William son of Oein, that is to
                  say, the toft and messuage that the aforesaid William held
                  and possessed, so that they may build it just as it shall
                  seem most beneficial to them at their own will. And it is
                  permitted to them to plough and cultivate that entire land
                  only which had beforehand been broken and ploughed, with all
                  the liberties of the forest between Gala and Leader, as it is
                  specified in the charters of my predecessors, and my own. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">This land I therefore concede to them, and by the present charter make firm in
                     everlasting alms, so that the aforesaid monks may have and
                     possess it freely and quitly, fully and honourably, just
                     as any alms can most quitly and freely be held, released
                     from every earthly service and secular exaction,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">so that I and my heirs shall warrant this land to them against all men.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Osbert abbot of Kelso; Hugh abbot of Newbattle; William
                  Malveisin; Richard de Prebenda; Hugh de Sigillo; Earl David,
                  the king's brother; Robert de Quincy; Hugh Ridel; Richard de
                  Munfichet; Philip de Valognes; Roger de Valognes; Waldef son
                  of Baldwin; Alexander de Saint-Martin; Hervey the marischal;
                  Richard [the] marischal; Robert de Saint-Michel; Alan son of
                  Hugh, Earl David's steward; Richard son of Eissun; Adam of
                  Standford.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>