<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.17</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:43:41.799659+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.17</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam,</ex> by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts, officials, and
                     all worthy men of his entire land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">us to have conceded, and by this our charter to have made firm, the amicable
                  peace made between the convent and church of Kelso on the one
                  side, and the convent and church of Melrose on the other
                  side, over the boundaries of the lands of Bowden, Eildon, and
                  Darnick. Wherefore we will and instruct that the aforesaid
                  peace made between the aforesaid convents and houses be
                  firmly and inviolably held in times to come and for ever,
                  just as it is more plainly specified in the cyrograph made
                  between the aforesaid convents and houses. We have also
                  conceded and by this our charter made firm the amicable peace
                  made between the aforesaid convents and aforesaid houses over
                  the dispute that was at issue between the aforesaid convents
                  and houses aforenamed, about the land of Mow and of Clifton,
                  just as it is specified in the aforesaid cyrograph made
                  between the two.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Alexander the lord king's son; Philip de Valognes, chamberlain;
                  Robert of London, the lord king's son; William Comyn, David
                  of Lindsay, justices; Oliver the lord king's chaplain;
                  William del Bois, the lord king's clerk; Philip of Mowbray;
                  Walter Oliphant; Henry the son of Earl David; Philip of
                  Lundin; David the marischal; Richard son of Hugh; Herbert de
                  Camera; John of Stirling; Richard, Adam Hastings.</seg> At Stirling on the 22nd day of June.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>