<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.8</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:34:58.083145+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.8</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to all worthy men of his entire land <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">[sends] greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Let present and future know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">us, for the welfare of our soul, and of our predecessors' and successors'
                  [souls], to have given, conceded, and by this our charter to
                  have made firm, to God, St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks
                  serving God in that same place now and for ever in the
                  future, the loch of Dunscore in Nithsdale, and that pennyland
                  which belongs to the same loch, and whatever is contained
                  within the same loch and land; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the same monks to hold and to have for ever, in free, pure, and perpetual
                     alms, of us and our heirs, freely, quitly, fully, and
                     honourably from all service, custom, and secular exaction.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">We and our heirs shall warrant all the aforesaid to the same monks against all
                     men,</seg> withholding nothing of right in the same, nor requesting in return for them
                     anything other than prayers only, provided that the same
                     monks each year on St Andrew's day have a pittance from
                     the profits of the same.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, G<ex>eoffrey</ex>, elect of Dunkeld; Laurence of Abernethy; Bernard Fraser; Thomas son of Ranulf;
                     William of Lindsay; David of Lindsay; Alexander of
                     Stirling.</seg> At Ancrum, on the third day of December in the twenty-second year of the reign
                  of the lord king.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>