<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.36</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:09:06.18635+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.36</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ’s faithful people who shall view or hear the present letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Ranulf the dean of Lothian, John the parson of Pencaitland, Robert of Methven,
                     and Richard of Kelso the rector of the church of Kinghorn,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">wish eternal salvation in the Lord.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">Since by authority of our venerable father William by God’s grace bishop of St
                  Andrews the valuation of the vicarage of Haddington was
                  committed to us, according to the assessment of trustworthy
                  men, who, having taken an oath, testified as far as this is
                  concerned; having viewed and inspected the sworn testimonies,
                  we have ordered the assessment be valued in the below-written
                  portions, David of Berwick, then vicar, being present and
                  consenting; that is in oblations and obventions of the whole
                  parish in respect of the living and the dead as well from
                  chapels as from the mother church, and all teinds of the
                  business of burgesses and of all other merchants and
                  conveyors, and all teinds of curtilages and orchards within
                  the burgh with half of the teind of hay; assigning the same
                  portions to him and his successors, by way of a perpetual
                  vicarage, by the authority of our said lord and father,
                  William, to support all episcopal burdens and synodal dues
                  attached to the said church; all other lesser teinds and
                  things coming to the said church, together with the teind of
                  corn, being reserved to the lords prior and convent of St
                  Andrews.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And in testimony of this matter we have caused the present letters to be
                  verified by the application of our seals.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Farewell. </seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>