<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.32</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:27:42.509664+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.32</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard, by the grace of God a humble servant of blessed Andrew</seg> to all sons of Holy Mother Church <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">[sends] greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know us, as much those to come after as those present,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have given, conceded, and by the guarantee of the present writing to have
                  made firm, to God, the church of St Andrew, and to the canons
                  serving God in that same place now and in the future, the
                  church of Haddington with the land of Clerkington by its
                  right marches, and with everything else rightfully pertaining
                  to the same church, in free and everlasting alms, to be held
                  freely and quitly and honourably from every exaction and
                  custom, saving the tenure of the nuns which we gave to them
                  and affirmed by our charter. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore we will and by episcopal authority command that the aforesaid canons
                     hold the aforenamed church as freely, and quitly and
                     honourably possess, just as any church in our whole
                     diocese is held most freely, and quitly and honourably
                     possessed, saving synodal dues and episcopal aids.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: John, abbot of Holyrood; A<ex>ndrew</ex>, archdeacon of St Andrews; Ilbert, prior of Haddington; William, prior of
                     Galloway; William, prior of Holyrood; Robert, the bishop's
                     brother; John of St Andrews; Roger of Liston; Robert of
                     Perth; Alexander and William, the bishop's chaplains;
                     Geoffrey, the bishop's steward; Master Abraham; Stephen
                     the clerk; William, son of Robert son of Guy; Adam,
                     brother of Earl Duncan; Merlswain son of Merlswain; Odo
                     the steward; Cospatric of Rires; Hugh the butler; Walter
                     the bishop's nephew; William the chamberlain; Guy the
                     marischal; Gamel the doorward; and very many other men of
                     good character.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>