<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Cotton Ch. xviii.22</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:14:05.226954+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Cotton Ch. xviii.22</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Henry the earl, son of the king of Scots</seg>, to bishops, abbots, earls, justiciars, barons, sheriffs, officials, and all
                     his sworn men, French and English, clerk and lay, future
                     as well as present, of his whole land, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> that I have conceded Clerkington to God and to the church of St Mary at
                     Haddington in perpetual alms with its right marches on
                     either side of the the river just as William of Graham and
                     Durand the sheriff, and Richard the clerk and Osbert the
                     prior of Edinburgh [Holyrood], and Malbeth of Liberton and
                     Gillanders son of Oggu led the way and went around, after
                     Thorald the archdeacon determined the bounds with me at
                     Peebles, and just as it was previously measured. I also
                     concede to the aforesaid church one full toft next to the
                     church in the toun of Haddington, and all teinds and
                     ecclesiastical revenues from the whole of Haddingtonshire
                     from mills as well as other things. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">I therefore will and firmly enjoin that the aforesaid church hold and have the
                     aforenamed land, Clerkington, alone, and quit in relation
                     to me and the thane and all others who shall have held the
                     aforesaid land of Haddington of me and my heirs and of
                     their heirs, and all other revenues and customs in teinds
                     and alms as freely and honourably and quietly and fully as
                     other alms in my whole land are well and fully and
                     honourably and quietly able to be given and granted.</seg> These aforenamed alms I give and confirm by my charter for the sake of my own
                     soul and of my father’s and mother’s, and the souls of my
                     ancestors and successors. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Engelram [Ingram] the chancellor, and William Maule, and Edmund
                  son of Aimar, and Anselm nephew of Bishop John.</seg> At Haddington.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>