<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL Harley 111.B14</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:22:49.218016+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>Harley 111.B14</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard, by the grace of God humble servant of the church of St Andrews</seg>, to all sons of Holy Mother Church of the whole of his diocese <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let those to come as well as those present know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">us to have given by the advice and agreement of our clergy in full chapter, and
                  by the corroboration of the present writing to have made firm
                  to the church of the Holy Cross and to the canons serving God
                  in that place the Church of Falkirk, which is called Varia
                  Capella, and the whole land which we ourselves had there, or
                  any of our ancestors, with everything belonging by right to
                  the aforenamed church and land, for the sake of the souls of
                  the kings David, Malcolm; and of our predecessors, Robert,
                  Arnold; and of our uncle, Alwin; and of each of the faithful;
                  in everlasting alms, by rendering each year in respect of the
                  above-written land one stone of wax to the our chapel and our
                  successors', at Pentecost. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore we will and enjoin that they have and possess the aforesaid church
                     with the aforenamed land free and quit from every
                     exaction, saving episcopal dues in respect of the church,
                     and the afornamed rent in respect of the land</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Geoffrey, abbot of Dunfermline; John, abbot of Kelso;
                  Osbert, abbot of Jedburgh; Andrew the archdeacon; Master
                  Osbert de Merlay; Walter, prior of Kelso; Aiulf the dean;
                  Robert, the bishop's brother; John, Bishop Robert's nephew;
                  Robert of Perth, son of Saewulf; Master Herbert; Alexander
                  the chaplain; Master Abraham; Henry, the archdeacon's
                  chaplain.</seg> This donation was made in the full chapter celebrated at Berwick, in 1166th year
                  since the Incarnation.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>