<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL L.F.C. Ch. xxx.6</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:15:12.974993+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>L.F.C. Ch. xxx.6</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, sheriffs, justiciars, provosts, officials,
                     and all worthy men of his entire land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting.</seg> </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> that, to the honour of God, the Glorious Virgin Mary, and the most holy King
                     Edward, for the promotion of the holy life of faith, for
                     our own salvation and that of all our predecessors and
                     successors, and for the souls of the illustrious King
                     William our father, and of Queen Ermengarde our mother,
                     and of all our predecessors and successors, we have
                     founded an abbey of the Cistercian Order at Balmerino in
                     Fife, and that we have given, conceded, and by this our
                     charter made firm, to the monks of that same Order serving
                     God there now and in the future the whole land of
                     Balmerino, and of Coultra in Fife, by their right marches.
                     We have also conceded to the same the mother church of
                     Balmerino with all its pertinents, and everything that
                     lawfully belongs to the aforesaid lands, which Adam of
                     Stawell, brother and heir of Richard Revel, quitclaimed to
                     us for the benefit of the lady, Queen Ermengarde, our
                     mother, in our full court at Forfar, and resigned them in
                     our hand for himself and his heirs by staff and baton. We
                     have also conceded to the aforesaid monks of the
                     Cistercian Order, for the founding of the aforementioned
                     Abbey, ‘Feuthmure’ [Barry] in Angus by its right marches,
                     and with all its just pertinents. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And we and our heirs shall maintain and warrant to the aforesaid monks the
                     aforesaid lands with all their pertinents and liberties in
                     perpetuity against all men.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore we will that the aforesaid monks shall have and hold all the aforesaid
                     lands of us and our successors in free, pure, peaceful,
                     and perpetual alms, in lands, and waters, in meadows and
                     pastures, in moors and marshes, in ponds and mills, in
                     roads and paths, and salt-works and fisheries, and all
                     other easements lawfully belonging to the aforesaid lands,
                     as freely, and quitly, fully, and honourably, as other
                     alms are most freely, and quitly, fully and honourably,
                     from aids, army service, tallage, tolls and all exactions,
                     customs, and secular services in the kingdom of Scotland,
                     held or possessed, such that nothing of these whatever can
                     be required of them throughout the whole kingdom of
                     Scotland except for prayers.</seg> </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Andrew, bishop of Moray; Walter, earl of Buchan, justiciar of the
                  Scots; Walter Oliphant, justiciar of Lothian; Walter son of
                  Alan, steward; Patrick, son of Earl Patrick; Henry de
                  Balliol; Thomas de la Haye; John and William, his brothers;
                  Thomas son of Ranulf; Henry son of the earl; Robert de la
                  Haye; Geoffrey, Walter of Nydie, our clerks. </seg>At Clackmannan, on the 3rd day of February, in the 17th year of our reign.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>