<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL L.F.C. Ch. xxx.5</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:22:00.551018+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>L.F.C. Ch. xxx.5</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William, by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts, officials, and
                     all the worthy men of the whole of his land, clerk and
                     lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have given and conceded, and by this my charter to have made firm, to John
                  Waleram, in return for his homage and service, the whole land
                  which William Carpenter held in Babbet, that is, every fifth
                  rig of the whole half of Babbet, and in the fields of Drony,
                  the land which Hugh Gifford, Alexander de St-Martin, Godfrey
                  the marischal, Winemar, and other worthy men perambulated for
                  Roger de Camera at the instruction of the Countess Ada, my
                  mother; and in addition, the whole land in Airdrie [in Crail]
                  that William de Beauver held, that is, the land which is on
                  the east side of the burn that runs beside the land of
                  Geoffrey the chaplain, as far as the well at Crail which in
                  Gaelic is called 'Tolari' [Toldrie, in Crail]; and the whole
                  land by the same boundaries which Geoffrey de Malville, Hugh
                  Gifford, Godfre the marischal, Winemar and other worthy men
                  perambulated for the aforesaid William on every side towards
                  the moor and elsewhere; and common pasture at Crail; and one
                  toft in Crail, that is, the one which the Countess A<ex>da</ex>, my mother, gave to the aforesaid William. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will and firmly enjoin that the aforesaid John and his heirs have
                     and hold all the aforewritten holdings of me and my heirs
                     in feu and heritage, in meadows and pastures, in moors and
                     marshes, and in all other easements that belong by right
                     to the aforesaid lands, freely and quitly, fully and
                     honourably, by the service of one sergeand on a horse with
                     a haubergel, and performing in aids and forinsec services
                     in return for the whole land that he has in Airdrie as
                     much service as pertains to half a Scottish ploughgate in
                     Crailshire.</seg> I have also granted to the aforesaid John and his heirs that they be quit of
                     multure for their own house at my mill, but that his men
                     should give multure; and that the corn of John and his
                     heirs be milled at my mill first after the corn that is in
                     already in the hopper, unless my corn already be there or
                     arrive in the meantime.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Philip de Valognes, my chamberlain; William, my chaplain; William
                  Comyn; Hugh and William and Adam, my clerks; Master Nicholas
                  and Master Martin, my clerks; Alexander, sheriff of Stirling;
                  William de Valognes; Alexander, son of Thor; John of
                  Stirling; Robert Quarrantilly.</seg> At Clackmannan, on the 13th day of October.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>