<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of BL L.F.C. Ch. xxx.1</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 08:21:13.323557+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <idno>L.F.C. Ch. xxx.1</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">D<ex>avid</ex>, by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to bishops, abbots, earls, justices, barons, sheriffs, provosts, officials, and
                     all his sworn men, French and English, clerk and lay, of
                     his entire land, as much those to come after as those
                     present, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have given and conceded Clerkington in everlasting alms to God, to the
                  church of St Mary at Haddington, and the church of St
                  Andrews, with its correct boundaries on either side of the
                  river, just as William of Graham, Durand the sheriff, Richard
                  the clerk, Osbert the prior of Edinburgh, Malbeth of
                  Liberton, Gillanders son of Oggu, Gill' son of Merchev,
                  Ulfkil son of Merwin, and Sewal the knight led the way and
                  went around after Thorald the archdeacon reached a settlement
                  with me at Peebles, and also just as it was measured. I also
                  grant to the aforesaid church one full toft next to the
                  church in the toun of Haddington, and all teinds and
                  ecclesiastical revenues from the whole of Haddingtonshire,
                  both from mills and from other things. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">I therefore will and firmly enjoin that the aforesaid church hold and have the
                     aforenamed land, Clerkington, free and quit of me and of
                     the thane and of all others who may hold the land of
                     Haddington of me and my heirs and also of their heirs, and
                     also all other revenues and customs, in teinds and alms,
                     so freely, honourably, quitely and fully as any alms in my
                     whole land can well, fully, honourably and quitely be
                     given and granted. All these aforenamed alms I give and
                     make firm by my charter, for the sake of my soul, and my
                     father's and my mother's, and the souls of my ancestors
                     and successors.</seg></seg> This is approved and allowed by Henry my son, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">and it is witnessed by Robert, bishop of St Andrews; John, bishop of Glasgow;
                  Gregory, bishop of Dunkeld; Geoffrey, abbot of Dunfermline;
                  Denis, prior of Scone; Roger, prior of Dunfermline; Robert de
                  Sigillo; Duncan the Earl; Hugh de Morville; Malise the Earl;
                  Edward the Constable; Leod of Brechin; Ranulf de Soules;
                  Robert the nephew of Bishop Robert of St Andrews.</seg> At Perth, 18th Kalends of July [14th June].</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>