<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5958</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.748234+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5958</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all the faithful who shall view or hear these letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Adam son of Cospatric of Little Reston</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">moved by charity and for the salvation of my own soul and of my predecessors'
                  and successors', to have given, granted, and made firm by the
                  present charter for ever, in pure and everlasting alms, to
                  God and Saint Mary, for the maintenance of the light where
                  the mass of Saint Mary is celebrated in the church of
                  Coldingham, the toft and croft which Huckard held in in
                  Little Reston; that is, which lies between the demesne toft
                  and toft of William son of Reginald; freely, quitely,
                  released from every work, secular service, exaction and
                  demand, with common pasture, and with all liberties and
                  easements pertaining to the same toun, within the toun and
                  outside; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">so freely and quitely as any alms in the kingdom of Scotland is freely, quitely,
                     and honourably held and possessed</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">I and my heirs shall warrant the aforesaid toft and croft against all men and
                     women. So that this my donation should remain valid and
                     unbroken for ever.</seg> </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">I have authenticated the present writing by the application of my seal.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord Anketin, prior of Coldingham; John and Stephen,
                  then chaplain of Coldingham; John, son of Elias of Ayton;
                  Robert son of Gregory; William the clerk; Adam, then grieve;
                  Robert son of Reginald; Roger son of Ralph; and many others.</seg> </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>