<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 973</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 14:52:15.597286+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 973</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex> king of the English</seg>, to Thomas archbishop of York, and to all his sworn men, French, English, and
                     Gaelic, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have granted to God Almighty, and to the church of Durham, and to the holy
                  confessor Cuthbert, and to Bishop William and the monks in
                  the same church serving God now and for ever in the future,
                  the lands in Lothian which Edgar, son of Malcolm king of
                  Scots, with my consent, donated to God and the above-said
                  church; that is, the manor of Berwick; and these manors
                  written below: Graden, Lennel, <ex>Dylsterhale</ex>, Birgham, Edrom, Chirnside, Hilton, Blackadder, Kimmerghame, Hutton, Renton,
                     Paxton, Foulden, Mordington, Lamberton, the other
                     Lamberton, Edrington. Fishwick, <ex>Horeford</ex>, Upsettlington, and the manor of Coldingham; and these manors written below:
                     Old Cambus, Lumsdaine, Reston, Swinton, <ex>Farndun</ex>, Ayton, the other Ayton, Prenderguest, Cramsmoo, Edington. These manors written
                     above, with their appurtenant lands, woods, water, and all
                     tolls and wrecked ships, and their other customs, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">just as King Malcolm well had</seg>, I grant for ever to God and Saint Cuthbert.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">FAREWELL.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>