<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5965</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 21:10:50.67455+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5965</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful to whom these present letters shall have come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Simon son of Elias of Prenderguest</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have given, granted, and by this my present charter to have made firm, for
                  myself and for my heirs for ever, to God and to the blessed
                  Cuthbert and the blessed Æbbe of Coldingham, and to the monks
                  in that place serving God now and in the future, for the
                  salvatino of my soul and of my ancestors', and in return for
                  a certain sum of money which the prior and convent of
                  Coldingham paid to me as a downpayment in my need, ten acres
                  of land in the ploughland at <ex>Coteflat</ex> with one toft and croft of one acre of land on the western side of my brother
                     Richard's garden, which the same Richard gave to me in
                     return for my homage and service; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the said monks and their successrs to hold and to have as freely and quitely
                     as I held the aforesaid land at any time.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I, Simon, and my heirs shall warrant the aforesaid land to the aforesaid
                     monks against all men, with all its pertinents inside and
                     outside the toun, without any withholding.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And so that this my donation and confirmation should possess the perpetual
                  strength of a charter, I have applied my seal to this
                  charter.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, the lords David of Graham, then sheriff of Berwick, David
                  of Haddington, Ralph Noble, Alan of Harcarse, William of
                  Scremerston, Adam of Morham, Robert of Paxton, Adam son of
                  John of Ayton, Adam son of Walter of the same, Patrick Scot,
                  Patrick son of Colman of Oldcambus, and others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>