<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5967</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 21:10:50.635281+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5967</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful who shall view or hear this written document, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Laurence, son of William son of Gocelin of Berwick,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> to have given, granted, and by this my present charter to have made firm, to the
                     lord prior, Richard, and the convent of Coldingham and
                     their successors for ever, one oxgang of land in the
                     territory of Prenderguest from the fortified land; namely
                     that oxgang towards the east which Haldan son of Waldef
                     held; and fifteen acres of land that were once in the
                     demesne of John of Neville, that is, six acres of land at
                     Thornedales, two and a half acres of land at
                     Backestanesrig, three and a half acres at Crumbedales, one
                     and a half acres at Schortelandes, one acre at Lillesacre,
                     and a half-acre at Crumbedales, which I had from the gift
                     of Robert my brother in return for a certain sum of money
                     which the said Prior paid me in great necessity; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the said prior and convent of Coldingham and their successors to have and to
                     hold freely and quitely in all things, just as it is the
                     more fully and better contained in the charter which the
                     said Robert my brother had from the conferment of John of
                     Neville, our cousin, drawn up in respect of the same
                     holding.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant, acquit, and defend the said donation and grant
                     to the said prior and convent and their successors for
                     ever against all men and women.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">As witness of this matter I have applied my seal to the present document.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, the lord William of Mordington, the lord David of Haddington, the
                  lord Ralph Noble, the lord William of Scremerston, Adam of
                  Prenderguest, Adam son of John of Over Ayton, Thomas of
                  Nisbet, Bertram of Reston, Patrick Scott, Gilbert of
                  Lumsdaine, John son of Ingram, Gregory of Bethock, and
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>