<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5944</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.986178+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5944</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div><p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful who shall view or hear the present writing, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Ralph Noble</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">by having sealed the present charter with my seal, to have obliged myself and my
                  heirs for ever, that on account of the charter of the Prior
                  and Convent of the Church of Durham which they made for me
                  concerning the land which I shall hold of them by right of
                  heritage in the toun of Lamberton, to wit, one toft, and four
                  acres of land, as it is specified in their charter composed
                  concerning that matter, I shall not seek defence or
                  warrandice from the said Prior and Convent if it should
                  happen that a demand be moved by anyone in a clerical or a
                  lay court over the said land, and that I shall keep the Prior
                  and Convent of Durham, and the Prior and Convent of
                  Coldingham free from financial loss in all things as to the
                  aforesaid land. And if a plea should be moved upon it, I and
                  my heirs shall support the expenses of the whole of the plea;
                  and that we shall keep inviolate faith on this side.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter, I have put my seal to the present writing for
                  myself and my heirs.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord William of Mordington; the lord William of
                  Scremerston; Adam of Prenderguest; Robert son of Gregory of
                  Coldingham; David of Lumsdaine; Adam son of John of Over
                  Ayton; John son of Ingram, of the same toun; Bertram of
                  Reston; Patrick Scott; Gregory of Beoch.</seg></p> <p> </p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>