<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 568</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 15:48:09.636229+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 568</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">D<ex>avid</ex> by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to all throughout his kingdom settled in Scotia and Lothian, Gael and English, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have conceded, and given in alms, to God, Saint Cuthbert and his monks of
                     Durham, these lands in Lothian, that is to say,
                     Coldingham, Old Cambus, Lumsdaine, Reston, Renton,
                     Swinewood, Prenderguest, Ayton and the other Ayton, and
                     Cramsmoo, Lamberton and the other Lamberton, Paxton,
                     Fishwick, and Swinton. All these lands written above I
                     give and concede to God, and to the aforesaid saint and to
                     his monks of Durham, with sake and soke, toll and team,
                     and infangtheif, and with all lands, woods, waters, and
                     shipwrecks, and with all customs, free and quit from every
                     work and service, for the salvation of my own soul and of
                     my son Henry, and for the souls of my father and mother,
                     and my brothers and sisters. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="injunction">I also enjoin and forbid that anyone cause any injustice, trouble, or challenge
                     in respect of this my donation to the monks of Saint
                     Cuthbert of Durham henceforward, since I will that this my
                     alms remain free and quit from every claim for ever.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">This charter has been made firm in the year 1126 after the Lord's incarnation,
                  in the third year of my reign, at Peebles,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">by the witness and consent of Henry my son. And these others are witnesses of
                  it: John the bishop, Robert de Brus, Herbert the chancellor,
                  Ascelin the archdeacon, Payn de Briouze, Hugh Brett, Berengar
                  Engaine, Cospatric the sheriff, Aimer.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>