<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 556</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 20:19:35.841127+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 556</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>
          <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Edgar king of the Scots</seg> to all Scots and English throughout his kingdom <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting.</seg> </seg>
          <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have come to the consecration of the church of St Mary at Coldingham. This
                     dedication was fulfilled to the glory of God and to my
                     pleasing, was acceptable to all and honourably received.
                     And I have offered to the same church upon the altar as an
                     endowment and have donated the whole toun of Swinton with
                     the boundaries just as Liulf had, to be had in perpetuity
                     free and quit from every claim, and to be disposed at the
                     will of the monks of Saint Cuthbert; for the souls of my
                     father and mother, and for the salvation of my own soul
                     and my brothers’ and sisters’. I have also donated to the
                     monks 24 beasts to re-stock that same land. And I have
                     established the same peace in Coldingham, to those going
                     and returning and abiding there, which is preserved in
                     Island and in Norham. I have moreover also established
                     with the men in Coldinghamshire, just as they themselves
                     have chosen and have confirmed in my hand, that they they
                     should pay every year for each plough half a merk of
                     silver to the monks. </seg>
          <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Ælfwine, Óttar, and Thor Long, and Ælfric the butler, and Algar
                  the priest, and Osbern the priest, and Cnut Carl’s son, and
                  Oggu and Leising, and Swain Ulfkill’s son, and Liulf of
                  Bamburgh, and Uhtred Eilaf’s son, Uviet White, and Tigerna.</seg>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>