<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 720</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 11:41:10.66332+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 720</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Ranulf of Bunkle</seg> to all who view or hear these letters <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me, moved by charitable love and for the souls of my father and of my mother and
                     for the salvation of my own soul and the souls of my wife
                     and of all my ancestors, to have granted, given, and by
                     this my present charter to have made firm, to God and to
                     blessed Cuthbert and the monks of Coldingham, land in the
                     territory of Edrom which lies next to the [White]Adder and
                     is called Todheugh, in free, pure, and everlasting alms. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the aforesaid monks have, hold, and possess the
                     aforementioned land as freely, quitly, and honourably as
                     any alms in the kingdom of Scotland is most freely,
                     quitly, and honourably had, held, and possessed.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Patrick son of the earl, Patrick son of Adam, Robert of
                  Upsettlington, David the marischal, Thomas of Gordon, Matthew
                  de Normanville, John de St-Michel, William de Vieuxpont,
                  Stephen of the Wardrobe, Henry of Prenderguest, William of
                  Wideslade, Alan of Swinton, Patrick of Preston, Simon son of
                  Thomas, Walter of Paxton, Andrew of Paxton, William of
                  Lumsdaine, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>