<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5966</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 21:10:50.656884+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5966</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of holy Mother Church to whom the present writing shall have come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Laurence, son of William son of Gocelin of Berwick</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">for the salvation of my soul, my ancestors' and successors', to have given,
                  granted, and by this my charter to have made firm, to God and
                  the Church of St Æbbe at Coldingham, to Richard the Prior,
                  and to the monks serving God in that place now and for ever
                  in the future, one oxgang of land in the territory of
                  Prenderguest of fortified land, namely, that oxgang of land
                  towards the east which Haldane son of Waldef held, and
                  fifteen acres of land which once belonged to the demesne of
                  John of Neville, that is, six acres of land at <ex>Thornedales,</ex> two and a half acres of land at <ex>Backestanesrig,</ex> three and a half acres of land at <ex>Crumbedales,</ex> one and a half acres of land at <ex>Scortlandes</ex>, one acre of land at <ex>Lilliesaccre</ex>, and a half acre of land at <ex>Crumbedales</ex>; and these lands I had from the gift of my brother, Robert, who freely acquired
                     them from John of Neville; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the said prior and monks of Coldingham and their successors to hold and to
                     have, with all liberties and easements pertaining to the
                     said lands, in free, pure, and perpetual alms, as freely
                     and quitely in all things as any alms within the kingdom
                     of Scotland is freely and quitely held or possessed.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, the lord William of Mordington, the lord David of Haddington, the
                  lord Ralph Noble, the lord William of Scremerston, Adam of
                  Prenderguest, Adam son of John of Over Ayton, Thomas of
                  Nisbet, Bertram of Reston, Patrick Scott, Gilbert of
                  Lumsdaine, John son of Ingram, Gregory of Beoch, and others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>