<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 623</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-13 14:14:00.620743+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 623</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of Scots,</seg> to all worthy men of his whole land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>: </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> that we have granted and by this our charter to have made firm the donation
                     which David of Quixwood made to God and to Saint Cuthbert
                     and to Saint Æbbe, and to the monks of Durham at
                     Coldingham, to those serving now and in perpetuity to
                     those who shall serve in future, of his whole land which
                     he had within and outwith the toun of Aldcambus, for the
                     exchange of sixty acres in the territory of Coldingham,
                     and one toft and croft which Waldef Pethun held and ten
                     acres of arable land at Fleurs, and one messuage near the
                     smiddy of Benedict the Smith. Wherefore we will, that the
                     aforesaid monks aforementioned have and hold the land, as
                     freely and quietly, as the charter of the aforesaid David
                     and the confirmation of Thomas the son of the same David,
                     made thereupon for the aforesaid monks declares, saving
                     our service. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Henry de Balliol, Chamberlain, Patrick son of Earl Patrick, Ralph
                  the Chaplain, Thomas of Stirling the Clerk, Henry of
                  Stirling, son of Earl David, John of Maxwell, Walter Comyn.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Selkirk, on the 9th day of December, in the Year of the Reign of the lord
                  King, the Tenth</seg>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>