<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5955</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.813496+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5955</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful to whom the present writing shall come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Bertram of Little Reston</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have given, granted, and by this my present charter to have made firm, to God
                  and to Saint Cuthbert, and to Anketin the Prior, and the
                  Convent of Coldingham, the homage and service of Patrick son
                  of Uhtred, with all lands and possessions which he had out of
                  the donation of Adam, my father, in the toun and territory of
                  Little Reston; that is, the toft and croft which lies near
                  the land of Henry towards the east, and fourteen acres of
                  land near <ex>Wambenese Cross</ex>, and three roods in <ex>Blakeclou,</ex> and two acres and a half near <ex>Blakeclou</ex> towards the east, and eight acres near <ex>Faules</ex>; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the Prior and Convent and their successors to have and to hold for ever,
                     quit in respect of me and my heirs, without any custom and
                     secular exaction and demand, just as any alms within the
                     kingdom of Scotland is well and freely held and possessed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">I, Bertram, and my heirs, shall warrant and defend for ever the aforesaid homage
                     and service for the Prior and Convent and their
                     successors, with all the lands and possessions written
                     before, against all men and women.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter, I have applied my seal to the present writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord William of Lindsay; the lord William of
                  Mordington; the lord Alan of Swinton; Thomas of Nisbet;
                  William of Scremerston; Adam of Prenderguest; David of
                  Lumsdaine; Robert son of Gregory; Gilbert of Lumsdaine; Adam
                  son of John of Ayton; Adam Francis; John son of Ingram; and
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>