<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 573</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 16:12:05.474939+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 573</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">D(avid), by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to all Holy Church's faithful, present and to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have allowed to the church of St Mary and St Cuthbert at Coldingham and to
                     the monks serving God there the gift which Cospatric
                     brother of Dolphin gave to the aforesaid church and monks,
                     that is to say, Edrom and Nisbet in perpetual alms, with
                     churches, waters, meadows, pastures, mills, and all other
                     places, and with the same correct boundaries by which he
                     held them on the day on which he was alive and dead, free
                     and quit from every service, and every custom, except for
                     thirty shillings which the said monks shall give to his
                     son Cospatric and his heirs after him in return for the
                     king's corrody each year at the feast of St Martin, and
                     excepting the king's army service, for which the monks
                     shall be responsible to the king himself; and Cospatric
                     shall be quit in respect of army service for ever.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">Present as witnesses: Robert the bishop of St Andrews, John the bishop of
                  Glasgow, Herbert the abbot of Roxburgh, Richard the abbot of
                  Melrose, Edward the chancellor, <persName>Thor</persName> the archdeacon, Hugh the constable, Herbert the chamberlain, Ralf de Soules,
                     Walter of Ryedale, Robert of Bournville, Orm son of
                     Malcolm, Norman sheriff of Berwick, Robert son of Guy, the
                     sheriff of Roxburgh, Swain the priest of Fishwick, William
                     of Lamberton, Haldane of Prenderguest.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Coldingham on the day of the Invention of the Holy Cross, in the year 1147
                  since the incarnation of the Lord, that is, the year in which
                  the king of France and many Christiants made their way to
                  Jerusalem. </seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>