<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 713</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-02 13:02:56.734997+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 713</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">William of Lindsay, to all sons of Holy Mother Church, greeting.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Let it be known to all who see or hear these letters that, inasmuch as it
                  pertains to me as to the possessor, I have given and by this
                  my charter made firm, to God, Saint Cuthbert, and to the
                  monks of the same saint serving God in Durham, the Church of
                  Earlston, with one ploughgate of land, and all its other
                  pertinents in pure and perpetual alms. Wherefore I will that
                  the same monks should possess the aforesaid church and all
                  that belongs to it, freely, quitely and wholly for ever. And
                  they should have its multure entirely quit; and whosoever
                  might hold the aforesaid church of them. I have promised
                  however that according to my ability I shall maintain this
                  alms for the benefit and use of the church of Durham.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses : John, archdeacon of Durham; Alan, priest of Wallsend;
                  Master Thomas; Andrew, archdeacon of Lothian; Master Richard
                  of Coldingham; Patrick, dean; Hervé and Romfar, priests;
                  Master Thomas of Lamberton; Richard, archdeacon’s chaplain;
                  Richard, parson of Tweedmouth; Richard, son of Hervé; Walter
                  the seneschal; Adam of Wallsend; Elias of Wallsend; and many
                  others. </seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>