<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 721</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 11:41:10.645198+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 721</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Ranulf of Bunkle</seg> to all who view or hear these letters sends greeting.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me, moved by charitable love, out of love and reverence for blessed Cuthbert the
                     glorious confessor, and for the souls of my father and my
                     mother and for the salvation of my own soul and the soul
                     of my wife and all my ancestors, to have quitclaimed the
                     entire claim which I had, and the right which I had or was
                     able to have, in the woods and moors of the prior and
                     monks of Coldingham, that is, Brockesholes, Harewood,
                     Denewood, entirely to the same monks, without any
                     renouncing. In addition, know that I and my heirs shall
                     maintain and preserve to the aforesaid monks in perpetual
                     peace the boundaries made and perambulated between
                     Coldingham and Bunkle, that is, from 'Middeldenesheued' by
                     'Mereburnesheued' westwards to 'Cratoketrestrete' and from
                     there by the same path to Eiford.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Patrick son of the earl, Patrick son of Adam, Robert of
                  Upsettlington, David the Marischal, Thomas of Gordon, Matthew
                  of Normanville, John of St-Michel, William de Vieuxpont,
                  Stephen of the Wardrobe, Henry of Prenderguest, William of
                  Wideslade, Alan of Swinton, Patrick of Preston, Simon son of
                  Thomas, Walter of Paxton, Andrew of Paxton, William of
                  Lumsdaine, and many others. </seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>