<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 734</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 10:59:47.561398+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 734</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall view or hear these letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Patrick, son of Patrick earl of Dunbar</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me faithfully to have understood and recognised through the charter of King
                     Edgar, and by many other proofs, in the court of the lord
                     king, Alexander, the full right of the prior and monks of
                     Durham serving God at Coldingham in respect of the toun
                     and demesne of Swinewood with its pertinents concerning
                     which I have at some time disturbed them. Hence it is that
                     I make known to you all that I, for myself and my heirs,
                     have quitclaimed and renounced for ever, to God, Saint
                     Cuthbert, Saint Ebbe, and the prior and monks of Durham
                     serving God at Coldingham, and who will in perpetuity
                     serve there, the toun of Swinewood and the entire demesne
                     of the same toun, with all its pertinents, and the whole
                     right and every kind of right and claim, if I had or could
                     have had it in the same toun, as well in demesnes as in
                     men, services and homages, woods and plains, lands
                     cultivated and uncultivated, and all other things
                     belonging to the said toun and the said demesne, without
                     any withholding; and I returned by rod and staff in the
                     king's court what my ancestors unawfully appropriated and
                     withheld, so that neither I nor my heirs nor any on our
                     side could have in the future right or claim in the
                     aforementioned toun and demesne with its pertinents.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">The said quitclaim was made in the court of the lord king, Alexander,
                  illustrious king of the Scots, at Roxburgh on the third
                  kalends of April [30 March] in the seventeenth year of reign
                  of the same king.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">So that everything aforesaid should remain valid and undisputed, I have
                  authenticated the present writing by the application of my
                  seal.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord Walter Oliphant, justice of Lothian; the lord
                  William, chancellor of the lord king; the lord John of
                  Maxwell, chamberlain of the lord king; the lord Robert of
                  Roos; the lord Ranulf of Bunckle; the lord Bernard Fraser;
                  the lord Thomas son of Ranulf; the lord Thomas de la Haye;
                  David, clerk of Walter Oliphant; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>