<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5961</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 21:10:50.74891+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5961</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall view or hear this writing, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William son of Robert of Scremerston</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">by the consent of my heir, William, to have given, granted, and made firm by
                  this my present charter, to God, and to Saint Cuthbert, and
                  to the lord Richard the prior, and to the convent of
                  Coldingham, and their successors for ever, in return for
                  forty-seven merks of silver which they have paid to me as an
                  advance, my whole land of Prenderguest, with dwellings,
                  tofts, and crofts, and with all its pertinents, without any
                  withholding; namely, six oxgangs of land with pertinents in
                  the territory of Prenderguest; that is, the two oxgangs with
                  toft and croft which Robert Wind held; and the two oxgangs of
                  land which William son of Geoffrey held; and the two oxgangs
                  of land which Geoffrey son of Waldef held; and the toft and
                  croft which Haldan son of Waldef held; and the toft and croft
                  which Richard son of Agnes held. These said lands with
                  dwellings, tofts, and crofts, with all their pertinents, I
                  had out of the gift of Robert son of Robert of Prenderguest
                  in the toun and territory of Prenderguest. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For the aforementioned prior and convent of Coldingham and their successors to
                     have and to hold of me and my heirs for ever, as freely,
                     quitely, and honourably in all things, as it is the more
                     fully and better set out and witnessed in the charter of
                     the same Robert drawn up thereupon. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I, William of Scremerston, and my heirs shall warrant, acquit, and defend
                     all the lands aforenamed, with dwellings, tofts and
                     crofts, and with all their pertinents, to the
                     oft-mentioned prior and convent of Coldingham and their
                     successors, against all men and women for ever.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter, I have applied my seal to this writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord William of Lindsay; the lord William of
                  Mordington; the lord Alan of Swinton; Alan his son; Thomas of
                  Nisbet; Adam his son; Ada of Prenderguest; Robert son of
                  Gregory of Coldingham; David of Lumsdaine; Gilbert of
                  Lumsdaine; Adam son of John of Ayton; Bertram of Reston; John
                  son of Ingram; Robert son of Reginald; and others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>