<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5962</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 21:10:50.728229+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5962</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall view or hear these letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert of Prenderguest</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have given and to have made firm by this present charter, to William of
                  Scremerston and his heirs, in return for their homage and
                  service, and for twenty-four merks of silver, six oxgangs of
                  land with pertinents in the territory of Prenderguest; that
                  is, the two oxgangs with toft and croft which Robert Wynd
                  held; and the two oxgangs which William son of Geoffrey held;
                  and the two oxgangs which Geoffrey son of Waldef held; and
                  the toft and croft which Haldan son of Waldef held; and the
                  toft and croft which Richard son of Agnes held. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For the said William and his heirs to hold and to have of me and my heirs in feu
                     and heritage, freely, quitely, and honourably; he and his
                     heirs yearly returning thereupon to me and my heirs seven
                     shillings and nine pence in return for every service
                     pertaining to me or my heirs; and performing such forinsec
                     service for the same holding as pertains to six oxgangs.</seg> And it is to be known that this is the first land which I have given or
                     alienated after my land of Prenderguest was given to me.
                     And if by chance William or his heirs incur a fine against
                     me or my heirs, they shall give twelve pence for the fine,
                     and give twelve pence for the relief. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I, Robert, and all my heirs, shall warrant and defend for ever the
                     aforenamed lands with pertinents to the aforesaid William
                     and his heirs against all men and women.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter, I have applied my seal to the present writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord Anketin, prior of Coldingham; the lord Laurence,
                  terrar; the lord William of Lindsay; Thomas of Nisbet; Adam
                  of Prenderguest; John son of Elias; Bertram of Reston;
                  Richard son of Elias; Alan Ridel; Robert son of Maurice; and
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>