<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5981</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 20:57:31.665127+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5981</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful to whose notice these letters shall come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Bertram son of Robert Cook</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you</seg>, to have given, granted, and by this my present charter to have confirmed to
                     God, to blessed Cuthbert, St Ebbe, the prior of
                     Coldingham, and the monks in that place serving God now an
                     for ever, in free and everlasting alms, one
                     half-ploughgate of land with toft and croft in the toun
                     and territory of Renton, with all pertinents belonging to
                     so much land, inside the same toun as well as outside,
                     without any withholding; that is, the half-ploughgate of
                     land which the late Waldef son of Cren held in the toun of
                     Renton; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the said prior and convent and their successors to hold and to have for
                     ever, as freely, quitely, and honourably as any alms doing
                     forinsec service within the kingdom of Scotia are freely
                     or honourably held or possessed, with all their liberties
                     and easements.</seg> And it should be know that I, Bertram and my heirs, shall be quit of the
                     forinsec service of the lord king and of the house of
                     Coldingham, so far as it pertains to so much land in the
                     same toun.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">In addition, it should be known that I, Bertram, and my heirs shall warrant,
                  acquit and defend the aforesaid land to the said prior and
                  convent and their successors against all men and women for
                  ever.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And that this my donation should have force for ever, I have applied my seal to
                  this written document.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, the lord David of Graham, W<ex>illiam</ex> of Mordington, W<ex>illiam</ex> of Scremerston, R<ex>alph</ex> Noble, R<ex>obert</ex> of Montgomery, R<ex>obert</ex> son of the Steward, David of Lumsdaine, Adam son of John, Adam son of Walter of
                     Ayton, Patrick Scott, John his son, John son of Ingram,
                     Patrick son of Colman, and others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>