<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5952</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.879556+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5952</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful who shall view or hear these letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Bertram, son of Adam son of Cospatric of Little Reston</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends Greeting</seg>. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">moved by charity and for the salvation of my own soul, and of my wife
                  Margaret's, and for the salvation of my father and my mother,
                  and of Robert my son, and my predecessors and successors, to
                  have given, granted, and to have made firm by this present
                  charter, to God and to Saint Mary, and for the improvement of
                  the church of Coldingham, in pure and perpetual alms, nine
                  acres of land in the territory of Little Reston, that is,
                  four acres in <ex>Blackechet'</ex> near <ex>Farnebed</ex>, and five acres in <ex>Goselauflat</ex>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held and had of me and my heirs in pure and everlasting alms for ever,
                     with common pasture and all liberties and easements
                     pertaining to so much land inside and outside the toun.
                     Wherefore I will and grant that the aforesaid church
                     should have and possess the aforementioned nine acres of
                     land for ever, free, quit, and released from all works,
                     secular services, aids, exactions and demands; saving
                     multure and the teinds of the house of Coldingham.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant the aforementioned nine acres of land to the
                     oft-mentioned church against all men and women.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And so that my donation should ever remain valid and undisputed, I have applied
                  my seal to this writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord A(nketin), then prior of Coldingham; the lord
                  William of Mordington; the lord Alan of Swinton; Alan his
                  son; Adam of Prenderguest; William of Scremerston; William,
                  vicar of Oldcambus; John son of Elias; Adam, then marischal;
                  Robert, son of Gregory the Steward; and many others. </seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>