<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5947</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.923071+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5947</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful to whom the present writing shall have come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert son of Reginald of Great Reston</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have given, granted, and made firm by this my present charter, to God, Saint
                  Cuthbert, Saint Æbbe, and the monks of Durham serving God at
                  Coldingham now and for ever in the future, in pure and
                  perpetual alms, for the salvation fo my own soul, and [the
                  souls] of my ancestors and successors, thirty acres and a
                  half in the territory of the toun of Great Reston; that is,
                  one-and-a-half acres in the toft and croft on the eastn side
                  of my toft; five acres and three roods in <ex>Held' </ex>; one-and-a-half acres between the woods; one acre in <ex>Gorbald</ex>; one acre in <ex>Coleleche</ex> and <ex>Bilie</ex><ex> haluch</ex>; one acre in <ex>Hopeland </ex>and <ex>Smethemedwe</ex>; one acre in <ex>Brere</ex>; two acres in <ex>Wyterleche</ex>; one rood below <ex>Bilielawe</ex>; four acres on the upper side of <ex>Laytolf</ex>; eleven-and-a-half acres on the western side of <ex>Wythenehep</ex>; with the common pasture and common easements of the said toun of Reston. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the said prior and monks of Durham should have and hold
                     the said lands for ever, as freely, quitely, fully and
                     honourably as any alms in the kingdom of Scotland is
                     freely, quitely, fully, and honourably held or possessed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant to the said prior and monks the said lands in
                     perpetuity against all men</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And in testimony of this matter, I have applied my seal to this writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord William of Mordington; the lord Alan of Swinton;
                  the lord Adam of Prenderguest; Walter, Andrew, Alexander of
                  Paxton; Welliam, vicar of Oldcambus; Robert, son of Gregory;
                  Adam of Little Reston; Bertram, his son; John, son of Elias
                  of Over Ayton; Maurice, son of Merlin; Ralph, grieve of
                  Coldingham; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>