<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5957</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.769803+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5957</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Liulf son of Ælsi and his heirs, namely, Cospatric, Gamel, <persName>Macbeth</persName>, Reginald, and Ecgheard,</seg> to all who view or hear these letters <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">send greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know us,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">in the court of the prior of Coldingham, and in his presence, to have abjured
                  whatever right we have had in Little Reston and to have
                  quitclaimed it to Adam son of Cospatric and his heirs, in
                  respect of ourselves or our successors, without any trouble
                  or counter-claim, in return for seven merks and one horse of
                  two merks which he has given to us in the presence of many
                  worthy men. And since we will that it should be firm, we have
                  affirmed by faith the oath to be sworn, in the hands of
                  Walter Oliphant, the king's justice, to be held for ever
                  without any deceit or counter-claim.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Walter Oliphant, the king's justice; Robert of Burneville,
                  sheriff, and his heir, Robert; Richard the marischal;
                  Patrick, the earl's uncle; Adam son of Aldan, and his heir,
                  Patrick; Gilbert Fraser, and John and Bernard, his sons;
                  Richard de Merlay; Stephen Papedy; Waldef of Prenderguest;
                  Edward of Oldcambus and his sons, Thomas, William, Stephen;
                  William the grieve; William of Nisbet; Adam son of Pace; Adam
                  of Prenderguest; Elias of Ayton; Adam of Lamberton; Alan of
                  Swinton; Richard of Swinton; Richard of Lumsdaine; Uchtred
                  son of Colman, and Adam his son; Waldef son of Uchtred; Ralph
                  son of Godwin; Adam of Beoch; Thomas son of Siward, and his
                  heir, Patrick; Adam son of Leysing; Eilaf son of Oddger, and
                  his heir; Robert the cook, and Philip of the cellar; and many
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>