<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 627</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 14:52:15.638731+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 627</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justiciars, sheriffs, provosts, officials,
                     and other other worthy men of the whole of his land, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know us</seg>, move by the love of God, to have given, granted, and made firm by this our
                     charter, to God, Blessed Mary, and Saint Cuthbert, and to
                     Thomas, prior of Coldingham, and the monks serving God in
                     that place now and for ever in the future, the twenty
                     annual merks which we and our ancestors we accustomed to
                     receive from Coldinghamshire as Waiting. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For the said monks and their successors to hold, receive, and have for ever, in
                     free, pure, and everlasting alms, as freely, quitely,
                     fully and honourably, as the same monks freely, quitely,
                     fully and honourably hold and possess any other alms.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witneeses: A<ex>dam</ex>, abbot of Melrose; W<ex>illiam</ex> of Bondington, chancellor; W<ex>alter</ex> son of Alan, steward and justiciar of Scotia; P<ex>atrick</ex> son of Earl Patrick; John of Maxwell, chamberlain; Roger Avenel; David Marshall;
                     Eymer of Maxwell; John of Stirling;</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Berwick on the sixteenth day of May, in the eighth year of the lord king's
                  reign.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>