<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD 1.1.Sacr.12</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-01-27 15:59:13.83033+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD 1.1.Sacr.12</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio"><persName>Walter</persName> del Bois</seg> to all sons of holy mother Church who see or hear these letters :</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Let them know that, for the health of my own soul, and of my father’s, and of my
                  mother’s, and of Galiena my spouse’s, and of Richard my
                  son’s, and of my ancestors’, and successors’, I have given,
                  and granted, and by this present Charter have made firm to
                  God and to Saint Cuthbert and the monks of <span data-dpt="place" data-dpt-cat="chars" data-dpt-type="name">Durham</span> in pure and perpetual alms the land at ‘Tavenaus’ by these boundaries: <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">that is, from the ‘Redehow’ on the ‘Kircelesbanc’ to the road that leads to
                     ‘Roberdesbi’, and by that road northwards to the first
                     syke that comes from the peat bog, and falls into the
                     Kirtle, and by descending as far as ‘Redebanc’.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will, and enjoin, that the aforesaid monks should have, and possess
                     the whole land aforesaid within the aforenamed boundaries,
                     in wood and plain, with common pasture of the toun of
                     Carruthers for a hundred sheep, forty cattle, fifty goats,
                     twenty pigs, and three horses, freely, quietly and
                     honourably, from all custom or aid, and exaction, just as
                     any Alms in the whole Kingdom is freely or quietly had, or
                     possessed</seg>. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses : Richard my son; Galiena my spouse; Ralph of Wassand;
                  Páitín the grieve; William d'Epaignes; Robert de Lithum; Adam
                  son of Richard; Stephen the clerk; Hamo; Geoffrey son of
                  Albelot; and many others. </seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>