<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5948</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.900658+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5948</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful to whom the present writing shall have come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert son of Reginald of Great Reston</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">truly to have come to know, by many proofs, that I and my ancestors ought to
                  have in the territory of the town of Great Riston but one
                  ploughgate of land only, that is, one-hundred-and-five acres.
                  Hence it is that I make known to you all that I have
                  resigned, and have quitclaimed for myself and my heirs, and
                  by rod and staff returned in the court of my lord, the prior
                  of Coldingham, to the prior and monks of Durham at Coldingham
                  serving God in that place now and for ever in the future, all
                  the lands which I or my predecessors unjustly occupied and
                  withheld above one ploughate of land in the territory of the
                  toun of Great Reston; that is, in seven acres in <ex>Ilvingishope</ex>, eighteen-and-a-half acres in <ex>Langelandis</ex>, twelve-and-a-half acres in <ex>Mers</ex>, the whole land in <ex>Alaynescastel</ex> in return for two acres, two acres in Bilielawe, eight acres in the grassland
                     which is called Swinwood, on the south side of the Eye
                     [Water]; so that neither I nor my successors shall in the
                     future be able to have any right or claim in the said
                     lands. And this resignation and quitclaim I have made to
                     the said monks for the salvation of my own soul and of all
                     my ancestors' and successors' [souls].</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And so that this resignation and quitclaim should have validity and strength I
                  have applied my seal to the present writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord William of Mordington; the lord Alan of Swinton;
                  the lord Adam of Prenderguest; Walter, Andrew, Alexander of
                  Paxton; William, vicar of Oldcambus; Robert son of Gregory;
                  Ada of Little Reston; Bertram his son; John, son of Elias of
                  Over Ayton; Maurice son of Merlin; Ralph, grieve of
                  Coldingham; Roger, his son; Adam son of Eilaf of Auchencrow;
                  David of Quixwood; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>