<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD 4.3.Sacr.1 (previously, Misc. Ch. 715)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-06 15:19:33.94762+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD 4.3.Sacr.1 (previously, Misc. Ch. 715)</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><persName>William</persName> de Vaux to all who hear or see these letters</seg> : <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Know that I have given and granted and by this my charter made firm to God and
                  to blessed Cuthbert and to the monks of <span data-dpt="place" data-dpt-cat="chars" data-dpt-type="name">Durham</span> serving God there, for their infirmary, two oxgangs of land in the territory of
                     Gullane, that is, the three perches that lie next to St
                     John's Croft to the west, and the twelve acres minus one
                     perch that lie between the land of William son of
                     Archibald and the Wingate, and the thirteen acres and
                     three perches that lie between the sea and those three
                     acres that belong to the sergeandry of Gullane on the
                     north with the pasture, as much as pertains to the two
                     oxgangs of land, in pure and perpetual alms, free and quit
                     from all secular service, custom and exaction. This
                     donation have I also made for the sake of the salvation of
                     my own soul and for the souls of my father and mother and
                     my heirs and all my forefathers. Wherefore I will and
                     firmly enjoin, that this my alms be as free and quit as
                     any alms is freely and quietly held and possessed in the
                     bishopric of St Andrews. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Ralph the Prior of Coldingham, Godard and Gumer the <persName><roleName>chaplains</roleName></persName>, Walter of Lindsay, Hubert de Vaux, Richard son of Michael, Simon the <persName><roleName>clerk</roleName></persName>, Richard Sans-Avoir, Richard son of Selburg, Nicholas of Gullane, Walter of
                     Ednam, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>