<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 589</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 16:47:55.690284+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 589</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex>, by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, sheriffs, provosts, officials, and all worthy
                     men of his entire land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> me to have conceded, and by this my charter to have made firm, the agreement
                     made between the church of St Andrews and the church of St
                     Cuthbert at Durham, and between Roger <ex>bishop</ex> elect of St Andrews and Prior Bertram and the convent of St Cuthbert at Durham,
                     that is to say, that the afore-mentioned <ex>bishop</ex> elect has conceded to God and St Cuthbert and the afornamed prior and convent of
                     the church of Durham that the church of Coldingham with
                     the chapels belonging to it be free and be quit for ever
                     from cain and conveth, procurations and hospitality, and
                     all other demands and synodal dues and aids, and all other
                     things, as much from the <ex>bishop</ex> elect himself as from his successors, and from all officials of the bishopric of
                     St Andrews, save only canonical justice and obedience to
                     the <ex>bishop</ex> elect and his successors; and that all other parish churches which the
                     aforementioned convent of the church of Durham possesses
                     in the bishopric of St Andrews be free and quit for ever
                     from cain and conveth, procurations and hospitality, as
                     much from the aforesaid <ex>bishop</ex> elect as from his successors, unless they wish to make it freely. And nothing
                     more in the aforesaid parish churches shall be demanded by
                     the officials of the bishopric of St Andrews than in the
                     parish churches of the abbot of Kelso or of any other
                     abbot who holds the more feely and better in the bishopric
                     of St Andrews. And when common aid is levied throughout
                     the whole bishopric of St Andrews, the prior and aforesaid
                     convent of the church of Durham shall answer for their
                     afore-written parish churches to the aforesaid <ex>bishop</ex> elect and his successors, just as the abbots or priors who freely hold in the
                     bishopric of St Andrews do in respect of their own. The
                     prior and aforesiad convent of the church of Durham shall
                     therefore have in perpetuity such authority, dignity and
                     freedom of disposition in all their parish churches as any
                     other abbeys have in their own churches which they hold
                     the better and more freely in the bishopric of St Andrews.
                     And on account of the aforesaid quittances and liberties,
                     and for the sake of peace, the said Prior Bertram and
                     convent of the church of Durham, by the advice and
                     agreement of Hugh, bishop of Durham, and his whole
                     chapter, have given and conceded to God and the church of
                     St Andrwes and the aforesaid <ex>bishop</ex> elect and his successors the chapel of Nenthorn to be held and conceded to whom
                     they wish in perpetuity, free, quit and released as much
                     from them as from the mother church of Ednam. Wherefore I
                     will that this agreement aforewritten between the
                     aforenamed churches be strictly and inviolably observed,
                     just as the authentic document produced between the
                     aforesaid <ex>bishop</ex> elect of St Andrews and the aforementioned Prior B<ex>ertram</ex> and convent of the church of Durham bears witness.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Hugh my chancellor, Archibald the abbot of Dunfermline, William
                  the abbot of Holyrood, Simon the archdeacon of Glasgow,
                  William Malveisin the archdeacon of Lothian, Roland son of
                  Uhtred, Earl Duncan, William of Lindsay, Robert of London,
                  Ranulf de Soulis, William of Ramsay, Henry Graham, William of
                  Conisbrough.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Edinburgh.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>