<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 560</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 15:48:09.428846+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 560</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Edgar by the grace of God king of the Scots </seg>to all to whom the present letters shall have come, as much to Frenchmen and
                     English as Gaelic, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">us, from the licence of William the king of England, overlord of the kingdom of
                  Scotland, for the sake of the souls of Malcolm our father and
                  Margaret our mother, and for the souls of Edward and Duncan
                  our brothers, and also for the sake of our own soul, to have
                  given and conceded to God and Saint Cuthbert the confessor,
                  to William the bishop, and Turgot the prior, and to the monks
                  of Durham serving God in perpetuity, the barony and manor of
                  Coldingham, with these manors written below, to wit, Berwick,
                  Old Cambus, Lumsdaine, Reston, 'Faudon', Ayton, the other
                  Ayton, Prederguest, Cramsmoo, Graden, Lennel, 'Dilchestre',
                  Edrom, Chirnside, Hilton, Blackadder, Hutton, Renton, Paxton,
                  'Fulden', Mordington, Lamberton, the other Lamberton,
                  Edrington, Horford, and Upsettlington, with all pertinents,
                  rights, and teinds of wheat and grain crops and hay, with all
                  liberties and royal immunities as freely and fully as our
                  aforesaid father and lord held it. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For the aforesaid bishop, prior, and monks and their successors to have and to
                     hold barony and manor, dwellings and teinds, all in
                     general and in particular, with all liberties, royal
                     immunities, and rights whatsoever, of us and our heirs in
                     pure and perpetual alms for ever.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And we and our heirs shall protect and defend for the bishop, prior, monks, and
                     their successors, the aforesaid barony and manor,
                     dwellings and teinds, all in general and particular, with
                     all liberties, royal immunities and rights whatsoever, as
                     it has been said before, against all people.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this this matter we have caused our seal to be applied to the
                  present letters at Norham</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">in the presence of the aforesaid King William of England the overlord of the
                  kingdom of Scotland, and of the aforesaid bishop and prior,
                  of Walter de Valognes, Odinel de Umfraville, Racho de
                  Loreyns, Odinel Heron, Robert de Mandeville, and a great
                  multitude of French, English and Scots.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>