<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 615</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-06 15:19:34.021513+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 615</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">Alexander, by the Grace of God King of Scots, to Bishops, Abbots, Priors, Earls,
                  Justices, Barons, Sheriffs, Provosts, Officials, and All
                  worthy men of the Whole of his land, Clerk and lay : <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> I will and firmly instruct that the woods of the monks of Coldingham, namely,
                     Greenwood, and the whole wood of Reston, and
                     Brockholeswood, and Aikieside, and 'Chirchedeneswde', and
                     'Harewde', and 'Denewde', and Swinewood, and Houndwood,
                     and all their other woods and wastelands shall be under
                     the protection and custody of the prior as well as of the
                     monks of Coldingham. Let no one, on pain of the forfeiture
                     of ten pounds, take anything in the aforesaid woods or
                     wastelands, except through the prior, or through the monks
                     of the aforenamed place if he is not himself present,
                     except for the requirements of my castle at Berwick alone,
                     those things only which are proper to me myself. And if my
                     servants shall come to the aforesaid woods for my needs
                     for the maintenance of my castle at Berwick, by the prior
                     or through his servants, and where he or his servants show
                     what things are necessary for me, they shall receive them.
                     I furthermore add and grant to them, that the aforesaid
                     prior and monks shall have warren in the aforesaid woods,
                     and throughought the whole of their land, as it stretches
                     by its right and ancient boundaries, namely, from the
                     boundaries between Berwick and Lamberton as far as Biollie
                     and as far as 'Drieforde' and so by the 'Mereburne' as far
                     as 'Crachoctre' and as far as 'Eieforde' and as far as the
                     burn which flows into the sea by Oldcambus peth, so that
                     nothing shall be taken there, neither firewood nor any
                     woodland beast, except by themselves. If anyone shall be
                     caught hunting in the aforesaid woods or wastelands, or
                     cutting firewood, or taking away anything from there
                     without the permission of the prior and monks, the prior
                     and monks shall have that which they find upon him and
                     with him, and I shall make the aforenamed forfeiture, as
                     the Charters of King David and of King William my father
                     bear witness and confirm. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses : William del Bois, my Chancellor; Earl Malcolm of Fife; Master
                  Adam of Scone and Robert, my Chaplains; Philip of Lundin;
                  David the marischal; Hervey the marischal; Adam Hastings. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Selkirk on the last day of July</seg>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>