<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 778</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 10:59:47.464123+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 778</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of the holy Church of God, eminent and lowly, ordained and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Cospatric the earl, brother of Dolfin</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">I have granted and given in alms to God and to Saint Cuthbert and to his monks
                  the <ex>uilla</ex> of Edrom and the church of the same <ex>uilla</ex> with all its chapels, and another <ex>uilla</ex> which is called Nisbet, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be possessed freely and quietly in perpetuity with everything that pertains
                     to the same <ex>uillae</ex> in lands and waters and meadows and pastures,</seg> for the soul of King Malcolm and of his sons the kings Edgar and Alexander, and
                     for King David and his son Henry, and for me myself and my
                     wife and my sons, and for the souls of all my forebears; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="malediction">and if anyone should wish to object to this charitable gift, let it be between
                     him and God</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: William son of Duncan; Cospatric his son; Ulfkil son of Maldred;
                  Ranulf of Lindsay; S. the priest; John the chaplain;
                  Cospatric son of Crin, and Haldane his brother; and Lambert
                  the steward.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Farewell</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="malediction">Whosoever take this away, let God take away from him both this life and the
                  kingdom of heaven.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>