<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 602</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 16:22:01.973671+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 602 </idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex>, king of the Scots</seg>, to the bishops, abbots, priors, earls, justices, barons, sheriffs, provosts,
                     officials, and all his men, French, English, and Gaelic,
                     as much present as future, of his entire land, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> I will and resolutely instruct that the woods of the monks of Coldingham, viz.
                     Greenwood, and the whole wood of Reston, and
                     Brockholeswood, Aikieside Wood, 'Kirchedeneswde',
                     'Harewde', 'Denewde', Swinewood, Houndwood, and all their
                     woods and wastelands, be under the protection and keeping
                     of the prior as well as the monks of Coldingham, so that
                     no one may take anything in the said woods or wastelands,
                     on pain of a £10 fine, unless through the prior himself or
                     the monks of the aforenamed place if he be not present;
                     saving only those things that are necessary for my castle
                     at Berwick, which I alone can agree to; and if my servants
                     come to the aforesaid woods for my needs regarding the
                     work on my castle at Berwick, and where he or his servants
                     have pointed out, they may receive those things I need
                     through the prior or through his servants. In addition, I
                     add and concede to them, that the aforesaid prior and
                     monks may have warren in the aforesaid woods, and
                     throughout their whole land, so far as the right and
                     ancient boundaries extend, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">viz. from the boundaries between Berwick and Lamberton as far as Billie, and up
                     to 'Drieford', and as far as the stream which flows into
                     the sea by Old Cambus peth,</seg> so that no one may take anything there, neither wood, nor any woodland beast,
                     unless by their permission; so that if someone in the
                     aforesaid woods or wasteland is caught hunting or cutting
                     wood, or taking anything from there without the permission
                     of the prior and monks, the prior and monks shall have
                     what they find on him or with him, and I the fine
                     specified before.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Richard, bishop of St Andrews; Ingram, bishop of Glasgow; Nicholas
                  the chancellor; the abbot of Jedburgh; David Oliphant,
                  justice; Dolphin the chaplain; Hugh the king's clerk; Walter
                  of Windsor; Robert Freeburn.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Berwick.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>