<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5970</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 20:57:31.52489+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5970</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div><p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all present as well as future know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">I, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">John Neville</seg>, have given, granted, and by this present charter made firm to Robert Goscelin,
                     my kinsman, in return for his homage and service, one
                     oxgang of land in the territory of Prenderguest from the
                     fortified land, namely the oxgang of land towards the east
                     which Haldane son of Waldef held, and fifteen acres of my
                     demesne, that is, six acres at Thorndales, two and a half
                     acres at Bakestanesrig, and three and a half acres at
                     Crumbedales, one and a half acres at Shortlands, one acre
                     at Lillesacre, and a half-acre at Crumbedales. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For the said Robert and his heirs or assigns to hold and to have of me and my
                     heirs in feu and heritage, freely and quitely, with all
                     liberties and easements belonging to the said land</seg>; by him and his heirs or assignees yearly rendering to me and my heirs
                     thereupon in return for the said fifteen acres some white
                     gloves at Pentecost for every service pertaining to me or
                     my heirs, and performing for the said oxgang of fortified
                     land as much as pertains to one oxgang of land of the same
                     holding to the service of the lord king and the house of
                     Coldingham. Robert himself and his heirs or assigns shall
                     also give to me and my heirs, in return for a fine, should
                     it occur, twelve pence, and for relief, twelve pence. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I, John, and my heirs shall defend and warrant all the aforenamed land with
                     all their pertinents and aforewritten liberties to the
                     said Robert and his heirs and their assigns against all
                     men and women for ever.</seg> And it should be known that this is the first land which I have given or
                     alienated since I became lord of my land of Prenderguest.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">As witness of this matter I have applied my seal to the present document.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, the lord A<ex>nketin</ex>, prior of Coldingham, the lord Henry the terrar, the lord A<ex>dam</ex> of Prenderguest, Thomas of Nisbet, William vicar of Oldcambus, William of
                     Scremerston, John son of Elias, Adam his son, Richard of
                     Prenderguest, Bertram of Reston, Robert son of Gregory,
                     Robert son of Maurice, and many others.</seg></p> <p> </p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>