<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 628</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-29 15:57:28.277371+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 628</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander by the grace of God king of Scots</seg> to all worthy men of his whole land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg></seg>: <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> we have granted and confirmed by this our charter the quitclaim and abjuration
                     that Patrick son of Earl Patrick has made for himself and
                     his own heirs to God, Saint Cuthbert, Saint Æbbe, and to
                     the prior and monks of Durham at Coldingham who are
                     serving God and, in perpetuity, those who will serve God,
                     of the toun of Swinwood and the whole demesne of that same
                     toun with all its pertinents and whole right, and every
                     kind of right and claim, if he has had or was able to have
                     such in the same toun, in demesnes as well as in men,
                     services and homages, woods and plains, lands cultivated
                     and uncultivated, and all other things pertaining to the
                     said toun and the said demesne. As freely and quietly,
                     fully and honourably, as the charter of the same Patrick
                     made more fully for the said prior and monks of Durham at
                     Coldingham justly declares. Saving our service.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Walter Oliphant, justiciar of Lothian; John of Maxwell,
                  chamberlain; David the marischal; Roger Avenel; Ranulf of
                  Bunkle; Ralph de Champagne; Thomas son of Ranulf; Bernard
                  Fraser; Thomas de la Haye; William of Bunkle. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Roxburgh, on the twenty-ninth day of March, in the seventeenth year of the
                  reign of the Lord king</seg>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>