<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5969</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 21:10:50.597554+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5969</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful to whom the present written document shall come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Hugh Levedyman of Langehope, and Eve his wife, sister of Laurence son of William
                     son of Gocelin of Berwick</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">send greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know us, all of you,</seg> to have granted at the urging of the said Laurence, and have made firm by this
                     our present charter, quitclaimed, and for ourselves and
                     our heirs for ever, entirely abjured the donation and
                     grant of the whole land, without any withholding, in the
                     territory of Prenderguest which Laurence, son of William
                     son of Gocelin of Berwick, had from the gift of Robert his
                     brother, which the same Laurence gave, granted, and by his
                     own charter made firm to God, St Ebbe, Richard the prior,
                     and the convent of Coldingham and their successors, in
                     free, pure, and perpetual alms.</seg> We have also pledged and sworn, touching holy relics, for ourselves and our
                  heirs, that we shall in no era of the world seek to move
                  against the aforesaid donation and grant. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">As witness of this matter, we have applied our seals to the present document.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, the lord William of Mordington, the lord David of Haddington, the
                  lord Ralph Noble, the lord William of Scremerston, Adam of
                  Prenderguest, Adam son of John of Over Ayton, Thomas of
                  Nisbet, Bertram of Reston, Patrick Scott, Gilbert of
                  Lumsdaine, John son of Ingram, Gregory of Bethock, and
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>