<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5977</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 20:57:31.598434+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5977</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful to whom the present written document shall come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Patrick son of Elias Dunning of Renton</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me all of you</seg> to have quitclaimed to the house of Coldingham for myself and my heirs in
                     perpetuity the homage and service that Henry my brother
                     and his heirs owe me for one toft and one croft of one
                     acre in the toun of Renton, and two acres in the plain of
                     the same toun, that is, one acre on the west side of
                     'Cromstaniside', and a large acre above 'Aletone', with
                     all escheats that could be due to me an dmy heirs for the
                     said land. The said Henry and his heirs shall each year
                     give as ferme to the house of Coldingham six pence at
                     Easter; and they shall give twelve pence for merchet,
                     twelve pence for heriot, twelve pence for forfeit.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And as witness of this my quitclaim I have applied my seal to this written
                  document.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witness, the lord William of Mordington, the lord Alan of Swinton, Adam of
                  Prenderguest, Robert, Andrew, Alexander of Paxton, Adam of
                  Reston, Bertram his son, Maurice of Ayton, Robert son of
                  Reginald, Ralph the provost, Roger his son, Robert son of
                  Gregory, John son of Elias of Ayton, and others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>