<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5946</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.944158+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5946</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all men present as well as future know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">I, Robert son of Reginald of Reston</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">have given and made firm by this my present charter, to God, Saint Cuthbert,
                  Saint Æbbe, and the prior and monks of Coldingham, in pure
                  and perpetual alms, the homage and service that Patrick Scott
                  of Reston used to owe to me and my heirs for the land which
                  the same Patrick and his heirs gave for his homage and
                  service from my land in the grassland of Reston with all
                  escheats, without any withholding, which could fall to me or
                  my heirs from the said land. And I, Robert, and my heirs,
                  shall acquit the said Patrick and his heirs or assigns of all
                  forinsec service belonging to the said land, as well towards
                  the lord king as towards the house of Coldingham, except what
                  the said Patrick and his heirs or assigns return annually to
                  the house of Coldingham, 6 pence at the feast of St John the
                  Baptist as ferme.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And that this my donation should remain firm, I have applied my seal to the
                  present writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord W<ex>illiam</ex> of Mordington; the lord Alan of Swinton; Adam of Prenderguest; Geoffrey Ridel;
                     Adam of Reston; Bertram his son; Maurice of Ayton; John
                     son of Elias; Adam, clerk of Prenderguest; Ralph the
                     grieve; Ralph the sergeant; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>