<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 675</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-02 13:02:56.801876+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 675</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Thomas the Prior, and the Convent of the church of Durham</seg>, to all to whom the present written deed shall come : <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting in the Lord.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">since I have examined the Charters of the lady Ada of Paxton, Robert her own
                     first-born, Robert and William her sons, clerks, her own
                     daughters, Cecilia and Matilda, and of Ogier of Tyas our
                     clerk, prepared in the form of a Cyrograph, and confirmed
                     by the application of their seals, by which they had
                     granted and handed over to our same clerk, Ogier of Tyas,
                     all their fisheries in Paxton upon the Tweed with all
                     liberties, easements, and all other things pertaining to
                     the same fisheries, without any withholding, for the same
                     Ogier and his heirs or assignees to have and to hold, from
                     the feast of Saint Martin in the winter, in the 1236th
                     year of the Lord, until the term of nine years following
                     is completed</seg> : We, very much approving the donation and grant between the aforementioned Ada,
                     Robert the first-born, Robert and William her sons, the
                     clerks, Cecilia and Matilda her daughters, and the said
                     Ogier de Tyas, made concerning the fisheries of Paxton
                     described before, have considered them to be confirmed
                     exactly as it is the more fully contained in the charters
                     described above; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">and we have caused them to be reinforced by the protection of the present
                     written deed to which is appended our seal.</seg> Saving the wardships contingent on the churches of Durham and of Coldingham.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>