<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 616</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-06 15:19:33.971737+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 616</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">Alexander, by the Grace of God King of the Scots, To all worthy men of his whole
                  land, Clerk and lay : <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know that</seg> I have granted, and by this my charter made firm to Robert de Aubein, and to his
                     heirs, those twenty merks which is owed annually as
                     waiting which the Prior and Convent of Coldingham owe to
                     me for their lands at Coldingham, until I or my heirs
                     shall have given to Robert, or to his heirs, twenty merks’
                     worth of land on the south side of the Sea of Scotia, or
                     between the Mounth and the Sea of Scotia. Wherefore I
                     will, that the aforesaid Robert de Aubein, and his heirs,
                     should receive those twenty merks each year at Easter. And
                     I command the Prior of Coldingham, and his Baillies, that
                     they should pay those twenty merks to them at Easter,
                     without hindrance until I or my heirs shall have given to
                     them the aforesaid twenty merks’ worth of land, just as
                     the Charter of the lord King, William my father, produced
                     on the matter for the aforesaid Robert, bears witness. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses : William del Bois, my Chancellor; William de Valognes, my
                  Chamberlain; Philip de Mowbray; Geoffrey son of Richard,
                  sheriff of Perth; Philip of Lundin.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Perth, on the third day of March.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>