<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5960</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.728883+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5960</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all the faithful of holy Mother Church, clerk and lay, as well present as
                  future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert, by the grace of God bishop of St Andrews</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Be it known to you all that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">we have granted and, so far as it belongs to episcopal authority, have made firm
                  by the testimony and guarantee of the present charter the
                  donation which Cospatric brother of Dolfin granted and gave
                  in everlasting alms to God and Saint Cuthbert and his monks,
                  that is, Edrom with the church, and the toun which is called
                  Nisbet, with waters, meadows and pastures and mills, and all
                  other things that belong to the same touns, just as the
                  charter of the King and of Cospatric bear witness.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Be is also known to you all that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">we, by episcopal authority, have granted and made firm to God and to Saint
                  Cuthbert and to his monks, the church of Swinton and the
                  church of Fishwick, in perpetual alms.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">And this we have made by the prayer and counsel of our venerable brothers,
                  Robert the prior of St Andrews, Thomas the prior of Scone,
                  Osbert the prior of Jedburgh, Osbert the prior of Holyrood,
                  Adam the king's chaplain at Roxburgh, and many others
                  residing with us at the synod which sat at Berwick</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">on the 8th of the kalends of November [25 October], in the year of the Lord's
                  incarnation, 1150.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>