<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 1330</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-10-31 20:44:43.378593+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 1330</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard, by the grace of God bishop of St Andrews, Æthelred abbot of Rievaulx,
                     and William abbot of Melrose,</seg> to all sons of holy Mother Church <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">send greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">We notify your aimiability</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">that at Berwick, by the command of Alexander, by the grace of God supreme
                  pontiff, we concluded the dispute which there was between the
                  church of Durham and the church of Kelso over the chapel of
                  Earlston according to the tenor of the letters of the lord
                  pope, which is such, that is to say, that if the prior of
                  Durham was able to prove forty-year title without
                  interruption in respect of the chapel of Earlston, that we
                  would impose on the monks of the church of Kelso in respect
                  of the aforenamed chapel restraint from all appeal and the
                  laying-aside of accusation.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="injunction">The forty-year title having been proved, therefore, by canonical oath-swearing,
                  in our presence, of 12 priests, one deacon, and two laymen,
                  we have imposed restraint on the aforesaid monks concerning
                  the aforenamed chapel, and adjudged it to the church of
                  Durham in perpetuity.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witness Osbert the abbot of Jedburgh, Nicholas the chancellor, Andrew the
                  archdeacon of Lothian, Aiulf and Joce the deans, Robert the
                  canon of St Andrews, Master Herbert, Elias of Ilderton,
                  Hervey and Eilaf the chaplains of Berwick, Romfar the
                  chaplain, Alan the priest of Hilton, Alan the priest of
                  Wallsend, Master Gocelin.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>