<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 5945</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 13:36:57.964856+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 5945</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful to whom the present writing shall have come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert son of Reginald</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">moved by divine love and for the soul of my father and of all my ancestors, and
                  for the salvation of my own soul, and especially for the soul
                  of Nicholas, son of Adam, whose death has been attributed to
                  me, to have given, granted, and made firm by this my charter,
                  in pure, free, and everlasting alms, to God, Saint Mary, to
                  the prior, and to the monks of Coldingham serving God in that
                  place now and for ever in the future, thirteen acres and one
                  rood in the territory of Great Reston in three places; that
                  is, in Billieside and <ex>Sonƿiwesacre</ex> and in <ex>Holewaye</ex>; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to have and to hold for ever, as freely, quitely, fully, and honourably as any
                     alms in the kingdom of Scotland is freely, quitely, fully,
                     and honourably held or possessed</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I, Robert, and my heir, shall warrant the said thirteen acres and one rood
                     to the said prior and monks against all men and women; and
                     we shall defend and acquit them in all services and aids,
                     both towards the lord king and also the house of
                     Coldingham.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord William of Lindsay; the lord William of
                  Mordington; the lord Alan of Swinton; the lord Adam of
                  Prenderguest; Robert, Alexander, William of Paxton; William,
                  clerk of the lord prior; John son of Elias of Ayton; Maurice
                  of Ayton; Bertram of Reston; Robert son of Gregory; Ralph the
                  grieve; Roger his son; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>