<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 1201</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 17:01:18.08898+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 1201</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div><p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Thomas, prior, and the chapter of St Cuthbert of the church of Durham,</seg> to all Holy Mother Church's sons present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">us to have given, conceded, and by this our charter to have made firm, to R<ex>obert</ex> son of Goze, our clerk, the church of Ednam with the entire land and all the
                     tofts and crofts belonging to the same church, and with
                     the three chapels of the same church, that is to say, the
                     chapel of Stichill, the chapel of Nenthorn, and the chapel
                     of Newton, and with all benefices belonging to the same
                     church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held of Saint Cuthbert and us for his life, freely and quitly from all
                     service that pertains to us, except that he shall give to
                     us yearly as recognition sixteen merks at three terms, 5
                     merks within the octave of the Purification of Saint Mary,
                     5 merks within the octave of Saint John the Baptist, and 6
                     merks within the octave of Saint Cuthbert in September.</seg> And he shall discharge all episcopal dues and customs, and when the prior or
                     monks of Durham shall pass through there he shall provide
                     suitable lodging for them and provide for their needs. And
                     if the dedication of the chapels should have happened, he
                     shall cover the expenditure. These things have I conceded,
                     however, to the same R<ex>obert</ex>, so long as he shall maintain the aforesaid agreement. The same R<ex>obert</ex> has indeed sworn that he shall faithfully maintain and not question the
                     aforesaid agreement by any craft or trickery so that we
                     are the loser in respect of the same church. For as long
                     as Goze, his father, shall live and shall wish to be in
                     the secular world, he shall have custody of the said
                     Rodbert and the same church; but if Robert should have
                     died before the said Goze, his father, Goze shall hold the
                     church by the same agreement. R<ex>obert</ex> has provided as pledge to this agreement Abbot Osbert and the community of
                     Jedburgh.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: John, archdeacon; Master Thomas de Vaux; Robert de
                  Fribois; S<ex>imon</ex> de Camera; John de Raine; Ingram, Elias, and W., the bishop's clerks; R., priest
                     of Selkirk; Dolfin, priest; William, priest; and Sigmund,
                     priest.</seg></p> <p> </p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>