<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 7162</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 16:22:01.895383+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 7162</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">M<ex>alcolm</ex> king of the Scots,</seg> to bishops, abbots, earls and barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts and
                     officials, French and English, Gaelic and Galwegian, clerk
                     and lay, and all men of his entire land, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> after I assumed knighthood, I gave, granted, and by this my charter made firm,
                     to Walter son of Alan, my steward, Birkenside and
                     Legerwood by their correct boundaries, that is to say,
                     fully and entirely, just as King David, my grandfather
                     held the said lands in demesne. I have also given Mow to
                     the said Walter by its correct boundaries, and with all
                     its lawful pertinents, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for him and his heirs to hold and to have of me and my heirs in feu and
                     heritage, as freely and quitly, fully and honourably, as
                     any earl or baron holds and possesses any land of me
                     freely, fully, and honourably,</seg> performing for the said lands to me and my heirs the service of one knight.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Arnold the bishop of St Andrews, Herbert the bishop of
                  Glasgow, John the abbot of Kelso, William the abbot of
                  Melrose, Obser the abbot of Jedburgh, Walter the chancellor,
                  William the king's brother, Richard de Morville, Gilbert de
                  Umfraville, Waldeve the brother of Earl Cospatric, Jordan
                  Ridel.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Roxburgh.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>