<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 987*</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 10:59:47.521895+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 987*</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard, by the grace of God a humble servant of the church of St Andrew,</seg> to all sons of Holy Mother Church, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let both them who shall come as well as those present know </seg>us to have granted, and by this our charter to have made firm, to the church of
                     Durham, and to the monks who shall in perpetuity serve God
                     there, the church of St Laurence at Berwick, in
                     everlasting alms, according to the agreement which has
                     been made between them and the monks of Kelso. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore, I will and instruct by episcopal authority, that the aforesaid monks
                     freely, quitly, honourably hold and possess it for ever,
                     just as the monks of Kelso previously held it</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">Witness, Andrew, archdeacon of Lothian; Walter, archdeacon of St Andrews;
                  Geoffrey, abbot of Dunfermline; John, abbot of Holyrood;
                  Amfred, abbot of Newbattle; Roger, abbot of Dryburgh; Aiulf
                  and Patrick, deans; Geoffrey of Lasswade; Robert of Perth;
                  Alexander and Albinus, chaplains; Geoffrey, clerk, of
                  Tyninghame.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">This [agreement <ex>deleted</ex>] charter was made and given in our full synod in the church of St Cuthbert at
                     Edinburgh.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>