<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of DCA DCD Misc. Ch. 714</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-11-01 12:40:59.663423+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Durham</settlement>
            <repository>Durham Cathedral Archives</repository>
            <idno>DCD Misc. Ch. 714</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">I, William de Vaux,</seg> have given, and granted, and by this my present charter have made firm to God
                     and Saint Cuthbert of Durham and the holy monks serving
                     God and Saint Cuthbert there, one toft in Gullane, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">that is the toft which lies nearest the croft of the hospital of St John of
                     Jerusalem towards the south, as long as the aforesaid
                     croft of Saint John is broad; and one perch of land which
                     Udard the fisherman held in the aforementioned toun, that
                     is the perch of land which lies nearest the croft of
                     William Smallware towards the north, and the northern edge
                     of Swindgthates, as it has gone out from Gullane towards
                     the large stone which lies outside Windgthates, towards
                     the north, and so upwards as the land of Saint Cuthbert
                     was perambulated and measured.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">I also will that Osmund of Gullane and his heirs should hold the aforesaid toft,
                     and the aforementioned perch of land, and the
                     aforementioned edge, as freely, quitly, and honourably as
                     any alms is most freely and quitly held or possessed in
                     the whole kindgom of Scotland, by rendering annually to
                     the aforesaid monks four pence at the feast of Saint
                     Michael in return for every service</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Robert Hotoft, Gregory of Fenton, Walter of Lindsay,
                  Richard Sans Avoir, Richard son of Seleburh, Godard the
                  chaplain, Gummer the chaplain, Simon the clerk, Gilbert the
                  butler of Gullane, Robert son of Adam of Dirleton.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>