<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 81</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 15:11:42.774104+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 81</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard, by the grace of God bishop of Dunkeld</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting and episcopal blessing</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="arenga">Since to augment the worship of holy religion belongs to our office,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">let those to come as well as those present know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">that I have granted and by this my charter made firm, to the abbot of
                  Dunfermline and to the monks serving God in that place, the
                  donation of King Malcolm and of Andrew bishop of Caithness,
                  according to that which is attested in their charters: the
                  church of the Holy Trinity at Dunkeld and all the lands
                  rightfully belonging to it, free and quit from all exaction
                  of the ecclesiastical as well as of the secular person,
                  saving episcopal right. I also allow them their mode of
                  living in my bishopric, and that they may perform their
                  divine office and have the cure of souls of those under their
                  authority; and that, living in my diocese, they may receive
                  from me that which concerns Christianity.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Matthew, archdeacon of St Andrews; Brice, prior of Inch<ex>colm</ex>; Michael the clerk; Master Matthew; and John, his brother; Robert the bishop’s
                     steward; Ralph the chaplain; Thomas the presbyter; Murdoch
                     the clerk; Abraham Small.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>