<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 31</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-06 15:37:23.25589+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 31</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">In the 1234th year since the Incarnation of the Lord, at Easter, this agreement
                  was made between William Comyn the Clerk on the one side, and
                  the prior and religious community of St Andrews on the other,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">namely that the said William has handed over to them to ferm the church of Dul,
                  with chapels, lands, teinds, obventions, and all other things
                  pertaining to the said church by rendering to him each year
                  for the whole of his life sixty-seven merks, that is,
                  twenty-two merks at the feast of Saint Martin, and twenty-two
                  merks at the Purification of Blessed Mary, and twenty-one
                  merks at Easter, and by answering for episcopal and synodal
                  dues. And it is to be known that the said Prior and community
                  shall retain for themselves the remainder each year in return
                  for three merks as a pension owed to the said William from
                  the said church of Dul. If, however, it should happen that
                  the said Prior and community should cease the payment of the
                  said money at the stated terms, by every week counted from
                  each term, they shall pay out as a penalty half a merk until
                  the aforesaid money has been paid according to the delay of
                  the payment.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And that this agreement might have enduring strength and durability, to the part
                  of this cyrograph remaining in the possession of the prior
                  and community has been affixed the seal of the said William.
                  And to the part remaining in the possession of William has
                  been affixed the seal of the chapter of St Andrews.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the Chapter of St Andrews; the lord M(alcolm), archdeacon
                  of Aberdeen; Gerard, dean of Fife; W(illiam) of Nydie, clerk
                  of the lord king; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>