<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 33</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 13:00:13.582348+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 33</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">P<ex>atrick</ex> and W<ex>ido/Guy</ex>, abbots of Dunfermline and of Lindores, and H<ex>ugh</ex>, prior of Pittenweem</seg> : To all to whose attention and understanding the content of the present written
                     document shall have come : <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting in the Lord.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">May your fraternity know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">that, with the mandate of Innocent the lord Pope having been received by us, we
                  have been enjoined either to decide by a judgment the dispute
                  which Ranulf, archdeacon of St Andrews, brought against Hugh
                  the Steward and Jordan his nephew over the lands on the west
                  side of the new work standing opposite the dwellings of
                  Lamburc, and which he was claiming to belong to his own
                  archdeaconry, having called together and heard the parties;
                  or to impose an end to the dispute by mediating an agreement.
                  The parties therefore having been called together several
                  times, with William, lord bishop of St Andrews, acting as
                  mediator, and standing between the two sides, with us also
                  discharging authority and employing effort and diligence, it
                  was agreed between the parties so that Hugh the Steward and
                  Jordan his nephew resigned and quitclaimed those lands for
                  the future, and the buildings in them that were built by
                  them, to R<ex>anulf</ex> the archdeacon and to his successors. And R<ex>anulf</ex> the archdeacon himself has given to Hugh the Steward, in return for making the
                     resignation and for the sake of peace, 15 merks, and to
                     Jordan 10 merks and four perches of land that he had
                     received from T<ex>homas</ex> the prior and his community near the dwelling of Simon the clerk on the east
                     side, for Jordan and his heirs to hold of him and his
                     successors by paying one pound of cumin yearly. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And so that this authoritative agreement should stand firm and remain unchanged
                  in perpetuity, to be observed without violation, it has been
                  reinforced and made firm by the application of the seal of
                  the lord bishop as well as our own.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord T<ex>homas</ex> the prior, and the community; Andrew of Moray; Master Adam; Master Stephen;
                     Master Isaac; Master Simon; William of Crail, dean;
                     William, chaplain of Brechin; William of Dairsie; Peter
                     and Edward, the chaplains of the lord bishop; John of
                     Haltwhistle; William of Gullane; John of London; Ralph
                     Niger; John the marischal; Simon de Noisy; Eutrope the
                     dispenser; Peter and Hugh of Nydie and Robert of Calder,
                     man-servants of the lord bishop; William Lambin; Gilbert
                     Breton; Simon the clerk.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>