<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 10</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-02-15 08:50:19.330973+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 10</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Arnald by the grace of God humble servant of the church of Saint Andrew the
                     apostle</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting. </seg></seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="arenga">It belongs to a bishop’s duty to have a care for the peace of those who live
                  according to a monastic rule, so that those who rest in God
                  within are not burdened by troubles without.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">Guided by this consideration, and having regard for the peace of the canons who
                  will in the future serve God in the church of blessed Andrew
                  the apostle, we have decreed that every offering of their
                  altar which the seven parsons not living in community
                  formerly held, which is divided into seven parts, is to be
                  granted to the aforesaid canons who have professed a regular
                  life and live in community, whole, entire and complete, with
                  reasonable and necessary provision. For, those who serve at
                  the altar ought to live of the altar, and according to the
                  rules of the decretals, portions ought not to be made of the
                  offerings where the community of the living makes a unity of
                  all that is possessed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">And so we grant to the aforenamed canons every offering of the altar at which
                  they serve, quit and free and without disbursement of parts.
                  And by the writing of the present page we confirm what is to
                  be held by perpetual right. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: William bishop of Moray, legate of the Apostolic See;
                  Gregory, bishop of Dunkeld; Andrew of Caithness, Samson of
                  Brechin, bishops; Geoffrey, abbot of Dunfermline; William,
                  abbot of Melrose; Alured, abbot of Stirling; Isaac, prior of
                  Scone; Walter, prior of Kelso; Matthew the archdeacon;
                  Thorald, archdeacon of Lothian; Master Andrew; Master
                  Herbert; Robert son of Sæwulf, the bishop’s chancellor; Roger
                  the chaplain of Perth; Nicholas the king’s chancellor;
                  Richard the king’s chaplain; Serlo the clerk; David Oliphant;
                  Ferteth, earl of Strathearn; Malcolm, earl of Atholl; Gille
                  Brigte, earl of Angus; Duncan, earl of Fife; Merleswain; Ness
                  son of William; Stephen the clerk.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>