<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 42</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 14:28:26.644818+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 42</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Hugh de Mortimer</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends Greeting</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let those to come as well as those present know</seg> t<seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">hat I have granted and by this my charter made firm, to God and to the Canons of
                  the Church of St Andrews, the Chapel of Fowlis together with
                  the land that went with it before Fowlis was given to William
                  Maule my grandfather, and with ten acres of land which the
                  same William gave to the said Chapel as an addition, and with
                  teinds and oblations, and with everything pertaining to the
                  same Chapel, in perpetual alms, for the welfare of my soul,
                  and of my wife’s, and for the souls of my ancestors and
                  successors. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I firmly will that the aforesaid Canons hold and possess the
                     aforementioned Chapel free and quit from every secular
                     service and exaction, and without my or my heirs’ claiming
                     it back, just as freely and quietly as they hold and
                     possess their other alms in Scot[ia <ex>or</ex> Scotland]</seg>. I have also allowed to the said Canons the teind of my mill and common pasture
                     according to the easement of my feu at Fowlis, namely, for
                     eight oxen, and ten cows, and three horses, and 100 sheep.
                     I have also allowed to the same Canons that there be
                     support of the said livestock in that pasture for one
                     year, the first after giving birth, just as it is more
                     fully set out in the charter of the aforesaid William;</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">and that this my grant should maintain the force of perpetual endurance, I have
                  caused it to be confirmed by the reinforcement of the present
                  written document with the application of my seal.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With theses witnesses: the lord William, bishop of St Andrews; Master Laurence,
                  archdeacon of St Andrews; Master Adam Ovid; Master Alexander
                  de Saint-Martin; Master David of Bernham; the lord Simon de
                  Noisy; William of Gullen; John of Haddington; and many
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>