<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 27</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 10:59:52.971677+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 27</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>I<seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">n the 1222nd year since the Incarnation of the Lord this agreement was made
                  between the lord S<ex>imon</ex>, prior of St Andrews and the religious community of the same place on the one
                     side, and on the other, Gillemuire the scoloc of Tarland,
                     their liegeman and neyf: namely that the same G<ex>illemuire</ex>, as their neyf and liegeman shall have permission to be with the lord J<ex>ames</ex>, son of M<ex>organ</ex> of good memory, late earl of Mar, for as long as it pleases the prior and
                     community, so that G<ex>illemuire</ex> and his children, with all their belongings, without any objection or any
                     impediment, should be returned to the said prior and
                     convent as their neyfs when it shall pease the said prior
                     and community; and they shall assign to them a suitable
                     dwelling place in good faith. And if G<ex>illemuire</ex> or his children should remain for a year or more with the said lord J<ex>ames</ex>, the same G<ex>illemuire</ex> or his children shall pay one pound of wax annually on the Assumption of Blessed
                     Mary in recognition of their homage to the said prior and
                     community.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And because the same G<ex>illemuire</ex> does not have his own seal, he has caused this agreement to be sealed with the
                     seal of the said lord J<ex>ames</ex> son of M<ex>organ</ex> the earl of Mar.</seg> And for greater security, the aforementioned G<ex>illemuire</ex>, touching holy relics, swore that he would faithfully uphold this agreement in
                  good faith without any objection. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord D<ex>uncan</ex>, son of M<ex>organ</ex>, late earl of Mar; the lord J<ex>ames</ex>, his brother; the lord P<ex>hilip</ex> de Malville, sheriff of Aberdeen; the lord R<ex>obert</ex> of Strathearn; Beldin, judex of Fern; William, chaplain of Tarland; Adam of
                     Cushnie; Mael Domnaig mac Gilla Doraid; Gilleserf of
                     Ruthven.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>