<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 46</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 14:44:15.970612+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 46</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church to whom the present written deed shall come,
                  Henry Revel and Margaret his spouse send Greeting in the
                  Lord:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">You should all know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">we have given, and granted, and by this our present charter made firm, to God
                  and to the Church of St Andrew the apostle in Scotia, and to
                  the Canons in that place serving God now and in the future,
                  in pure and perpetual alms, the land that lies from Coultra
                  northwards, and from the the road that goes from Balmerino to
                  Coultra westwards, just as I, the aforesaid Henry Revel, and
                  Rcihard Revel my nephew, and Matthew the Canon, with my
                  worthy men, perambulated for fifteen acres, with the common
                  pasture that belongs to so much land, for my soul and the
                  soul of Margaret my spouse, and for the souls of our
                  ancestors and successors. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore we will that the aforesaid Canons have and possess the aforesaid land
                     as free and quit from every secular service and exaction,
                     just as they hold and possess any land free and quit in
                     the whole of the kingdom of Scotland</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Richard Revel; Josse of Ballindard; Ralph the chaplain;
                  Adam of Airdit; Robert son of Arnold; Robert son of Geoffrey;
                  Odo of Corbrig; Maurice the clerk; Adam de Bruneie; and many
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>