<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 32</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 11:08:39.630801+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 32</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall view the present letters, Master William of Parma, Chaplain of
                  the Lord Pope and <ex>auditor contradictarum</ex> of the same, Greeting in the Lord:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">You should know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">when Ralph de Helig’, clerk, procurator admitted by special mandate of the the
                  lord pope, on behalf of the provost and chapter of the church
                  of St Mary, of St Andrews in Scotia, petitioned for apostolic
                  letters under this form: Innocent the bishop, etc., To his
                  beloved sons, the Provost and Chapter of the church of St
                  Mary, of St Andrews in Scotia, Greeting etc. When what is
                  requested from us is just and worthy, the force of equity as
                  well as the order of reason require that it should be carried
                  through to its due effect by the consideration of our office.
                  Therefore, beloved sons in the Lord, we gladly approve and
                  consent to your just requests, and we take under the
                  protection of St Peter and ourselves the churches,
                  possessions, and your other goods which you reasonbly possess
                  now or which by just means and God’s gift you will be able to
                  acquire in the future, and we confirm them to you and your
                  church by apostolic authority and defend them by the
                  protection of the present document. Therefore let no one etc.
                  If, however, anyone etc. Given at Lyons on 12 Kalends of
                  September [21 August], in the seventh year of our
                  pontificate. Peter de Vercelli, procurator of the prior and
                  chapter of the cathedral church of St Andrews in Scotia,
                  objected to the same letter on their behalf in public
                  audience, but in the end withdrew on the condition that any
                  prejudice should not be generated by the aforesaid letters to
                  the privileges of the aforesaid prior and chapter of the
                  catehdral church of St Andrews, nor be used in any way to
                  impede the jusrisdiction of the executors of the same
                  priviliges, which the other party firmly promised in our
                  sight</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter we have caused the present letters to be made and
                  protected by our seal.</seg> Given at Lyons on the 2 Ides of of September [12 September] in the seventh year
                  of the pontificate of the lord pope, Innocent IV.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>