<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 16</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2022-09-14 01:16:58.08343+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 16</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church who shall view or hear the present document, <persName>David</persName> and <persName>Albin</persName>, bishops by the grace of God, of St Andrews and of Brechin, and Master <persName>Abel</persName>, chaplain of the lord Pope and archdeacon of St Andrews, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">wish eternal salvation in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">We have inspected the mandate of the bishops of the kingdom of Scotland in these
                  words:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">To their most excellent lord, A<ex>lexander</ex>, by the grace of God illustrious king of Scot<ex>s</ex>, David, William, Peter, Clement, Albin, Robert, William, servants of the
                     churches of St Andrews, <span data-dpt="place" data-dpt-cat="chars" data-dpt-type="name">Glasgow</span>, Aberdeen, Dunblane, Brechin, Ross, Caithness, wish health and ever faithful
                     and devoted allegience. Although those things that had
                     been appointed during the last council celebrated at
                     Edinburgh, where you and to your magnates were present,
                     have hardly been put in writing, we nevertheless do not
                     believe that they have been forgotten by your counsellors,
                     namely, that the churches and their prelates might rejoice
                     in the peaceful possession of all rights and liberties
                     which they had during the time of King Alexander your
                     father of happy memory, saving your right and your
                     possession in all things. Yet now a certain new thing
                     previously unheard of in the kingdom of Scotland has been
                     introduced by your counsellors, namely that ecclesiastical
                     persons may be deprived by laymen of their ecclesiastical
                     possessions granted in alms without a judicial inquiry of
                     their prelates taking place, as lately we heard from the
                     prior of St Andrews to have happened. Since, however,
                     these things and things like them, against God, and
                     ecclesiastical liberty ... ought not to pass by
                     unregarded, we humbly and devotedly entreat your
                     Excellency, that what among the goods of the said prior
                     has been irreverently and inconsiderately appropriated,
                     having first considered our appeals, you would please in
                     no way permit similar things to be done in future.
                     Otherwise we shall expose ourselves instead to however
                     many dangers, a more inestimable injury to the church than
                     we would wish to sustain in the future. May your
                     Excellency ever have strength in the Lord. In testimony of
                     this matter we have caused our seal to be affixed to the
                     present document.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>