<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 41</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 13:04:55.077741+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 41</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, Saer de Quincy sends greeting:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all people know, present as well as future,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">that I have granted and by this my charter made firm, to God and to the church
                  of St Andrew the apostle in Scotia, and to the canons serving
                  God there now and in the future, the davoch of lower Ethie by
                  its right marches, which my mother gave to them, in pastures,
                  in meadows, in wood, in plain, in moors, in waters, with all
                  easements pertaining to that land; to be held of me and my
                  heirs in perpetual alms, for the salvation of my soul and my
                  ancestors’ and successors’ souls. I also allow them common
                  pasture throughout the whole of Ethie. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the aforesaid canons shall have, hold and possess the
                     aforesaid alms as freely, quietly and honourably as they
                     freely, quietly and honourably hold and possess any alms,
                     just as the charter of my mother bears witness</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Robert de Quincy, my father; Stephen, parson of Leuchars;
                  Alan the chaplain; John the steward; William the chaplain;
                  Uhting his brother; Constant<ex>ine</ex> and Patrick, sons of my grandfather, Ness; Duncan, son of Hamelin; Siward.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>