<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 71</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 15:09:36.753586+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 71</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">Richard, by the grace of God humble servant of the church of St Andrews, to all
                  sons of Holy Mother Church, clerk and lay, Greeting:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="arenga">Since we know that it is our responsibility to build up the Church of God, and
                  to change for the better those things that have been built,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">we have judged worthy to be confirmed those things that belong to the church of
                  Dunfermline, to take them under the tranquillity of our peace
                  and to confirm them by our charter. Instructed and supported
                  by the Lord’s authority, we have notified those absent as
                  well as those present that we have granted, and by our
                  charter made firm, that the aforementioned church should
                  possess the churches and their possessions, and all
                  ecclesiastical benefices that have been bestowed in alms to
                  the same by the generosity of kings, prelates, and other
                  faithful people, as freely and honourably and quit from every
                  service and exaction as any church well and honourably and
                  freely and quietly holds and possesses its possessions in the
                  whole of our bishopric, namely, the church of Perth, and the
                  school of the same toun, the castle chapel, and the church of
                  St Leonard, the church of Friarton, the church of Stirling,
                  the school of the same toun, and castle chapel, and the rest
                  of the things rightfully belonging to them, the church of
                  Kellie, and the church of Crombie, and the church of Newburn,
                  and the church of Kinglassie, and the chapel of
                  Inverkeithing, and the church of Inveresk, and the chapel of
                  Cousland, and the teinds of Keith, the church of Woolmet, and
                  the church of Hailes with all its belongings, and the church
                  of Newton, and the church of West Calder, saving episcopal
                  right and custom.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: G<ex>regory</ex>, bishop of Dunkeld; W<ex>illiam</ex>, abbot of Holyrood; W<ex>alter</ex>, prior of St Andrews; M<ex>atthew</ex>, archdeacon; A<ex>ndrew</ex>, archdeacon of Lothian; Aiulfo, dean; John, nephew of Bishop Robert; Roberto,
                     son of Seolf; Master Herbert; A<ex>lexander</ex>, chaplain; Master Bartholomew; Master Turpin; Master Abraham; Simon, the
                     archdeacon’s chaplain.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>