<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 34</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 13:02:49.269447+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 34</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall view or hear this written deed, Ralph, by divine permission
                  humble servant of the church of Aberdeen, wishes eternal
                  salvation in the lord.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">You should all know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">we, moved by charitable love, and at the presentation of the prior and religious
                  community of St Andrews, have given, granted, and by this our
                  charter made firm to Robert de la Runce, our chaplain, the
                  vicarage of the church of Bourtie, and have canonically
                  instituted him in the same with the land of that church and
                  the teind of the same land, and with all its obventions and
                  pertinents, saving to the aforementioned canons the land
                  assigned for the lighting of the church. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore we will that the aforementioned Robert should hold and possess the
                     aforementioned vicarage as freely and quietly as any vicar
                     freely and quietly holds and possesses any vicarage in our
                     diocese, saving episcopal dues</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">In testimony whereof we have affixed our seal to the present deed. As witnesses:
                  Master Hugh del Bois; Master Ralph del Bois; Master Richard,
                  our official of Aberdeen; the lord Stephen, our steward; the
                  lord John de Soutra, our chaplain; Andrew, Henry, William,
                  and Roger, our clerks; and others</seg>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>