<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 37</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-06 15:40:12.68473+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 37</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">In the One-thousand-two-hundred-and-forty-seventh year since the Incarnation of
                  the Lord, when a suit was moved between John the lord prior,
                  and the religious community of St Andrews, on the one side,
                  over land that Robert King bequeathed in his last will to the
                  said canons serving God and Saint Andrew, for the sake of his
                  own soul and of his ancestors’ and successors’, and Goda, the
                  daughter of the brother of the said Robert on the other side,
                  an agreement of the following nature was made between the
                  parties in full court;</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">namely, that the said prior and religious community have given to the said Goda
                  thirty shillings sterling as an exchange; and they have given
                  and also granted to the same G<ex>oda</ex> and to her heirs a land in the toun of Aberdeen, which Robert Petith donated to
                     the said canons for God and his soul independently, or the
                     rent of the aforementioned land to be received annually,
                     paying yearly from the said land, for the sake of
                     brotherly love, to the aforementioned canons serving God
                     and Saint Andrew, one pound of cumin at the fair of the
                     apostles Peter and Paul. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">The said Goda has sworn in full court for herself and her heirs that she would
                     faithfully abide by all the aforesaid things, and that she
                     shall warrant the said land to the aforementioned prior
                     and canons against all men and women; and the aforenamed
                     prior and religious community shall warrant to the said
                     Goda and her heirs that they will faithfully abide by all
                     the aforesaid things without scruple or deceit.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">The prior and community caused the common seal of the chapter to be affixed to
                  the part of the agreement which remains with Goda and her
                  heirs. To the other part was affixed the common seal of the
                  toun of St Andrews.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: the chapter of St Andrews, and the court of the same toun.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>