<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 47</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 14:47:47.651369+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 47</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Walter Young of Roxburgh</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">You should all know</seg> t<seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">hat I have granted and quitclaimed to Ranulf, archdeacon of St Andrews, and to
                  his successors in perpetuity, Scoonie, and Balkaithley, and
                  the land that lies on the south side of the city of St
                  Andrews, between the burns, the lands which Walter of blessed
                  memory, archdeacon of the same place, my uncle, held and
                  possessed during his lifetime, which after his time I myself
                  also had and possessed. I have also resigned to the aforesaid
                  archdeacon, Ranulf, the whole right that I had in the
                  aforesaid lands, either from gift, or from grant, or else
                  from confirmation of Bishop Hugh of blessed memory, or my
                  uncle Archdeacon Walter; and I returned the charters which I
                  had concerning those lands to the same aforenamed Ranulf when
                  I knew them to belong to the archdeaconry of St Andrews;</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">and so that this grant and resignation be established and firm for the future, I
                  have reinforced them by the application of the seals of the
                  lord R(alph), bishop of Brechin, and H(enry), abbot of
                  Arbroath, and mine, hanging from the present page, wishing
                  faith to be had in its wording and content in the future.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: R(alph), bishop of Brechin; H(enry), abbot of Arbroath,
                  and the religious community of the same place; ... archdeacon
                  of Brechin; William and Peter, chaplain of the lord [bishop]
                  of Brechin; Henry, chaplain of Montrose; Hervey, parson of
                  Inchbraoch; Alan, clerk of Montrose; Roger of Inverkeithing;
                  Herbert of Montrose; William son of Áed; Stephen the Mair;
                  Robert of Hailes; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>