<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 20</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-12-20 15:32:42.542833+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 20</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William, by the grace of God Bishop of St Andrews,</seg> to all who shall view or hear these letters, wishes <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">eternal salvation in the Lord</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know us all of you</seg>,<seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"> at the request of Adam of Kinninmonth, to have granted and by this our charter
                  to have made firm to William son of Lambin and his heirs, the
                  ploughgate of land, that is, Balrymont, which the
                  aforementioned Adam holds for his lifetime of the Prior and
                  religious community of St Andrews; for him and his heirs to
                  hold of the said Adam for as long as Adam of Kinninmonth
                  shall live; by rendering thereupon annually to the aforenamed
                  Adam one merk of silver, half at the feast of St Martin and
                  half at Pentecost. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore we will that the aforesaid William son of Lambin and his heirs shall
                     have, hold and possess the aforesaid land of Balrymont
                     with everything rightly pertaining to the aforesaid land,
                     as long as the aforenamed Adam of Kinninmonth shall live;
                     as freely and quietly, fully and honourably as the charter
                     of Adam of Kinninmonth bears witness.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Master Laurence, archdeacon of St Andrews; Peter and
                  Edward, our chaplains; John of Haltwhistle, Gervase de
                  Neaufles, Master Stephen, Master Michael, Geoffrey de
                  Neaufles, Peter of Dryburgh, our clerks; William of Wyville;
                  Malcolm the judex; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>