<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NLS Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 66</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2016-06-07 15:00:51.783125+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>Adv. MS 15.1.18, no. 66</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Malcolm, son of Morgan Earl of Mar,</seg> To all who shall view or hear these letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg></seg>: <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">I have granted, and by his my charter made firm, to God and to the church of St
                  Andrew the apostle in Scotia and the canons serving God in
                  that place now and in the future, the church of St Moluoc at
                  Tarland, which my father gave them, with teinds, and
                  oblations, and all revenues pertaining to the same church,
                  and the land which belongs to the said church, with a mill
                  built on the same land, and a ploughgate of land which is
                  called ‘Hachadgouan’ by its right marches; in pastures, in
                  meadows, in wood and plain, with all easements pertaining to
                  those lands, to be held of me and my heirs in perpetual alms,
                  for the welfare of my soul, and the souls of my ancestors and
                  successors. I also grant in perpetual alms the teind of my
                  whole render from my whole land, namely, of hides, grain,
                  cheese, flour, malt, fatted cattle, muttons, pigs, and of my
                  game, with meat and hides, and the teind of my pleas and
                  reliefs, in cash as well as other income. I also allow to
                  them that they may receive material from my woods for their
                  buildings, as much as they might need, and and that they
                  should have common pasture for their livestock with my own
                  livestock and the livestock of my own men on my lands without
                  any disturbance and annoyance. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the aforesaid canons should fully have and hold the
                     aforesaid alms of me and my heirs as freely and quietly as
                     they freely and quietly have and possess any alms in
                     Scotia</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses : Adam, bishop of Aberdeen; Omer the archdeacon; Alexander
                  the dean; Malcolm, William, Edward, Alan, canons; Master
                  William, John of Calder, clerks; James son of Morgan, Duncan
                  his brother, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>