<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/95</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 13:33:32.714656+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/95</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div><p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of holy Mother Church, both present and to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William de Morville</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> to have granted, and by this my present charter to have made firm, to God and to
                     the church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks serving
                     God in that place, in free and pure and perpetual alms,
                     the freedom and licence to plough and sow the whole land
                     of Blainslie, and the whole plain around the outside of
                     the wood down to the Leader, and to make good use of it
                     according to their will between its boundaries, except for
                     clearing woodland, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">as far as 'Windeslawe' and from there by the great road which descends by
                     'Windeslawe' towards Lauder, down to the boundaries of
                     Lauder,</seg> just as my father Richard de Morville gave them in free alms. This foresaid
                     liberty and licence I have granted to them at the request
                     of my father, and for the salvation of the souls of David
                     and Malcolm, late kings of the Scots, my lords, and for
                     the salvation of William, king of the Scots, my lord, and
                     for the salvation of my own soul, and of the soul of my
                     wife and of all my ancestors and successors. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the foresaid monks should have and possess the previously
                     named liberty and licence as freely and quitely in
                     everlasting alms, just as they possess any alms freely and
                     quitely and honourably</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow; Richard de Morville, my
                  father; Avice of Lancaster, my mother; Herbert, dean of
                  Glasgow; Clement the physician, chaplain; Adam, parson of the
                  church of Lauder; Roger the clerk, my father's steward; Alan
                  of Thirlestane; William Mansell, fintor [?founder <ex>or</ex> ?surveyor of boundaries*]; Herbert son of Robert; Alan of Clapham.</seg> </p> <p>*<ex>fintor</ex> is not attested; <ex>finitor </ex>is otherwise only attested in Classical Latin; <ex>funtor</ex>, 'founder', is the most likely reading.</p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>