<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/34</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 11:29:48.642851+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/34</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Roger of Skelbrooke</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends Greeting</seg></seg>: <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> to have granted, and to have given, and by this my charter to have made firm, to
                     God and to the church of St Mary at Melrose and to the
                     monks serving God in that place, for the salvation and the
                     soul of my lord Duncan son of Gilbert son of Fergus, and
                     for the souls of all his ancestors and successors, and for
                     the salvation of my own soul and of all my kindred and
                     heirs, in free and pure and perpetual alms, my fishery in
                     the mouth of the River Doon above <ex>Harenam</ex>, and one saltpan, and one pan, wheresoever they might wish in the whole of my
                     land of Greenan, and sufficient timber from my wood near
                     the said fishery and saltpan and for the enjoyment in all
                     ways of the brethren and their own men abiding there. I
                     have also granted to them one toft to inhabit where they
                     will near the sea shore, and another toft below my castle
                     at Greenan where they can keep their moveable goods and
                     cattle, and the parcel of arable land that is to the west
                     side of the old elm towards the former saltpan, and
                     pasture sufficient for six oxen and ten cows. All these
                     things have I granted and given to the said monks free and
                     quit and released from all earthly service, custom and
                     secular exaction. And I will that they have, hold and
                     possess them for all time in this wise freely and quietly,
                     fully and honourably, just as freely and quietly, fully
                     and honourably as they hold or possess any alms. And the
                     monks shall make use of all things described before as it
                     pleases them, and by all means, just as it might seem good
                     and useful to them and to their brethren and their men.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant to them all these things against all men and we
                  shall acquit every service which could be exacted in return
                  for any alms</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, the lord Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow, Simon the archdeacon, Duncan
                  my lord, Walter Corbet.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>