<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/142</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:07:42.590974+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/142</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall see or hear this written deed, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Walter son of Alan, steward of the lord king of Scotland</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let your whole community know that</seg> the land of Mow with its correct boundaries and with whatever is contained
                     within the same boundaries that I held in feu of the lord
                     William de Vescy I have given in exchange to the monks of
                     Melrose in return for a land that is called ‘Freretun’,
                     with all its pertinents, everything that the nuns of South
                     Berwick possessed in that place; and in addition, together
                     with the same land which is called ‘Freretun’, the same
                     monks have given me two hundred merks by reason of the
                     same exchange. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">I and my heirs shall warrant, defend and maintain this land of Mow with its
                     contents and its pertinents within its boundaries.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">As witness of this matter I have reinforced the present written deed by the
                     application of my seal.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Thomas Crook, Simon son of Bertolf, Adam Wallace, William
                  of Halkerston, Robert of Kippo, knights; William and Robert,
                  our chaplains; Leon de Normanville, Richard of Musselburgh,
                  John of Leicester, monks of Melrose; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>