<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/210</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 16:02:24.555125+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/210</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church present and to come <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">John son of Michael of Methil</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let your whole community know</seg> me to have given, granted, and by this my charter to have made firm to God and
                     to the church of St Mary at Melrose and to the monks
                     serving God in that place now and to come, my whole land
                     at Penshiel; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the same monks to hold and to have of me and my heirs in pure and perpetual
                     alms for ever; as freely, quitely, fully, and honourably
                     as any alms in the kingdom of Scotland is freely, quitely,
                     and fully held and possessed; in wood and plain, in lands
                     cultivated and uncultivated, in meadows and pastures, in
                     roads and paths, in moors, peat-bogs and marshes, in
                     running waters and ponds, fish-ponds and mills, and all
                     other easments that can be found or employed within the
                     said land.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and defend to the said monks the whole
                     aforesaid land with all its liberties and just pertinents
                     against all men; except for the land that I gave to the
                     monks of May, and except for the land that I allowed to
                     Henry Little and his heirs by its correct boundaries in
                     the territory of Penshiels.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">The whole aforesaid land, as it is said, the aforementioned monks shall hold and
                     have free and quit from every service, custom and exaction
                     and demand of me and my heirs for ever.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Thomas, earl of Atholl; Thomas of Kent; Master John the
                  Albigensian; Master Ness, physician of the lord king;
                  Geoffrey del Bois; James son of William; Andrew of Swinton;
                  and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>