<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/218</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 07:53:56.313607+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/218</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Philip of Pitcox</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have given and granted, and by this my charter to have made firm, out of
                     the good will and agreement of Philip my son and heir, to
                     God and to the church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the
                     monks in that place serving God, for the souls of my
                     lords, Cospatric, and Waldef, earls of Dunbar, and for the
                     souls of my father and mother, and of all my ancestors,
                     and for the salvation of my lord, P<ex>atrick</ex>, earl of Dunbar, and for my own salvation, and of P<ex>hilip</ex> my son and heir, and of all my successors, the land in the territory of Pitcox
                     which lies between the boundaries of the monks' land at
                     Hartside and the little stream that is called Pressmennan
                     Burn, which the aforesaid monks have annexed along the
                     aforesaid stream to their own land at Hartside by reason
                     of my donation and instruction; and ten acres in
                     ploughland at 'Beleside' most closely adjacent to their
                     land at Edmundstoun; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">in free, pure, and perpetual alms; as freely and quitely, fully and honourably,
                     as they freely, quitely, fully and honourably hold and
                     possess any alms.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant the said land to the
                     aforementioned monks against all men for ever, and we
                     shall discharge claims in respect of the lord king and all
                     others from every service and custom and secular exaction</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Earl Patrick my lord; Patrick his son; Bernard Fraser; Roger de
                  Merlay; Adam of Polwarth; Adam of Gordon; Thomas of Nisbet;
                  Philip my son and heir; Waldef parson of Whittinghame; Master
                  William of Earlston; Master John, parson; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>