<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/237</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:04:29.739244+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/237</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to all worthy men of his entire land, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> us to have inspected the writing of agreements made at Berwick in our presence
                     between Patrick, earl of Dunbar, our nephew, on the one
                     side, and the abbot and convent of Melrose on the other,
                     about a land in the territory of Hassington which Master
                     William of Greenlaw gave in the full court of the said
                     Earl of Dunbar to the said abbot and convent as well as to
                     their assigns, drawn up in these words:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">To all Christ's faithful who shall view or hear this writing, Patrick, earl of
                  Dunbar, sends greeting. Let everyone present and future know
                  that, since Master William of Greenlaw had solemnly given in
                  our court at Edrom, to the abbot and convent of Melrose as
                  well as to their assigns, a certain land that he had from the
                  gift of Robert de Muschamp our tenant in the feu of
                  Hassington, donated to him and his heirs and assigns, and
                  since the same Master William had put himself out of
                  possession of the same land in that place and solemnly put
                  them in possession of the same, so that the possession of the
                  abbot and convent is peaceably and perpetually established
                  for future times, between them on the one side and us on the
                  other, in the presence of our well-beloved lord Alexander,
                  illustrious king of the Scots, and his barons; it was agreed
                  that we promise, grant, and by this our present charter bind
                  ourselves and our heirs, that we would acquit, warrant, and
                  defend for ever the said holding to the abbot and convent
                  against all people. For the same abbot and convent to hold
                  and to have in free and perpetual alms, by the boundaries by
                  which the said Master William held it and with all
                  pertinents, liberties, and easements pertaining to it, and
                  with common pasture of the toun of Hassington, and with free
                  entry and exit to the same pasture and to the said easments,
                  as wholly, freely, quitly, and honourably from every secular
                  service, exaction, and demand, just as any alms in the
                  kingdom of Scotland is most freely, quitly, fully, and
                  honourably held and possessed. And if anyone move a claim
                  against the said Abbot and convent of Melrose concerning the
                  foregoing, and we or our heirs do not defended them, so that
                  it becomes necessary for them to lose the said land, or be
                  ejected from it by judgment; we or our heirs shall give the
                  reasonable value to the claimant in our demesne or elsewhere
                  in a suitable place to the value of the said land; and so we
                  shall make satisfaction to the same in everything, that the
                  said abbot and convent of Melrose shall retain and possess
                  the said land which Master William of Greenlaw conveyed to
                  them free and quit, peaceably and continuously forever. We,
                  however, in order to do the aforesaid things, for the sake of
                  ourselves and our heirs have provided a bodily oath, and we
                  have the more fully obliged ourselves and our heirs,
                  submitting ourselves and our heirs to the jurisdiction of the
                  Bishop of Glasgow -- whoever it shall be at the time -- so
                  that besides the royal power, by which we ought and wish to
                  be constrained, the said bishop can compel us and our heirs
                  by ecclesiastical censure, with every legal remedy removed
                  and without appeal, to the observance of all the aforesaid
                  things. And so that this writing retain authority and
                  strength, we have caused it to be authenticated by the
                  application of our seal. Enacted at Berwick on the fourteenth
                  day of April in the thirty-fourth year of the reign of the
                  lord king, Alexander. As witnesses, Master Gamelin, the lords
                  Robert of Roos, David of Graham, Robert of Menzies, William
                  fitz Count, Thomas de Normanville, John Comyn, Henry of
                  Graham, Nicholas Corbet, Walter son of Walter the steward,
                  Robert fitz Count, Thomas del Bois, Bernard of Ripley, and
                  many others.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">At the request of the same Earl Patrick, the abbot and convent, we have
                  therefore licensed the aforesaid agreements and made them
                  firm by our present charter and royal authority.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, William earl of Mar, Alexander the steward, Robert of Roos,
                  William of Lindsay, William Oliphant, Nicholas de Soulis,
                  William our chaplain, Alexander the clerk of the chapel,
                  Thomas the clerk of the livery, and others.</seg> At Berwick on the twentieth day of April in the thirty-fourth year of the reign
                  of the lord king.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>