<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/206</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:49:05.195772+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/206</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful who shall see or hear this written deed, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Thomas de Aunay, knight,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">wishes eternal salvation in the Lord.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let your whole community know</seg> me to have given, granted and by this my present charter to have made firm to
                     God and to Blessed Mary at Melrose and to the monks
                     serving God in that place now and to come, for ever, in
                     free and everlasting almsthe lands of ‘Brunsceth’,
                     Auchencrieff, and Dargavel, by their correct boundaries,
                     with all their pertinents and whatever is comprised within
                     the same bounds as well in men as in pastures, buildings,
                     meadows, moors, marshes, waters, mills, woods and all
                     other things, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">so that they hold and have all the foregoing things with their pertinents so
                     freely in perpetuity as I held them, and in all the
                     foregoing things I have withheld nothing to myself.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">Indeed, I and my successors shall warrant all the foregoing to the same monks
                     for ever.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter I have applied my seal to the present written deed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: John of Maxwell; Thomas son of Ranulf, sheriff of
                  Dumfries; John of Mandeville, Walter Crook, and Thomas
                  Maitland, knights; Laurence of Brackley; Thomas of Kent; and
                  many others.</seg> Given in the year of the Lord 1237.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>