<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/246</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-03-30 15:51:37.140095+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/246</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex> by the grace of God King of Scots</seg> to all worthy men of the whole of his land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Let present and future know me to have granted, and by this my charter to have
                  made firm, the donation which William de Vieuxpont made to
                  God and to Holy Rood at Edinburgh and to the Canons there
                  serving God, of the land of Ogilface, by its correct bounds
                  and with all its just pertinents. For them to hold in free
                  and pure and perpetual alms, with all things justly
                  pertaining to the aforesaid land, so freely and quitely,
                  fully and honourably, as the charter of the aforesaid William
                  de Vieuxpont made for them thereupon bears witness. Reserving
                  my service from that land both in aids and in other things
                  from the heirs of the aforementioned William.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">Witness, Walter my chaplain, Philip de Valognes my chamberlain, William Comyn,
                  William del Bois, David de la Haye, William of Moray, Richard
                  Revel, Henry Revel.</seg> At Forfar on the fourth day of November. Given by the hand of William del Bois,
                  in the time of Florence the chancellor, in the year of the
                  Incarnation of the Lord, 1203.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>