<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/300</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 12:30:44.250349+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/300</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of holy Mother church present and future <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Patrick of Ryedale</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> to have given and granted, and by this my charter to have made firm, to God and
                     to the Church of Saint Mary at Melrose and the monks in
                     that place serving God, in free, pure, and perpetual alms,
                     for the salvation of my lord, King Alexander, and for my
                     own salvation, and for the souls of my ancestors and
                     successors, twenty acres of the land called ‘Raven’s Fen’, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by these boundaries; that is, from the upper end of the Harrow valley, the whole
                     of the little stream upwards as far as the land that
                     William of Ryedale gave as a dower to his wife, Matilda
                     Corbet, and from there upwards towards Whitton as the
                     furrow has been drawn between the said land and ‘Raven’s
                     Fen’, as far as the dyke that the monks built, and from
                     there as the old dyke descends into the Harrow valley</seg>. I have given this whole land contained within the said boundaries with all its
                     pertinents to the said monks in return for twenty acres of
                     land, free, released, and quit from every earthly service,
                     custom, and secular demand; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held, possessed and used as seems best to them; as freely, quitely, fully
                     and honourably as they freely, quitely, fully, and
                     honourably hold and possess any alms</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant to the monks the whole said land
                  against all men in respect of all things which can be
                  demanded in return for land</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Walter the bishop of Glasgow, Richard the dean of
                  Tweeddale, William son of John, Thomas of Colville, Richard
                  le Nain, Simon of Grubbit, Walter of Ryedale my son, Ralph of
                  Ryedale, Adam of Chatto, Robert of Barnoldby, Adam of
                  Whitton, Hugh of Newbattle, William my nephew, and many
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>