<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/139</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:05:47.106739+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/139</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all who shall see or hear this charter know</seg> that <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">I, Simon of Lindsay,</seg> have given and granted and by my present charter made firm to Helen my daughter
                     my land at ‘Hungerigge’ that I hold in the territory of
                     Mow of Robert of Pollok and his wife Isabel, and a certain
                     meadow within ‘Ederedesete’ that is called ‘Holemede’,
                     which I hold of the lady Eschyna and her heirs; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for her and her heirs to hold and to have of the said Robert and his heirs, and
                     of the lady Eschyna and her heirs, free and quit of every
                     service and aid and exaction; by annually returning
                     thereupon to the said Robert and his heirs ten shillings,
                     that is five shillings at Pentecost and five shillings at
                     the feast of St Martin; and to the lady Eschyna and her
                     heirs one red <ex>not moulted</ex> hawk at the Roxburgh Fair.</seg> And if it should happen that the said Helen has died by ill fortune without
                     issue, I will that my daughter Eschina, her sister and
                     heir, succeed her in the said land. And I have bestowed
                     and entrusted the said land to Helen and her heirs as
                     freely and quitely in all things and through all things as
                     the charter of the said Robert and his wife Isabel, and
                     the confirmation of the heirs of the lady Eschina of Mow
                     composed thereupon, confer and bear witness.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Simon Mauleverer; Gilbert Avenel; Richard of Lincoln;
                  Ralph le Nain; Simon of Grubbit; Adam of Yetholm; Adam son of
                  Nicholas; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>