<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/234</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-12 13:45:35.983215+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/234</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful as well present as future to whom the present writing
                  shall come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Master William of Greenlaw son of Roland</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">I make known to your whole community that</seg> moved by divine love and for the salvation of my soul and for the salvation of
                     the souls of all my predecessors and successors I have
                     given and granted and by this my charter made firm to God
                     and to the church of Blessed Mary at Melrose and to the
                     monks in that place serving God and their Mother and who
                     in perpetuity will serve there three ploughgates of land
                     that I had in the territory of the toun of Hassington with
                     all its pertinents; that is, those that the lady Matilda,
                     mother of the lord Robert de Muschamp, gave to William,
                     son of John of Hownam, with Gilia, daughter of the said
                     Matilda, in free marriage; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the said monks to hold and have with all liberties, easements, and rights
                     belonging to it for ever, in free, pure, and everlasting
                     alms; by performing no secular service whatever for them
                     to anyone, except for prayers and sugffrages and other
                     spiritual goods which the said monks promised in faith, as
                     much as they owe to God and their own Order, that they
                     would perform for me for ever.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain to the said monks this alms, and we shall
                  warrant it against all men, and we shall acquit it in respect
                  of every service for ever.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this thing my seal has been applied to these presents.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Ralph of Bunkle; John of Latham; John of Papedy; David of
                  Burradon; Alan of Harcarse; John son of Simon; John of
                  Lambden; Robert his son; Roland son of John; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>