<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/123</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:09:43.617663+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/123</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg> to the bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts, officials,
                     and all worthy men of all his land clerk and lay <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> us to have granted and by this our charter to have made firm to God and St Mary
                     and the church of Melrose and the monks serving God in
                     that place, in free and quit and perpetual alms, the
                     church of Hassendean with lands and teinds and all that
                     pertains to the church itself, assigned by Jocelin bishop
                     of Glasgow by our advice for the reception and support of
                     the poor and of pilgrims coming to the church of Melrose.
                     Since there was a dispute about this church between us and
                     the same bishop, to which our donation of this church
                     pertains, we have granted our right which we had or could
                     have had in it to the same bishop to be disposed to that
                     church according to God. And the bishop himself, so that
                     church’s harvest in the works of charity should be
                     distributed and perpetually be converted to good uses has
                     by pious regard conveyed and affirmed that same church
                     with all that belongs to it, for the sake of the souls of
                     all our predecessors and his own, both for the salvation
                     and also the souls of us and him, and of all our heirs and
                     his successors, by our advice and consent, for the
                     perpetual use of the poor and of pilgrims, to the church
                     and convent of Melrose. In order that this pious action,
                     both reasonable and complete, should endure for ever we
                     have granted and by this our charter affirmed the
                     aforesaid church of Hassendean with all its pertinents to
                     God and St Mary and the church of Melrose in free and
                     everlasting alms for the afore-named holy uses; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held for ever as freely, quitely, fully and honourably as any parish
                     church in our kingdom is as freely, quitely, fully, and
                     honourably held and possessed by any conventual church;
                     saving a pension of twenty shillings to be paid each year
                     by the monks to the church of Glasgow in respect of the
                     church of Hassendean, just as the charter of Jocelin
                     bishop of Glasgow bears witness</seg>; and lest there could be any dispute in the future between us or our heirs or
                     those who shall have held of the aforesaid manor and those
                     monks over the pasture of the aforesaid toun, it is
                     provided by our command and by the consideration of our
                     worthy men, we have granted and by this our charter
                     affirmed that the aforesaid monks ought to have for ever
                     in the pasture of the aforesaid toun, to wit, two hundred
                     ewes, sixteen oxen, and four cows, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="injunction">firmly forbidding that anyone commit any injury or vexation to them over this,
                     on pain of our full forfeiture.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow; Richard, bishop of Moray; Archibald,
                  abbot of Dunfermline; Earl David our brother; Hugh our
                  chancellor; William of Lindsay, justice; Philip de Valognes;
                  David of Lindsay; Hugh de Normanville; Walter of Berkeley our
                  chamberlain; Herbert Chalmers.</seg> At Melrose.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>