<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/60</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 13:16:56.552392+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/60</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church both present and to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Roger son of Glay</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> to have given and granted, and by this my present charter to have made firm, to
                     God and to the church of St Mary at Melrose and to the
                     monks in that place serving God; for the salvation of
                     Walter fitz Alan my lord, and for my own salvation, for
                     the soul of my father and mother; certain land in the
                     territory of Innerwick, as the ditch built by their
                     brethren encloses the same land; in free, pure, and
                     everlasting alms, released and quit from every earthly
                     service and exaction, and secular demand, just as they
                     freely, quitely, and honourably hold and possess any alms
                     in the kingdom of Scotland. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant to the foresaid monks the same land against all
                     men for ever.</seg> In addition I have given and granted, and by this my charter made firm, to the
                     foresaid monks the common pasture of the same toun of
                     Innerwick, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">from the low road to the head of the 'Manyneth', to those boundaries that are
                     between us and the monks of Kelso, that is, transversely
                     from the 'Monesclhat' to the 'Wytsclad', and from the
                     'Wytsclad' to the 'Edwardescloth', and from the
                     'Edwardescloth' to the 'Botkil', and so upwards by the
                     same water, that is the 'Botkil', by the correct
                     boundaries of Innerwick to the sheepfold of the foresaid
                     monks, and from that sheepfold to the forenamed low road.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">The foresaid monks shall hold this whole land with easements within the foresaid
                     boundaries, that is in peateries, in peat bogs, in heath
                     ground, in pastures, of me and my heirs in pure and
                     perpetual alms, freely, quitely, and released from all
                     services, exactions and demands, just as any alms is
                     freely and quitely and honourably held in the kingdom of
                     Scotland.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: my lord, Walter fitz Alan; Roger Avenel; Hugh Mauleverer;
                  Hugh Ridel; William de Heriz, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>