<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/235</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:08:01.794465+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/235</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">[To the entirety of Christ's faithful people, who shall hear or view the present
                  letters,] <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Patrick, earl of Dunbar </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> us to have granted and by this our charter to have made firm the donation that
                     Master <supplied>William made</supplied> in our court at Edrom to the abbot and monastic community of Melrose as well as
                     to their assigns, of a land to be found in the territory
                     of Hassington, of which Master <supplied>William</supplied> ... dispossessed himself and solemnly gave them saisine, and it was this land
                     that Robert de Muschamp, our tenant, gave to the said
                     Master William for him and his assigns to possess by
                     everlasting right; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the said abbot and monastic community to have and to hold in free, pure and
                     everlasting alms by the boundaries by which the said
                     Master William held it, and with all pertinents, liberties
                     and easements pertaining to it, and with the common
                     pasture of the said toun of Hassington and with free
                     entrance and exit to the the same pasture and to the said
                     easements, as wholly, freely, quitely, and fully from
                     every secular service, exaction, custom and demand as any
                     alms in the kingdom of Scotland is freely, quitely, fully
                     and honourably held and possessed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And so that the abbot and monastic community should not have to be troubled in
                     times to come by any one in respect of the same land, we
                     and our heirs for the salvation of our souls shall
                     guarantee, release from obligation, and protect the same
                     land by its said boundaries, with everything
                     aforementioned, for the abbot and monastic community
                     against all men for ever.</seg> And in order to do this [easily] and without any difficulty, we and our heirs
                     bind ourselves to the aforesaid abbot and monastic
                     community by these letters patent.</seg> Done at Berwick in the presence of the well-beloved ... ... ... on the
                  eighteenth day of April in the thirty-fourth year of the same
                  king. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witness: Robert of Roos; David Graham; Robert Menzies; William the earl's
                  son; Thomas de Normanville ... ... ... Henry Graham; Nicholas
                  Corbett; Walter son of Walter the Steward; Robert the earl's
                  son; Thomas del Bois, Bernard of Ripley, and ... ... ...</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>