<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/45</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-06 15:19:33.797628+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/45</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Walter by the grace of God bishop of Glasgow</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in Christ</seg> to all sons of Holy Mother Church, both those to come as well as those present.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> us to have given and granted and by this our charter to have made firm to God
                     and to the church of St Mary at Melrose and to the monks
                     serving God in that place, in free and everlasting alms,
                     the toft in the burgh of Glasgow that Ralph of Haddington
                     built at the first erection of the burgh, for the benefit
                     of the monks of Melrose, as fully as he built it and held
                     it, and just as the charter of our predecessor of good
                     memory, J<ex>ocelin</ex> bishop of Glasgow, bears witness to the aforementioned toft given to the
                     aforesaid monks. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore we will that the abovesaid monks of Melrose hold and possess the
                     aforesaid toft as freely and quietly as they freely and
                     quietly hold and possess any alms.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Master William de Blois, archdeacon of Buckingham; Master
                  William of Greenlaw, Master William of Ednam, Master Adam of
                  Walpole, Master Theodoric, our clerks; Thomas and Walter our
                  chaplains; William of Ainslie; Warin our nephew; Ralph our
                  clerk; and many others. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Melrose.</seg><br/></seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>