<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/29</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 09:53:21.896797+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/29</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Duncan son of Gilbert son of Fergus</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> I have granted and given and by this my charter made firm to God and to the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose and to the monks serving God
                     there, for the souls of my lords, the kings David and
                     Malcolm, and of Earl Henry, and for the salvation of my
                     lord, King William, and of Earl David his brother, and of
                     Earl Duncan, and for my own salvation and the souls of my
                     father and my mother, and of all my ancestors and
                     successors, in free and pure and perpetual alms, the whole
                     land of Maybole-beg by these boundaries: <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">That is, from the head of the burn that descends from <ex>Crumder</ex> downwards as far as <ex>Culelungford</ex> and as the same burn descends from <ex>Culelungford</ex> to <ex>Polnetib’</ex>, and as <ex>Polnetib’</ex> falls into the Doon, and by the Doon upwards as far as where <ex>Polgarroh</ex> falls into the Doon, and so upwards by the <ex>Polnegarrah</ex> as far as the small peat bog, and thence as far as a syke which goes down from
                        the south side of the same peat bog to <ex>Polnegarrah</ex>, and by the same syke upwards as far as where the same syke goes up to <ex>Polnecogi</ex>, and <ex>Polnecogi</ex> ascends to <ex>Duuah</ex>, and thence by the syke upwards as far as the road which is called <ex>Enahconecal</ex>, and by the same road downwards as far as the burn that descends from the said <ex>Crumder</ex>.</seg> In addition, I have granted and given and by this my charter made firm to the
                     said monks and church of Melrose the whole land of Beoch
                     in free and pure and perpetual alms by these boundaries,
                     that is, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">from <ex>Lemenelung</ex> eastwards by the road as far as <ex>Neskecokeri</ex> and from there eastwards as far as a great spread of willows, and thence
                        downwards from the northern side of <ex>Croah</ex> <ex>paruus</ex> to <ex>Gallan</ex>, and from there eastwards as far as a syke which goes from the northern side of
                        the black rock, and from the same syke as far the place
                        which is called <ex>Tundregaith</ex>, where from this syke a certain stream, which is called <ex>Polnesalahart</ex>, comes out, and from there as far as where the same stream falls into the <ex>Polnetyberes</ex>.</seg> This whole land as well that of Maybole-beg as that of Beoch, with all their
                     pertinents, and whatever is contained within the said
                     boundaries in wood and plain, in meadows and pastures, in
                     roads and paths, in moors and marshes, in lands and waters
                     and fisheries, and in all other things and easements, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">I have given to the said monks and the church of Melrose to be held and
                     possessed in perpetuity as freely and quietly, fully and
                     honourably, and loosed from every earthly service and
                     custom and secular exaction as they hold or possess any
                     alms freely and quietly, fully and honourably, provided
                     that they shall give to me and my heirs each year no more
                     than two merks of silver as a recognition in return for
                     the land of Beoch, that is, one merk at Pentecost, and one
                     at the feast of St Martin.</seg> And the monks shall make use of all the aforementioned at their pleasure, by all
                     means, just as it seems good and useful to them and their
                     men.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant these things to them against all
                  men for ever and we shall discharge them from all service.</seg> And because I have willed that this my alms be firm and secure and that it could
                  by no means be brought to nought, I have placed the bishop
                  and church of Glasgow as witnesses and sureties of these
                  things, so that if at any time I or my heirs stray from the
                  purport of this charter, that church and its bishop may call
                  us back to correction by ecclesiastical censure. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, the lord Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow, William abbot of
                  Holyrood, Simon the archdeacon, Earl Duncan, Malcolm his son,
                  Earl Gilbert, Aed the son of the earl of Lennox, Roger of
                  Skelbrooke, Gilla Asaild mac Gillanders, Gilla na Naem mac
                  Colman, Edgar my chamberlain, Gilchrist Bretnach.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>