<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/279</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-04 14:42:11.797728+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/279</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, Malcolm Earl of Fife send Greeting:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Let present and future know that I have granted, and by this my charter made
                  firm, to God and to Blessed Mary and to the nuns of North
                  Berwick, in free and pure and perpetual alms, the church of
                  North Berwick with the land of the same church and with
                  teinds and oblations and all other revenues rightly belonging
                  to the same church, and the land in which the house of the
                  foresaid nuns is built, that is, which used to be called
                  ‘Gillecalmestun’, and the land of the hospital of North
                  Berwick; and the land of the hospital of Ardross, and the
                  church of Kilconquhar in the land of the same church, and its
                  teinds, and oblations and all other revenues; and the church
                  of Largo with its teinds and oblations and all other
                  revenues; and the church of Logie with ‘Drumnach’, that is,
                  the land of the same church and with teinds and oblations and
                  all revenues belonging to the same church; and Athernie, and
                  Montrave, and half of the land of Breich by its correct
                  bounds. Wherefore I will that the forenamed nuns hold and
                  possess the foresaid churches and foresaid lands as freely,
                  quietly, fully and honourably, in meadows and pastures, in
                  waters and moors and marshes and all other easements and just
                  pertinents as any abbey freely, quietly and fully holds and
                  possesses any alms in the land of the king of Scots of an
                  earl of baron, just as the charters of my father give,
                  confirm and bear witness concerning the foresaid churches and
                  foresiad lands.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, the lord James, prior of North Berwick, Duncan and David
                  my brothers, Waldef son of Merleswain, John son of Michael,
                  Ness of Ramsay, Thomas of Kilmaron, William of Wyville,
                  Malcolm de Malville, Alexander of Blair, Henry of Abernethy,
                  William Norris, Walter, Gregory, Alexander, chaplains, and
                  many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>