<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/73 (2)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-02-24 13:35:08.738133+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/73 (2)</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful who shall view or hear this writing, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Walter son of Alan, steward of the lord king,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me, all of you,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to the honour of God, and for the souls of my lords the kings of Scotland, and
                  for my own soul, and the soul of my wife and of all my
                  ancestors and heirs, to have given, granted, and by this my
                  present charter to have made firm, to God and the monastery
                  at Melrose, and to the monks in that place serving God now
                  and for ever in the future, the territory of Mauchline, and
                  the church of St Michael to be found there. I have indeed
                  granted to them, and have made firm by this my charter, the
                  whole territory, mentioned before, by its own boundaries,
                  that is, as they are contained in my charter which the monks
                  have concerning it, so that they should have everything
                  contained within the boundaries already said, with all
                  liberties and pertinents that belong to the same holding by
                  right or long-standing custom. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">I and my heirs shall warrant and defend the said monks against all men, and make
                     them possess in peace all the things said above, with
                     their pertinents.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">To be held and had entirely free and quit from every earthly service and every
                     custom and exaction and demand.</seg> In addition, the five merks which the aforesaid monks were bound to have to pay
                     to me and and my heirs in return for the same land each
                     year according to the words of my charter and the charter
                     of my father, to the same monks, in the spirit affection
                     and charity, I have, for my part and for all my heirs and
                     successors, perpetually remitted and made them free and
                     immune for ever from the payment of them. I have also
                     freed and entirely released the same land and its
                     pertinents from hunting and the capture of birds which I
                     and my ancestors were accustomed to excercise in the free
                     land of the said church of Mauchline and from the practice
                     of any art and business whatever.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And so that my donation and confirmation should be made firm and become lasting,
                  without any impediment, I have strengthened the present
                  writing by the application of my seal.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord John of Maxwell, Berhard Fraser, Adam son of
                  Gilbert, Reginald of Crawford, Roger son of Glay, Robert
                  Logan, Robert of Crawford, Nigel de Heriz, Robert the clerk,
                  and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>