<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/159</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:20:42.322925+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/159</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Patrick of Ryedale</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have licensed and by this my charter to have made firm to God and to the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose and monks serving God in that
                     place the donation of Geoffrey son of Waldef of
                     Lilliesleaf which he made to the aforesaid church and
                     monks in respect of four oxgangs of arable land in the
                     territory of Whitton, in free, pure, and perpetual alms,
                     just as they lie in one holding above ‘Raven’s Fen’ near
                     the land of ‘Heuiside’ which they have from my donation. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the aforesaid monks of Melrose should hold and possess the
                     aforenamed land free, quit, and loosed from all earthly
                     service and custom and secular exaction, just as the
                     charter of the said Geoffrey more fully bears witness and
                     affirms.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant to the oft-mentioned monks the
                     aforewritten land against all men for ever, saving only
                     the service to me and my heirs from Geoffrey himself and
                     his heirs in respect of the the same land.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Robert, archdeacon of Glasgow; John, dean of Roxburgh;
                  Richard le Naym; Walter, my son and heir; Ralph of Ryedale;
                  Robert of Bernoldby; Adam of Whitton; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>