<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/312</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 07:58:24.404367+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/312</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To the whole body of Christ's faithful who shall view or hear the present
                  writing, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Nicholas Weaver, burgess of Berwick,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know, all of you, that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">since I conveyed to the abbot and convent of Melrose half of my land at Briggate
                  in pure and perpetual alms, and sold the other half in return
                  for one hundred merks of legal sterling, just as the seal
                  which they have from me concerning the same land testifies;
                  the said abbot and convent, for the increase of the
                  aforementioned money, have given and granted to me [and]
                  Hilda, my wife, or to others of ours who live for a longer
                  time, for the whole of our life, 10 bolls of marketable wheat
                  and one chalder of marketable barley and a half mark of
                  silver each year at the feast of Saint Michael, to be
                  received at Berwick. Wherefore, I, by this my charter, bind
                  myself and all my goods, moveable and immovable, to the said
                  abbot and convent, so that if by chance they are put to
                  trouble on account of a defect of warranty relating to the
                  aforementioned lands, or they lose them in part or in whole,
                  they shall immediately cease from the payment of this
                  increase. And whatever I or Hilda my wife shall have received
                  from this increase, we shall fully and wholly restore it to
                  the same with the hundred merks above said, and with all
                  costs or losses they may have incurred, without dispute.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">As witness of this matter I, for myself and my heirs, have caused my seal to be
                  put to this writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, the lord William the Earl's son, the lord Nicholas his son, John
                  of Letham, and others.</seg> Enacted in the year of grace 1251, on the eleventh of the kalends of March [19
                  February 1250 n.s.]</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>