<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/143</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:08:19.869488+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/143</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall see or hear these letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Master W<ex>illiam</ex> of Lindsay, dean of Glasgow,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">wishes eternal salvation in the Lord.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all people know</seg> that Abbot [Herbert] and the <ex>monastic</ex> community of Kelso have in our presence resigned and quitclaimed for ever any
                     right they used to have in the lands and pastures of Mow
                     within the portion belonging to the lord Walter son of
                     Alan, Steward of Scotland, and also the right of common
                     that they used to have in the moor of Innerwick to the
                     same Walter and his heirs and their attorneys; no right in
                     the same is to be reclaimed in return for a portion of the
                     said moor of Innerwick from the same W<ex>illiam</ex> in the exchange bestowed <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by these boundaries, namely, from Birk Cleugh <ex>Bothwell</ex> going up by the small stream which falls from Scullins as far as Scullins Head
                        where the ditch is drawn, and by that ditch as far as
                        the road which stretches from Rise Lea towards
                        Innerwick, and so from that road going up by the ditch
                        eastwards as far as a certain furrow, and so from the
                        furrow going down by the ditch as far as
                        ‘Meldrescloesheued’, and so by the little stream of
                        ‘Meldrescloesheued’ continually going down by Monynut,
                        as far as the edge of Easter Wide Hope, and so going up
                        by Easter Wide Hope westwards next to the bounds of
                        ‘Ellum’ and of Rise Lea, as far as Wester Wide Hope,
                        and from Wester Wide Hope as far as Whiteadder, and
                        from Whiteadder far as Birk Cleugh, and so continually
                        going down by Birk Cleugh as far as the said little
                        stream which falls from Scullins</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord W<ex>illiam</ex>, by the grace of God, bishop of Glasgow, Chancellor of Scotland; the lord W<ex>illiam</ex>, abbot of Paisley; Master H<ex>ugh</ex>, archdeacon of Glasgow; and many others, among whom there were Master W<ex>illiam</ex> of Greenlaw, Master Abel, and Master Peter of Alinton,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">who for the greater security of thie matter together with us have applied their
                  own seal to the present written deed.</seg> Done at Kelso in the year of grace . . .</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>