<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/287</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:24:14.846613+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/287</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons and faithful men of Holy Mother Church present and future who shall
                  view or hear these letters <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Walter of Ryedale son of Patrick of Ryedale</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me all of you</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have given, granted, and by this my charter to have made firm to God and to
                  the church of blessed Mary at Melrose and to the monks in
                  that place serving God, in free, pure, and perpetual alms, a
                  portion of my land in the territory of Lilliesleaf with the
                  tofts and crofts which are between Roger of Newbattle's land
                  and the land that I gave to Alexander of Ashkirk, that is,
                  the whole land that Matilda Corbett held in dower in
                  'Lintedikes' and 'Benelandes' and 'Brunerig', in two places,
                  both in 'Kaueres' and 'Chengisflat', and the meadow which is
                  called 'Stobimedue', and five acres and one perch from my
                  demesne below 'Harekamb' on the southern side, that is, from
                  the land which Alexander son of Thoc held from me at ferme.
                  These lands and whatever is contained in them I have given to
                  the aforesaid monks. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">And I will that they have, hold and possess them with the aforesaid meadow and
                     with all common easements of the same toun for ever, as
                     freely, quitly, fully, and honourably as they hold or
                     possess any alms freely, quitly, fully, and honourably.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant the aforesaid lands with the
                     aforesaid meadow, and we shall acquit from every earthly
                     service and custom and secular exaction and demand towards
                     the lord King and everyone else for ever.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, my lord William de Vescy, Richard Gernun, Robert of Airth,
                  Richar de Nichol', Hugh of Redden, Gilbert of Whitton,
                  William son of Alexander of Lilliesleaf, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>