<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/136</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:03:48.080136+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/136</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother church, present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard of Lincoln</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have given and granted and by this my charter to have made firm to God and
                     to the church of St Mary at Melrose and to the monks
                     serving God in that place, for the souls of my father and
                     my mother and of all my ancestors and successors, and for
                     the salvation of my lord, King William, and of the queen
                     and their son Alexander, and of Earl David, and for my own
                     salvation and my wife's and all our heirs' <ex>salvation</ex>, in pure and everlasting alms, the portion of land in the territory of Mow that
                     Anselm of Whitton gave to the same church and monks with
                     the adjacent meadows, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held and possessed for ever by all the borders and boundaries contained in
                     the charter of the said Anslem</seg>. In addition I have given and confirmed the whole peatery that is between
                     Mowhope and Berhope and 'Herdstrete' which divides the
                     land of Mow and of Hownam. I have moreover given them in
                     my wood of Mowhope as much firewood as one horse can carry
                     to Hownam Grange, each year from Easter to the Nativity of
                     Saint Mary. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">I will that the said monks hold and possess all these things for ever as freely
                     and quitely and honourably as they hold and possess any
                     other alms freely and quitely, fully and honourably</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant to the said monks this alms
                     against all men</seg>, and dishcarge it of forinsec and every earthly service in respect of all men
                     for ever. And the monks shall have free and appropriate
                     entrance and exit through my land for fetching their
                     firewood and peats and other necessities without
                     disturbance and hindrance.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Gervase Avenel; William Avenel; W<ex>illiam</ex> of Cresswell; W<ex>illiam</ex> de Crachin; Alan the clerk; Walter of Ryedale; Robert of Barnoldby.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>