<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/162</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:47:22.655047+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/162</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church as well future as present <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Patrick of Ryedale</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in Christ</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have granted and by this my charter to have made firm to the hospital of
                     Jerusalem one oxgang of land in the territory of Whitton,
                     that which lies to wit between ‘hord lauue’ and
                     ‘toccechelis’ and between the trench and Harrow and the
                     dower land of Matilda Corbet which Geoffrey my cook as a
                     free man has given to the hospital of Jerusalem by the
                     consent and good will of his heirs in free, and in pure,
                     and in perpetual alms, for the souls of his ancestors and
                     successors, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">on the condition that Isabel the spouse of William of Ryedale and her heirs or
                     the one to whom she may wish to assign it may in feu and
                     heritage hold the foresaid land of the aforenamed <ex>monastic</ex> house and have possession in peace, free and quit from multure and from all
                        other service and custom and from all secular exaction,
                        by the yearly rendering one pound of cumin annually to
                        the aforenamed hospital at the feast of Saint James.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord William son of John; the lord Walter of Ryedale;
                  Ralph of Ryedale; Adam of Whitton and his sons; Adam of
                  Wauchope; John son of Adam of Chatto; Robert of Bernoldby and
                  Robert his brother; Alexander of Lilliesleaf; Henry de Heriz;
                  Richard the abbot's man; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>