<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/213</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 16:05:09.761278+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/213</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall see or hear these letters, as well present and to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">John son of Waldef</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> to have granted and by this my charter to have made firm, to God and the church
                     of St Mary at Melrose, and the monks in that place serving
                     God, all donations, agreements, and grants which John of
                     Methil has made to them regarding the land of Penshiel,
                     with all its pertinents, and liberties and easements
                     pertaining to the said land of Penshiel; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for them to have and to hold for ever, of the said John of Metliil and his
                     heirs, according to the tenor of the charters which the
                     said monks have of the said John over the said land;</seg> saving the service to me and my heirs of the said John of Methil and his heirs,
                     contained in my charter and the charters of my
                     predecessors, which the said John has in respect of the
                     said land.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord earl, Patrick of Dunbar; Patrick, his son;
                  William, his son; Walter Oliohant; Bernard Fraser; Adam of
                  Polwarth; Roger of Merlay; William of Boltby; Alan, son of
                  Alan son of Edgar; John, my son.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>