<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/291</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 08:43:44.574843+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/291</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard, by the grace of God Bishop of Dunkeld,</seg> to all sons of Holy Mother Church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> that we have granted, and by this our charter made firm, to God and to the
                     church of St John the Apostle at Inchaffray, and to the
                     brethren serving God there now and in the future, our land
                     in Madderty, the land that is called ‘apdaine’, by its
                     correct bounds, with all is just pertinents, at the
                     request of Earl Gilbert of Strathearn and his brother M<ex>alise</ex>, for the redemption of our soul and of our ancestors’, and of the the foresaid
                     Earl G<ex>ilbert</ex> and his own people. For the foresaid brethren and their successors to hold in
                     free and perpetual alms, by rendering to us and our
                     successors annually one merk of silver, that is, half at
                     Pentecost and half at the feast of St Martin. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">We therefore will and enjoin that the same foresaid brethren and their
                     successors hold and possess the foresaid land of us and
                     our successors, as freely and quietly, fully and
                     honourably, from every exaction and custom and secular
                     service pertaining to us, in wood and plain, in meadows
                     and pastures, in waters and mills, and all other easements
                     pertaining to the same land, just as any land in our
                     bishopric is freely and honourably held and possessed, and
                     just as the charter of Bishop John, our predecessor, bears
                     witness, but saving the foresaid pension.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Henry our archdeacon, Ralph, Bernard, and Thomas, our
                  chaplains, Louis and John our clerks, Brice the parson of
                  Crieff, Robert the chaplain of Tibbermore, Gilbert the son of
                  the archdeacon of Strathearn.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>