<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/217</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 07:52:57.409275+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/217</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, present and to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Henry of Belton</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let your whole community know</seg> me to have given, granted, and by this my charter to have made firm, to the
                     monks of Melrose my whole land of Kingside in the
                     territory of Penshiel, as it lies between Kell Burn and
                     King Burn and Whiteadder; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held and had of me and my heirs at feu ferme for ever; by paying from it
                     to me and my heirs each year two merks of silver, that is
                     one at the feast of St Michael, and the other on
                     Whitsunday.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">I and my heirs shall assuredly maintain and warrant and defend to the said monks
                     the whole aforesaid land with all its liberties and
                     pertinents and we shall discharge claims towards all men
                     from every service, custom, exaction and demand;</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">so that the said monks shall hold and have the said land freely and quitely for
                     ever by the siad rent of two merks.</seg></seg> Enacted in the year of grace 1231. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord Joh of Maxwell, king's chamberlain; the lord
                  Thomas son of Ranulf; the lord Bernard of Howden; the lord
                  John of Methkil; Philip of Pitcox; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>