<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/189</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-02-24 14:10:11.415155+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/189</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of holy Mother Church and to the faithful, present and future, who
                  shall view or hear these letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Duncan, earl of Carrick,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know, all of you, that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">since the monks of Melrose were yearly bound to me in the payment of three
                  merks, that is, two for the land of Beoch and one for the
                  land of Auchnefure, just as it is set out in their charters</seg>: <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">I have entirely released and perpetually quitclaimed the same three merks for
                  the aforementioned monks in return for the forty merks
                  sterling which the same monks have paid to me in my great
                  need, that is, for my land to be put at liberty. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">For this reason, both I and my heirs and successors shall warrant this quitclaim
                     of the aforesaid three merks against all men for the
                     aforementioned monks for ever.</seg> And so that this quitclaim should be strong and enduring, I have placed as
                     witness and guarantor the lord William, bishop of Glasgow,
                     allowing that if at any time I or my heirs or successors
                     should try anything against this or against the alms made
                     to the same monks by me as set out in my charters, the
                     same bishop and his successors shall compel us to observe
                     all the foregoing at the request of the monks themselves,
                     without knowledge of the cause, upon pain of
                     ecclesiastical censure.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">As witness and defence of this matter I have applied my own seal to the present
                  writing together with the seal of the lord W<ex>illiam</ex>, bishop of Glasgow.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord Walter son of Alan, steward of Scotland, Ralph of
                  Livingston, clerk, Alan my knight, Alan my son, parson of
                  Kirchemanen and of Straiton, Master Hugh my clerk, and many
                  others.</seg> Done in the year of the Lord 1236.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>