<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/219</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-12 13:45:36.028862+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/219</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Philip son of Philip of Pitcox</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="undefined"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have allowed, and by this my charter to have made firm, to God and the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks in that
                     place serving God, for the souls of my lords, Cospatric
                     and Waldef, earls of Dunbar, and for the souls of my
                     father and mother, and of all my ancestors, and for the
                     salvation of my lord, Earl Patrick, and for my own
                     salvation, and of all my successors, the lands in the
                     territory of Pitcox which my father has given to the same
                     monks, that is, the land which lies between the boundaries
                     of the monks' land at Hartside and the little stream which
                     is called Pressmennan Burn, which the aforesaid monks have
                     annexed along the aforesaid stream to their own land at
                     Hartside by reason of the donation and instruction of my
                     father, and ten acres in ploughland at 'Beleside' most
                     closely adjacent to their land at Edmundstoun; in free,
                     pure, and perpetual alms. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will and allow that the aforesaid monks of Melrose should have,
                     hold, and possess the aforenamed lands, as freely,
                     quitely, fully and honourably, as they freely, quitely,
                     fully and honourably hold and possess any alms.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant the aforesaid lands to the
                     aforementioned monks against all men for ever, and we
                     shall discharge all earthly service and custom, and
                     secular exaction.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Earl Patrick, my lord; Patrick his son; Bernard Fraser; Roger de
                  Merlay; Adam of Palworth; Adam of Gordon; Thomas of Nisbet
                  [Philip my son and <ex>struck through</ex>] Waldef parson of Whittinghame; Master William of Earlston; Master John the
                     parson; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>