<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/119</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 14:55:24.158837+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/119</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, both present as well as to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Uhtred of Grubbit, and Simon his son and heir</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">send greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> us to have given and by this our charter to have made firm, to God and to the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks serving God
                     in that place, for the souls of all our lords, and for our
                     own souls, and of our fathers' and mothers' <ex>souls</ex>, and of all our ancestors' and successors' <ex>souls</ex>, and especially of Earl Henry's <ex>soul</ex>, that pat of the land in 'Elstaneshalche', <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">which lies on the western side of the old river, towards the land of the same
                     monks which they have of the feu of Whitton, to the east
                     of their land,</seg> in free, and pure, and perpetual alms, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">that they may have it, and hold it, and possess it, freely and quitely, and
                     honourably, just as freely, and quitely, and honourably as
                     they hold any alms, moreover from all earthly service and
                     custom, and secular exaction,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">and we and our heirs shall warrant to them the same land against all men</seg>, and we shall discharge towards the lord king, and all our lords in respect of
                     forinsec service, and all earthly service for ever. We
                     have made this donation to them for the sake of
                     fraternity, and for prayers, and for the participation in
                     all the benefits of the same church for ever.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Godard the chaplain; Adam the parson of Maxton; Robert of
                  Barnoldby</seg>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>