<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/241</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-02 13:02:56.671561+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/241</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons and faithful of Holy Mother Church, Saer de Qunicy, earl of
                  Winchester, Greeting:</seg> T<seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">he whole body of you should know that in the presence of the lord king of Scots
                  and his magnates in his full court at Forfar I quitclaimed
                  for myself and all my heirs to the abbot of the church of
                  Holyrood in Edinburgh and the convent of that house in
                  perpetuity whatever right I am considered to have in the
                  church of Tranent and its pertinents, moved by divine reward
                  and for the welfare of the soul of my lords the kings of
                  Scots and my predecessors and successors. Moreover, I confirm
                  to them one ploughgate of land and ten acres in the territory
                  of Tranent at Falside, with free exit and common pasture,
                  which my father gave them in free and perpetual alms, as his
                  charter to them attests. I also confirm to them the whole
                  land in Niddrie which my father gave them to serve the chapel
                  of the same toun. For them to hold in free and perpetual
                  alms, by the same bounds with which my father saised the
                  canons themselves in the presence of worthy men.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">Witness the Lord King, Earl David the brother of the lord King, Robert of
                  London, Wiliam Comyn, Florence the chancellor, William del
                  Bois, William and Oliver the king’s chaplains, Hugh de
                  Prebenda, Herbert de Camera, A<ex>dam</ex> the parson of Kinghorn, Adam of Hastings, and very many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>