<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/290</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:22:42.600214+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/290</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful people who shall view or hear the present writing <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Adam son of Adam of Durham</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Your whole community should know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have sold, for my own, my wife's and my childens' needs, to the monks of
                  Melrose my whole land that I have in 'Thodholeside' and
                  'Standestanerigis', which I held of the lord William of
                  Ryedale and his heirs in West Lilliesleaf, situated between
                  the land of the same monks which is called 'Clerk's Land' and
                  the land of William son of Alexander, in respect of which
                  payment has been fully made to us for twenty shillings. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">The said monks shall hold and possess for ever the whole said land as freely and
                     quitely as they freely and quitely hold and possess any
                     land in the kingdom of Scotland, with common easements of
                     the said toun as they pertain to so much land, and the
                     monks shall be free and immune from every private and
                     external service, from every custom, exaction and demand
                     which can occur in the land.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant and defend the said land with all its
                     pertinents with everything that was mentioned before to
                     the said monks against all people for ever, so that
                     neither I nor my heirs shall alienate the residue of our
                     land that we have in West Lilliesleaf, in order that
                     through it we should be able to warrant the said land to
                     the said monks if a cause arises.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter I have caused my seal for myself and my heirs to be
                  applied to this writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses William son of Alexander, Alan Spenser, Alexander of Herdmanston,
                  Simon the brewer, William son of Hugh, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>