<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/234</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 09:26:02.113494+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/234</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Christian, by the grace of God bishop of Candida Casa [Whithorn],</seg> to all sons of the most holy Mother Church, clerk and lay, present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting:</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">You should all be notified that</seg> I have granted, and by this my charter have made firm, to God and to the church
                     of Holyrood in Edinburgh, and to the canons serving God
                     there, the church of St Mary and St Bruoc of Dunrod, in
                     free and perpetual alms with all its revenues and
                     pertinents, reserving episcopal right, and the church of
                     Twynholm, with all its revenues and pertinents. I also
                     confirm by this same charter the donation of Fergus and
                     his son Uhtred of the whole toun of Dunrod by its correct
                     bounds, with all its rightful pertinents and revenues, and
                     as their own charters the better and more fully bear
                     witness.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witness, William abbot of Dundrennan, John the archdeacon, Gilbert the
                  chaplain, James the parson of Troqueer, Robert the priest,
                  son of Dolfin, Mac Raith of Spittal, Máel Bethad the bishop’s
                  nephew, Walter his brother, Nicholas [and] James the bishop’s
                  nephews, William of Cartmel, Gilbert the bishop’s steward,
                  Bran son of Macgillegunnin, Arnold the doorward, Adam de Ele.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>