<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/223</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-02-15 19:15:46.374368+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/223</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>Thor son of Swain to all his friends and lords, Greeting: Let those to come as
               well as those present know that I, by the counsel and consent of
               my heirs, have given and granted, for the salvation of my soul
               and my ancestors’, in perpetual alms to God and the church of
               Holyrood in Edinburgh and the brethren serving God there, the
               whole of the donation that I was seen to have in the church of
               Tranent in lands and pastures and teinds, free and quit from
               every secular dominion and exaction. And besides those things
               that my ancestors bestowed to the aforesaid church of Tranent, I
               give and grant, and by the present charter make firm, to the
               said church two dwellings with two tofts to the aforesaid canons
               with the aforementioned church confirmed in perpetual alms, my
               sons granting and confirming all things aforesaid with me. With
               these witnesses, William bishop of Moray, Osbern abbot of
               Jedburgh, Thorald the archdeacon, Aiulf the dean, Nicholas the
               king’s clerk, Ness son of Chilierus, Edmund son of Forn, Bernard
               son of Tóki, Gillanders his steward, Edmund of Fazeside, Aldan.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>