<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/225</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-07-07 12:14:11.662629+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/225</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard, by the grace of God a humble servant of Saint Andrew</seg>, to his beloved in Christ, the sons of Holy Mother Church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting and episcopal blessing.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let your fraternity know</seg> that we have granted, and by his charter made firm, all the churches that are in
                     our diocese which King David, and King Malcolm, and
                     Bishops Robert of good memory, and Bishop Arnald, or other
                     faithful of Christ, gave in perpetual alms to the church
                     of Holyrood in Edinburgh; that is to say, the church of
                     [Edinburgh] castle with Saughton, and all its other
                     dependencies; the church of St Cuthbert [in Edinburgh]
                     with two ploughgates of land and its other rights; and the
                     church of Corstorphine with two oxgangs, and six acres of
                     land, and the rest of the things rightfully belonging to
                     it; the church of Airth with two ploughgates of land, and
                     the rest of its dependencies, and a saltpan with
                     twenty-seven acres of land; and the church of Livingston,
                     with half a ploughgate of land, and all other things which
                     rightfully belong to it; and the church of Kinneil, with
                     one ploughgate of land, the teind of the mill, and the
                     saltworks of that toun; and the church of Whitekirk with
                     all its dependencies; and the church of Carriden, with the
                     land which rightfully belongs to it, and all its rights;
                     and the church of Tranent, with land and everything
                     rightfully belonging to it; and the church of Bathgate,
                     with one ploughgate of land, and everything rightfully
                     belonging to it; and all things which that church
                     rightfully possesses from any donation, as the charter of
                     King David, and the charter of King Malcolm, and the
                     charter of Bishop Robert, and the charter of Bishop Arnald
                     attest and confirm. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">We therefore wish, and with the assent of all our chapter we grant, and by
                     granting we confirm, that the aforesaid church of the
                     Holyrood is to hold all the aforenamed churches, and the
                     rest of its possessions, with all its rights free and
                     quit, and protected and unharmed by any exaction.
                     Reserving episcopal right.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Andrew, archdeacon; Aiulf, dean; Robert, chaplain and the
                  bishop’s brother; Geoffrey, priest of Lasswade; Robert, canon
                  of St Andrews; Alexander, the bishop’s chaplain; Master
                  Herbert [and] Master Abraham, the bishop’s clerks.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>