<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/285</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:28:58.779935+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/285</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church present and future <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Margery de Vescy</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me all of you</seg> to have granted to God and to the Church of St Mary at Melrose and to the monks
                     in that place serving God the donation of land and pasture
                     which Patrick of Ryedale made to them in the territory of
                     Lilliesleaf just as Patrick's own charter and the
                     confirmation of his son and heir Walter bear witness, by
                     the same boundaries which are contained in the charter of
                     the aforementioned Patrick and the confirmation of the
                     aforenamed W<ex>alter</ex> his heir. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">And I will and grant that the aforesaid monks have and hold the aforesaid land
                     and pasture in free, pure, and perpetual alms with all
                     their easements and liberties as freely, quitely and
                     honourably, minus every custom and secular exaction, as
                     they hold and possess any alms freely, quitely, fully and
                     honourably in the kingdom of Scotland; reserving to myself
                     and my heirs the service pertaining to the aforesaid land
                     from the aforementioned Patrick of Ryedale and his heirs.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant all the aforesaid things to the
                     aforesaid monks that they should have them and hold them
                     and possess them and make use of them by all means which
                     seem to them best and most convenient to them, so freely
                     as the aforesaid charters of the aforesaid donors bear
                     witness.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Bernard of Howden, William de Vescy, Philip of Stichill,
                  Robert of Broxmouth, Master W<ex>illiam</ex> of Ednam, Nicholas the chaplain, Walter of Ryedale, Ralf of Ryedale, and many
                     others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>