<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/135</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:03:04.489623+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/135</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Anselm of Whitton</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg> to all sons of Holy Mother Church, both lay and learned.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let future and present know</seg> me to have given and by this my charter to have made firm to God and to the <ex>monastic</ex> house of Melrose, and to the monks serving God in that place, in everlasting
                     alms the land with meadows <supplied>which</supplied> I and Glay nephew of Robert Avenel perambulated with the cellarer and brethren
                     of the same place, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">namely, as the furrow of the plough extends on the north side from the road that
                     lies from ‘Hunedune’ towards Mow and runs down to the
                     rock, and from the rock down to the spring, and as the
                     same trench runs from the spring . . . and from there as
                     far as the burn</seg>; and this alms I have given to them for the soul of King David, and of Earl
                     Henry and King Malcolm, and for the salvation of King
                     William and David his brother, and for my own soul and my
                     wife’s and my childrens’ <ex>souls</ex>. In addition I have given to them in everlasting alms my whole peatery that is
                     between Mowhope and Berhope and ‘Herdstrete’ which divides
                     the land of Mow and of Hownam. In addition I have given to
                     the said monks in everlasting alms in my wood of Mowhope
                     as much firewood as one horse can carry, each year from
                     Ester until the Nativity <supplied>of Saint Mary. And</supplied> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">the monks of Melrose shall have this my alms, and the rest aforesaid, and they
                     shall hold of me and of my heirs quit and <supplied>free from all</supplied> services and all customs;</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">and I and my heirs shall warrant those to the monks in respect of all men.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses . . . abbot of Newbattle; Robert Avenel, and Gervase his
                  son; William de Somerville; John son of Orm, William his son;
                  Glai nephew of Robert Avenel; Gernun; Nicholas son of Adam;
                  Peter, parson of Morebattle; W . . . of Hownam.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>