<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/170</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 12:44:28.191303+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/170</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex> by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg> to Bishops, Earls, Barons, Justices, Sheriffs, Officials, and all worthy men of
                     the whole of his land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> me to have granted and given and by this my charter to have made firm to God and
                     to the church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks
                     serving God in that place, the land that they have from
                     Patrick of Ryedale in the territory of Whitton, by those
                     bounds that are contained in the charter of Patrick of
                     Ryedale which they have from him concerning the same land; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">so that they have and possess whatever is within the bounds for ever, as freely
                     and quitely, honourably and peaceably, as any alms is
                     freely and quitely and honourably possessed in my kingdom.</seg> For I have given to them and confirmed that land free from all aids, pleas,
                     gelds, and from every service and custom and secular
                     exaction; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">so that I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant it for them against all men
                     for ever, saving my service from Patrick and his heirs</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow; David my brother; Walter Oliphant,
                  justice; Alan son of Walter; Hugh, clerk of the seal; Hugh
                  Ridel; Walter of Windsor; Walter of Berkeley, chamberlain;
                  William de Mortimer; Robert of Berkeley; John of London.</seg> At Lanark.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>