<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/42</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-06 15:19:33.891465+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/42</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William, by the grace of God king of Scots</seg>, to Bishops, Abbots, Earls, Barons, Justices, Sheriffs, Provosts, Officials,
                     and all worthy men of the whole of his land, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> me to have granted and by this my charter to have made firm, to God and the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks in that
                     place serving God, the whole land of Eskdale, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by the same boundaries which are named and contained in the charters of the lord
                     Robert Avenel and Gervase his heir, which they have from
                     them in respect of the same land;</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">so that whatever is within the same boundaries, they shall have and possess for
                     ever, as freely and quietly, fully and peacefully, as any
                     alms is freely and quietly possessed in my kingdom; I
                     have, then, confirmed and granted to them the same land
                     for ever, released also from all aids, and from all
                     service and custom and secular exaction, reserving my
                     service from Gervase and his heirs.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Osbert, abbot of Kelso; Hugh, abbot of Newbattle; William
                  Malveisin; Richard de Prebenda; Hugh de Sigillo; Earl David,
                  the king’s brother; Robert de Quincy; Hugh Ridel; Richard de
                  Muschet; Philip de Valognes; Roger de Valognes; Waldef son of
                  Baldwin; Alexander de Saint-Martin; Hervé the marischal;
                  Richard the marischal; Robert de Saint-Michel; Adam of
                  Stanford.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>