<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/106</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 13:37:00.611595+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/106</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard de Morville constable of the King of Scotland and William his son and
                     heir </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">send greeting</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> us to have granted and by this our present charter to have made firm to God and
                     to the church of St Mary at Melrose and to the monks
                     serving God in that place, for our souls and of all our
                     ancestors' and successors' souls, a place in Whitelee
                     inside the limits of the forest for making a vaccary, that
                     is, for a hundred and twenty-six cows, or a sheep-fold,
                     whatever seems better and more useful to them and their
                     house; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held and possessed freely and quitely by them for ever without any
                     disturbance from us and of all our men </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">and of all men against whom we shall have been able to maintain them and warrant
                     the same possession to them</seg>; and one building in which they may make a dwelling for the brethren and their
                     shepherds and one building also in which they may put
                     their hay. We have granted these three buildings in pure
                     and everlasting alms to the same monks to be built in the
                     forementioned place at Whitelee and to be possessed for
                     ever. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">And it is to be known that</seg> they shall build no other dwellings in the forest, but their shepherds shall
                     have wattled huts under which the livestock being guarded
                     shall lie when the need arises</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Jocelin bishop of Glasgow; Herbert dean of Glasgow;
                  Thomas, clerk; Godfrey de Ros; Ralph Mackerel; Richard son of
                  Sewar; Alan son of Aelsi; Gilbert of Lancaster; Richard son
                  of Gilbert; Richard son of Geoffrey; William the bishop of
                  Glasgow's steward; Master Roger of Newport.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>