<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/76</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 12:41:32.707682+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/76</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Earl Waldef</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg> to all sworn men and friends, French and English.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let those to come as well as those present know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have given, and made firm by this my charter, with the agreement of my
                  heir, to God and St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks serving
                  God in that place, common pasture upon Lammermuir, with me
                  and my men, by these boundaries, that is: from Baldred’s
                  Stane by the highway as far as the Hazliecleugh and thence
                  downwards as the Hazliecleugh falls into the Bothwell and
                  thence as far as the boundaries of Innerwick; for the
                  salvation of my soul and my ancestors’ and successors’; in
                  everlasting alms, as freely and quitely and honourably from
                  all secular services and customs as any alms is freely,
                  quitely and honourably given or held. And if they shall quit
                  the pasture of Innerwick, their sheep-folds shall follow
                  their flocks, with their bothies that belong to the said
                  sheep-folds within the marches named before, without manual
                  labour, and with my own bothies at Belton.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">This donation I and my heirs shall warrant to the foresaid monks against all men
                  for ever.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Aelina, countess; Ralph, chaplain; John, chaplain; Walter,
                  chaplain; Hugh of Duns; Patrick the earl’s brother; Edward
                  the earl’s uncle; Gilbert Fraser; Adam son of Aldan; Aldan
                  the seneschal; Gamel of Pitcox; Adam of Fogo; Gilbert son of
                  Walter; Stephen Papedy; Warin le Malle; Adam son of Edgar;
                  Adam of Edington.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>