<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/96</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:16:49.070754+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/96</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex>, by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts, and all
                     worthy men of his entire land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> me to have given and by this my present charter to have made firm to God and to
                     the church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks of
                     Rievaulx serving God there, for the souls of my father and
                     my mother, and of King David my grandfather, and for my
                     own soul, and of all my brothers and sisters, my ancestors
                     and successors, in free, pure, and perpetual alms, the
                     enitre land of Blainslie, by the boundaries named in the
                     charter of Richard de Morville, for ploughing and
                     cultivating just as it shall seem best and most useful to
                     them, without performing assart, and permission for
                     constructing their own buildings wherever they wish on the
                     burn which is between Blainslie and Milsie, and the entire
                     land of Milsie which Richard de Morville and his heir gave
                     to them, and made firm by their charters, by the same
                     boundaries which are contained in their charters, and the
                     chapel of Park just as it is contained in their charters,
                     and the building at Colmslie and at Buckholm and at
                     Whitelee, just as they were at the feast of Saint Michael
                     next after the first coronation of Richard, son of Henry
                     king of England, provided no enlargement or more buildings
                     are built there than were theere at that time unless by my
                     permission. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">And so that none of my foresters give or sell wood within their boundaries
                     specified in my charter, I give and grant all these things
                     to them to possess in everlasting tenure, and by this my
                     charter make firm in free and everlasting alm, and I will
                     and instruct that they have and possess all things
                     mentioned above as freely and quitly, fully and
                     honourably, as any alms can most freely and quitly, fully
                     and honourably be had and possessed by monks of the
                     Cistercian order</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Jocelin bishop of Glasgow, Arnold abbot of Rievaulx, Hugh my
                  chancellor, Robert my chaplain, Philip de Valognes, Robert of
                  London, William of Lindsay, Malcolm son of Earl Duncan,
                  William Comyn, Gervase Avenel, William de la Hay, Adam son of
                  Gilbert, Adam of Ceres, Adam of Stanford, Herbert the
                  marischal.</seg> At Traqhuair.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>