<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/103</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:19:33.840398+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/103</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex>, by the grace of God king of the Scots,</seg> to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts, officials, and
                     all worthy men of his entire land, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> me to have granted, and by this my charter to have made firm, the friendly
                     agreement made at Selkirk in my presence and in my full
                     court, on the one side between Earl Patrick of Dunbar,
                     with his son and heir, Patrick, consenting, and the house
                     of Melrose on the other side, about the disagreement which
                     arose between them concerning the pasture towards the west
                     of Leader. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will and firmly instruct that the said agreement between them made
                     thereupon be inviolably and constantly held fast, just as
                     the cyrograph made between them bears witness. Saving my
                     service</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, B<ex>rice</ex> bishop of Moray, Ralph bishop of Down, William and Oliver my chaplains, Robert
                     of London my son, David of Lindsay and Gervase Avenel,
                     justices, William del Bois and Hugh de Sigillo my clerks,
                     Roger de Mortimer, Adam of Kinghorn, John of Maxwell,
                     Alexander of Synton.</seg> At Selkirk on the 6th day of November.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>