<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/39</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2024-03-05 14:35:59.762473+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/39</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of holy Mother Church, as well present as future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert Avenel</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all people know that</seg> I, Robert Avenel, with my lord William king of the Scots approving, by the
                     consent and agreement of my heir, Gervase, have granted
                     and given, and by this my charter made firm, to God and to
                     the church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks in that
                     place serving God, my land of Eskdale, that is,
                     Tomleuchar, and Watcarrick, in pure and free and
                     everlasting alms, for the soul of my lord, King David, who
                     gave the same land to me in return for my service, and for
                     the soul of Earl Henry, and of King Malcolm, and for the
                     soul of my lord William, king of the Scots, and of all
                     their predecessors and successors, and for my own soul,
                     and of Sibyl my wife, and for the souls of all my heirs
                     and ancestors. This land, that is Tomleuchar and
                     Watcarrick, I have given to the aforesaid monks and
                     written in a charter, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by these boundaries, namely, as the two Esks meet, so upwards by the Black Esk
                     as far as the first stream that descends from Hartside;
                     and from that stream, upwards through the middle ridge of
                     the mountains, between them and Robert de Brus, as the
                     waters descend towards the monks themselves; and so
                     between the forest of <ex>Thimeus</ex> and themselves, by the middle ridge of the mountains, as they descend towards
                        themselves; similarly between the land of <ex>Bordewich</ex> and the monks themselves, by the middle ridge of the mountains, as the waters
                        descend towards them; and so as far as the land of <ex>Hawich</ex>, and thence across by the middle ridge of the mountains, that is, between
                        myself and the aforesaid monks, as the waters descend
                        towards them; this ridge extends from above <ex>Harewude</ex>, and so descends to where the two Esks meet.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">And this whole aforenamed land, possession, and whatever is contained within
                     these aforewritten boundaries, in wood and plain, in
                     meadows and pastures, in waters and marshes, and in all
                     benefits and easements, I have granted and given, and made
                     firm to the aforesaid monks, in pure and everlasting alms,
                     as a perpetual holding to be held and possessed of me and
                     my heirs, free and quit from all services, and from every
                     secular exaction, as freely and quitely, fully and
                     honourably, as any alms is able to be held and possessed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And if by chance anyone should wish to claim the aforesaid alms, I and my heirs
                     shall answer all claimants, and sufficiently protect and
                     warrant it for the aforesaid monks. </seg>This is also to be known: that I have retained for myself and my heirs only deer
                     and hind, swine and roebuck, within the aforenamed
                     boundaries, without harm and injury of crops, meadows,
                     hedges, livestock, animals, and all the other possessions
                     of the same monks; provided, however, that I and my heirs
                     shall not have a forester within the described boundaries,
                     nevertheless we shall have within the same boundaries
                     robbers, and eyries of hawks and sparrow-hawks, and the
                     guards to guard them, and trespassers; and it should be
                     known that the aforesaid monks shall have and possess the
                     whole aforesaid land, free and quit from me and my heirs,
                     saving my aforesaid wild game, and the eyries of hawks and
                     sparrow-hawks; and the monks shall make use of all this
                     tenement according to their will and pleasure, just as it
                     shall seem to them best and most useful to be of use to
                     themselves, their brethren, their servants and livestock.
                     With the exception that they shall not hunt there with
                     packs of hounds and ropes, nor bring others there for
                     hunting, nor set traps there, unless for catching wolves;
                     and they shall not take the eyries of hawks and
                     sparrow-hawks within these boundaries. It should be known
                     in addition that the aforenamed monks were accustomed to
                     render to me yearly five merks when I first gave them this
                     land; but after some years, for the honour of God and for
                     the salvation of my soul, I have remitted and given them
                     the five merks in alms to provide for the light before the
                     altar of Saint Mary, for ever; and by the advice of my
                     friends, I have entirely remitted and given to God and the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks serving God
                     in that place, in pure and everlasting alms, and
                     quitclaimed the four merks which for many years they were
                     accustomed to render to me. Therefore this payment, and
                     the whole aforewritten possession, being agreed and
                     allowed by my heir, Gervase, I have given to God and the
                     aforesaid monks, in free and pure and everlasting alms,
                     quit and released from every service and secular exaction.
                     And that this my alms be established and firm for ever and
                     not able to be brought by any means to nought, I have
                     renewed and made for the same monks this my charter in the
                     time of my lord William, king of the Scots, and my lord
                     William the king, at my petition and request, has
                     confirmed this my donation and alms by his own charter,
                     just as my lord, King Malcolm, previously granted it at my
                     request, and confirmed by his own charter.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">These are the witnesses of my first donation and charter which I made for them
                  in the time of King Malcolm: Richard, bishop of St Andrews;
                  Ingram, bishop of Glasgow; Gregory, bishop of Dunkeld;
                  Geoffrey, abbot of Dunfermline; John, abbot of Kelso; Aelred,
                  abbot of Stirling; Nicholas the chancellor; Matthew the
                  archdeacon; Waldef the earl; Duncan the earl; Ferteth the
                  earl; Malcolm the earl; Richard de Morville; Walter son of
                  Alan; David Oliphant; Robert de Quincey; Richard Comyn;
                  Bernard son of Brian; Robert of Berkeley; Walter the clerk;
                  Richard the clerk; Walter of Berkeley. But after that, in the
                  time of my lord William the king, when this donation was
                  renewed, and the aforesaid ferm was remitted in full, these
                  are also the witnesses: Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow; Simon,
                  archdeacon; Hugh Small, clerk of the king; William, steward
                  of the bishop; Walter, clerk of the bishop; David the earl,
                  brother of the king of the Scots; Alan, steward of the king
                  of the Scots; Robert le Croc, my knight; Alan son of Hugh,
                  the earl's steward; David, Herbert d'Arches; William de
                  Aldri; Gervase de Eincurt, nephew of the lord Robert; Glay,
                  nephew of the same.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>