<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/248</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 08:09:54.987278+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/248</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex> by divince mercy humble servant of the church of St Andrews</seg> to all who shall view or hear these letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Eternal Salvation in the Lord:</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">We wish to bring to your attention of you all that</seg> we have, by the common agreement and will of our chapter and of our archdeacons,
                     given and granted to the abbot and canons of Holyrodd and
                     their successors in perpetuity, in pure and perpetual
                     alms, the whole moiety of the teind of corn pertaining to
                     the church of Kinghorn for the support of the aforesaid
                     canons, paupers and pilgrims. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore we will that the aforesaid canons and their successors should hold and
                     possess the same teinds in perpetuity as a simple
                     benefice, as freely, wholly, and honourably as any simple
                     benefice in the whold kingdom of Scotia is freely, quietly
                     and honourably held and possessed</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And that this our grant might endure sure and unbroken, we have secured it by
                  the testimony of this document, and by the application of our
                  own seal and the seals of the Chapter and our archdeacons.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Master Laurence the archdeacon of St Andrews, W<ex>illiam</ex> del Bois the archdeacon of Lothian, Ralph Niger the dean of Lothian, Ralph the
                     dean of Crail, Master Alexander de Saint-Martin, Master
                     David of Bernham, Simon de Noisy, William of Gullane,
                     Simon the chaplain of the lord bishop, Richard of Kelso
                     the clerk, John the clerk of the lord Bishop, and many
                     others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>