<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/221</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 07:55:03.22692+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/221</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall see or hear the present letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Philip of Pitcox</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me in good will to have allowed to the monks of Melrose that they may cross the
                     stream called the Pressmennan Burn, which is the boundary
                     between me and the monks, because frequently damage was
                     occurring to their meadows and crops. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">The crossing of this stream begins at Swine Burn, and extends southwards in the
                     same way as the land cultivated of old and the meadow come
                     together, as far as the ford where the road from
                     'Lunkepeth' descends into the Pressmennan Burn and from
                     the siad ford as far as 'Thorneburht' and so below
                     'Thorneburht' as far as the 'Broc'.</seg> This whole land and meadow indeed which is contained within the aforementioned
                     crossing towards the monks themsleves I have given and
                     granted, and by this my charter mande firm, to God and the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the aforesaid monks
                     in that place serving God, in free, pure, and perpetual
                     alms, for the salvation of my lord, Earl Patrick, and his
                     heirs, and for the salvation of my own soul, and of my
                     wife's, and of all our forefathers', quit and released
                     from every earthly service and custom and secular
                     exaction. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain to the said monks this alms, and warrant
                     against all men, and acquit it from every service for
                     every.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Simon and Hugh, chaplains of Dunbar; Richard the chaplain
                  of Stenton; Patrick son of Adam of Whitehouse; Roger de
                  Merlay; Bertin of Ruchlaw; Adam, at that time cellarer of
                  Melrose; Walter and Albin, lay-brethren of Melrose; and many
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>