<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/141</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:06:37.856219+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/141</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">I, Simon of Lindsay,</seg> have given, granted, and by this my charter made firm to Patrick my man and [in
                     return for] his homage and service in my land at Mow,
                     which he has had from the gift of my mother, six acres of
                     land, and one acre of meadow, and one and a half acres of
                     land in toft and croft, and one acre of meadow of the the
                     land nearest ‘Erdeburesburne’, and ‘Subchestres[?burne]’ . <supplied>?two acres</supplied> . and upon ‘Selestede Adam’ two and a half acres; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for him and his heirs to hold of me and my heirs in feu and heritage freely and
                     quitely, fully and honourably, also with all common
                     easements of my land and common easements which my men in
                     my mother’s land [can] and ought to have; by paying me and
                     my heirs one pound of cumin or three pence at the feast of
                     St James in return for all services pertaining to me or my
                     heirs, and by doing such forinsec service on my land as
                     pertains to such an amount of land;</seg> I therefore will that he should give four pence [to me and] my heirs for his
                     fine, and six pence for his aid.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">[With these witnesses: Peter] de Valognes; Robert of Rapelaw; Adam of Wauchope;
                  Adam of Whitton, and Gilbert his son; Walter de . . . Richard
                  Scott; Mervyn of Mow; Richard the clerk; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>