<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/254</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 08:28:52.555398+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/254</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons and faithful people of Holy Mother Church, present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Ness of London</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends Greeting</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> I have granted, and by my present charter made firm, to God and to the church of
                     Holyrood in Edinburgh and to the canons serving God there
                     now and in the future, for the salvation of my soul and of
                     my wife’s, and for the salvation of the souls of my lords,
                     and my predecessors and successors, the mill of Linton,
                     which Ness my predecessor gave to the same canons, and
                     made firm by his charter, with the easement of the Tyne
                     Water and the messuage assigned to them. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For them to hold in pure and perpetual alms, in every ecclesiastical liberty,
                     just as they hold and posses alms from any gift, freely,
                     quietly, fully and honourably,</seg> reserving the multure of my mills, provided that none of my own men might mill
                     at the mill of the foresaid canons without the permission
                     of the canons’ miller. If the miller of the foresaid
                     canons mills any grain at the foresaid mill except the
                     canons’ grain and the grain of their own men, I and my
                     heirs shall receive a half of the whole of that multure.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Walter of Lindsay, William Noble, Walter of Congleton,
                  Alan de Crahoc, Robert son of Patrick, Jocelin of Fortune,
                  William of Carmichael, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>