<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/61</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 13:17:54.01879+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/61</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div><p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of holy Mother Church as well present as future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William of Halkerston, and Richard of Halkerston, his brother, and John son of
                     Alan of Montgomery, and Vincent son of Robert Avenel, and
                     Nicholas son of Roland,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">send greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">us to have given and granted, and by this our present charter to have made firm,
                  to God and to the church of Saint Mary at Melrose, and to the
                  monks serving God there, for the salvation of our souls, and
                  for the souls of our fathers and mothers and of all our
                  ancestors and successors, and for the soul of Walter son of
                  Alan our lord, and for the souls of all the faithful
                  departed, a land in the territory of Innerwick, as the ditch
                  encircles the same ... made by their brethren, in free, pure,
                  and everlasting alms, loosed and quit of every earthly
                  service and secular exaction, just as they hold any alms
                  freely, <supplied>quitely</supplied> and honourably in the land of the king of Scotland. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And we and our heirs shall warrant to the aforesaid monks the same land against
                     all men for ever.</seg> In addition we have given up to the aforesaid monks the common pasture of the
                     same toun of Innerwick, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">from the low road to the head of <ex>Manineth</ex> at the boundaries which are between us and the monks of Kelso, that is, across
                        from <ex>Monnesclacht</ex> as far as <ex>Witsclad</ex>, and from <ex>Witsclad</ex> as far as <ex>Edwardescloth</ex>, and <ex>Edwardescloth</ex> as far as <ex>Botkil</ex>, and so upwards by the same water, that is <ex>Botkil</ex>, by the correct boundaries of Innerwick as far as the sheep-fold of the
                        aforesaid monks, and from that sheep-fold as far as the
                        low road aforenamed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">This aforesaid pasture with easements within the aforesaid boundaries, that is,
                     in peataries, in turbaries, in heathland, the aforesaid
                     monks shall hold of us and our heirs in feu ferme for
                     ever, freely and quitely, released from all services and
                     earthly exactions by returning from it yearly to us and
                     our heirs ten shillings at Pentecost</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: William Wallace of Stenton, Nigel, parson of Rutherglen,
                  Master William of Earlston, William clerk of ...ford, Robert
                  Avenel, Robert son of Gregory, William Francis, Richard
                  Taylor, Walter ... and many others.</seg></p> <p> </p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>