<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/258</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-04 14:39:35.432678+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/258</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons and faithful of Holy Mother Church to whom the present deed shall
                  come, present and future, William son of Gamel of Twynholm
                  sends Greeting:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">I make known to you all that I, with the consent of my lord, Alan son of Roland,
                  and the agreement of Walter my son and heir, have given and
                  granted, and by this my charter made firm, to God and to the
                  church of Holyrood in Edinburgh and to the canons serving God
                  there, in free and pure and perpetual alms, the whole right
                  that I thought good to have in the church of Twynholm, and I
                  have renounced in perpetuity, for myself and my heirs, the
                  claim that I claimed in the advowson of that church.
                  Furthermore I give and grant, with the assent of Walter my
                  son himself, to the foresaid church and the foresaid canons,
                  in perpetual alms, four acres of land in the territory of the
                  same toun, for the canons themselves to hold the same bounds
                  by which I perambulated that very land in the sight of worthy
                  men. And to the foresaid church I give and grant one dwelling
                  in the toun itself, in respect of which I have put the
                  foresaid canons in possession, with common pasture of the
                  same toun for sixteen draught animals and for one horse, and
                  with all other common easements of the same toun. Wherefore I
                  will that the aforenamed canons should hold and possess in
                  perpetuity the foresaid church with all its just pertinents,
                  freely and quietly in perpetual and pure alms.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Silvester, Andrew and Thomas, chaplains, Matthew the dean,
                  Robert the clerk, Robert Halfknight, Robert and Gamel,
                  brothers, Robert son of Matilda, and very many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>