<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/32</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 10:06:03.155095+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/32</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Duncan son of Gilbert son of Fergus, Earl of Carrick</seg>, to all worthy men of the kingdom of Scotland, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg></seg>: <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let those as well future as present know</seg> that I have granted and given, and by this my charter made firm, to God and to
                     the church of Melrose and to the monks there serving God,
                     the whole donation that I and Roger of Skelbrooke my
                     knight have granted and given to them, that is, the whole
                     land of <ex>Drumentheisuiene</ex> and of <ex>Aleburc</ex>, and of <ex>Althefur</ex>, by the same boundaries that are described in the charter of Roger himself,
                     with all easements of the same land, in free and pure and
                     perpetual alms, as freely and quietly, fully and
                     honourably, as any alms in the whole Cistercian Order is
                     freely (and) quietly both held and possessed, and as the
                     charter of the same Roger well bears witness, reserving
                     the service of the lord king from me and Roger and our
                     heirs. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will and firmly enjoin that the aforenamed church of Melrose, and
                     the aforenamed monks of the same place, should have and
                     hold this donation, and possess in perpetuity, of me and
                     Roger of Skelbrooke my knight, and our heirs, as granted,
                     given, and made firm to them by this my charter, as freely
                     and quietly and honourably as any earl or any patron of
                     any feu both might be able and ought to grant, give, and
                     confirm to any conventual mother church</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Jocelin bishop of Glasgow, and the Church of Glasgow, Earl
                  Duncan and Malcolm his son and heir, Earl Gilbert, W., Alan
                  the steward of the lord king, William de Morville the
                  constable of the lord king, Gilchrist mac Eachann, Ewen mac
                  Alwine, John son of William, Rether mac Coirill, Edgar mac
                  Murthar my chamberlain, Gilla Brigte mac Mehin, Achostduf,
                  and Cane his brother.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>