<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/198</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 12:38:52.766267+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/198</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to all worthy men of the whole of his land, clerk as well as lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">May you all know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">in our presence and of our barons at the colloquium at Liston in the Year of
                  Grace 1235 an amicable agreement was made between the Abbot
                  and Monks of Melrose on the one side, and Roger Avenel on the
                  other, over the disputes instigated between them, that is,
                  how Roger, contrary to the tenor of his charter and those of
                  his predecessors, put a horse-stud and his own animals and
                  men into the Monks’ land in Eskdale within the boundaries set
                  out in his charter, and how the said Roger and his men
                  destroyed some houses built by the said monks, and levelled
                  their dykes and other enclosures of theirs, and brought other
                  injuries upon them, as they said. To wit that Roger has
                  allowed that neither he himself nor his heirs nor their men
                  shall have a horse-stud, cattle, pigs, sheep or any other
                  live-stock within the boundaries specified in the said
                  Roger’s charter, unless by the monks’ permission, saving to
                  the said Roger the beasts of the chase in the manner stated
                  in his charter, which we and our barons have explained in
                  this way; to wit, that Roger and his heirs shall have so many
                  stag and hind, boar and sow, and roe-bucks and roe-does; in
                  addition, the eyries of hawks and sparrow-hawks, provided
                  that the monks do not maliciously cause hindrance so that
                  they can nest in the place where they nest as long as they
                  have the habit of nesting there; they should not remove the
                  nests of hawks or sparrow-hawks within the said boundaries,
                  nor should they fell the trees in which they nest in one year
                  until it is determined whether they wish to nest in those
                  trees in the following year or not; and if then they have not
                  nested, let the monks make use of the trees by all means that
                  they wish. In other places within the boundaries set out in
                  the charter of the said R<ex>oger</ex>, they may build lodges and buildings wherever they wish, according to their
                     pleasure and intent, and make use of the tenement
                     contained within the said boundaries as shall seem to them
                     best and most usefully profitable to themselves, their
                     brethren, servants, and livestock. In addition, thus have
                     we determined about thieves and trespassers: that they are
                     not deemed trespassers in respect of the right of the
                     monks and the use of the same, of their tenants, brethren,
                     and men, whenever they go for grazing their own animals,
                     or keeping watch, or searching, or carrying out their
                     other business, whether by day or by night, unless they
                     have been caught in clear wrongdoing. And if they have
                     been discovered in such a way at night, they should be
                     guarded until the next day; and if they are tenants of the
                     monks, they should straightaway freely be given up in
                     order to obey the law where they ought to obey. When
                     captured by day, they should be returned immediately to
                     them. Also the said monks shall not hunt there with packs
                     of hounds and ropes, nor lead others to that place for
                     hunting, nor set traps there except for catching wolves.
                     Accordingly the said Roger and his heirs shall enjoy the
                     wild game as was agreed before, without deceit and bad
                     intention, without loss and injury of crops, hedges,
                     meadows, livestock, animals and all the other possessions
                     of the same monks.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, A<ex>ndrew</ex> of Moray, and C<ex>lement</ex> of Dunblane, bishops; W<ex>alter</ex>, earl of Menteith; W<ex>alter</ex> son of Alan, steward of Scotland; W<ex>alter</ex> Oliphant, justiciar of Lothian; Henry de Balliol; David the Marischal; Geoffrey
                     the clerk of the Liverance.</seg> On the eighth day of April in the twenty-second year of the reign of our lord
                  the king [1236].</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>