<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/248</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-29 15:57:28.175141+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/248</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of Scots</seg>, to all worthy men of his whole land, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>: </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> that we have granted and made firm by this our charter the donation of a share
                     of his own land in the territory of Maxton that John de
                     Normanville made to God and to the church of St Mary at
                     Melrose and to the monks who are serving God there now and
                     in perpetuity; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the said monks of Melrose and their successors to hold and to have from the
                     aforesaid John de Normanville and his heirs in pure and
                     perpetual alms by the same correct boundaries that are
                     contained in the same John de Normanville’s charter;
                     freely, quietly, fully, and honourably, just as the
                     aforesaid John’s charter to the aforesaid monks of Melrose
                     more fully drawn up on the matter justly bears witness;
                     with the exception of our service.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: William of Bondington, chancellor; Walter Oliphant, justiciar of
                  Lothian; Robert of Roos; Walter Comyn; John of Maxwell,
                  chamberlain; Bernard Fraser; Ralph de Champagne; Aymer of
                  Maxwell. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Traquair, on the fourth day of February, in the nineteenth year of the reign
                  of the lord king</seg>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>