<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/230</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-05 09:20:01.812941+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/230</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert by the grace of God bishop of St Andrews</seg> to all sons of Holy Mother Church <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting and Blessing</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let those to come as well as those present know that</seg> I have granted in perpetual alms to God and to the church of Holyrood in
                     Edinburgh and to the canons serving God there the church
                     of Tranent with everything that rightfully belongs to it,
                     free and quit from every exaction, as Waleran the chaplain
                     ever had and held it well, reserving the tenure of Waleran
                     the chaplain himself for as long as he remains in secular
                     life, just as King Malcolm has given and affirmed by his
                     charter the aforesaid church of Tranent to the church of
                     the Holy Cross and to the canons serving God there by the
                     advice of his barons. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">I therefore will and by this my charter make firm that after the departure of
                     Waleran the aforesaid canons shall hold that church as
                     freely and quietly as they have and hold their other alms
                     and possessions, reserving the episcopal right.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Thor<ex>ald</ex> the archdeacon, Aiulf the dean, Waleran himself being present and suggesting it,
                     Swain of Fishwick, William the bishop’s chaplain, Aelward
                     the chaplain, John the bishop’s nephew, Ralph the bishop’s
                     nephew.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>