<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/249 (2)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-03-30 14:27:45.759292+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/249 (2)</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">John, by the grace of God Bishop of Whithorn, to all sons and faithful of Holy
                  Mother Church, Greeting:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Let present and future come to know that with the agreement of the whole of our
                  chapter, for the salvation of our soul and of all
                  predecessors’ and successors’, we have granted and by
                  episcopal authority confirmed by the testimony of the present
                  document, to God and the church of Holyrood at Edinburgh, and
                  to the canons serving God there now and in the future, in
                  free and pure and perpetual alms, all the churches, with
                  their lands, that Fergus of good memory, and Uhtred his son,
                  and David son of Terrus, bestowed to the same canons,
                  inspired by divine reward, with the agreement of the diocesan
                  bishiop, and made firm with their charters. That is, from the
                  donation of Fergus, the church of Dunrod with the whole toun
                  and with all its pertinents, and the Isle of Trail, and
                  Galtway with the church of the same toun and with all its
                  pertinents. And from the donation of Uhtred his son, the
                  church of St Cuthbert of Desnesmor, and the church of
                  Tongland, and the church of Twynholm, and the church of St
                  Andrew, and the church of Kelton, and the church of
                  Kirkcormack with the chapel of Barncrosh. And from the
                  donation of David son of Terrus, the church of Anwoth with
                  the chapel of Culenes, and with all its pertinents. Wherefore
                  we will and grant by episcopal authority that the aforesaid
                  canons should wholly convert to their own benefit all the
                  aforenamed churches with chapels and all their revenues, and
                  with lands and all their pertinents, as it pleases them; and
                  hold and possess them freely and quietly and released from
                  all procuration and exaction in perpetuity; and they should
                  cause the same chapels to be served by chaplains agreeable to
                  them, presented by us or our successors, or by themselves, as
                  it seems expedient to them, and they may remove the less
                  suitable ones in consultation with the bishop. Reserving to
                  the ourself and our successors only reasonable synodals, and
                  common aids from the aforesaid churches, except from the
                  churches of Kirkcormack, with the chapel of Barncrosh, and
                  Kelton, which have been entirely exempted from synodals and
                  the rest of the episcopal dues by our predecessor, Bishop
                  Christian of good memory, and by us.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Michael the prior of Whithorn, and the chapter of the same
                  place, the lord Alan son of Roland, constable of the lord
                  king of Scots, John the archdeacon, Matthew the dean of
                  Desnes, William the dean of Farines, Gilbert the dean of
                  Rhinns, Walter the parson of Kinkandres, Durand the parson of
                  Minnigaff, Martin the clerk of Kirkcudbright, and very many
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>