<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/235</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-03-09 21:24:44.352366+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/235</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">M<ex>alcolm</ex> king of Scots to Uhtred son of Fergus, and Gilbert his brother, and Ralph son of
                     Dunegal, and Domnall his brother, and to all his other
                     worthy men of the whole of Galloway and Clydesdale,
                     Greeting:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Know that I have justly given my firm peace to all those men who go or shall go
                  to Galloway to lodge or dwell in the Land of Dunrod, which
                  Fergus gave to the church of Holyrood in Edinburgh in
                  perpetual alms and affirmed by his charter, which Uhtred his
                  son also confirmed by his charter, whose charters I myself
                  have also confirmed. I therefore firmly forbid that any man
                  presume unjustly to vex or disturb anyone travelling to the
                  said land by reason of dwelling in it, or dwelling in the
                  same land by consent and will of the canons of the aforesaid
                  church, or departing from that land in the fealty of the same
                  [canons]. And no-one may remain in the same land by anyone’s
                  advowson or lordship against the will of the said canons, on
                  pain of my forfeiture of ten pounds.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Alured abbot of Stirling, Robert prior of May, Ingram the
                  chancellor, W<ex>alter</ex> the steward, son of Alan, John de Vaux.</seg> At Clackmannan.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>