<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/286</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:27:03.845592+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/286</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church present and future <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William de Vescy</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me all of you</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have granted and by this my charter to have confirmed, moved by love of God
                  and for the salvation of my soul and for the salvation of all
                  my ancestors and successors, to God and to the church of St
                  Mary at Melrose and to the monks in that place serving God,
                  the two ploughgates of land, one of which Patrick of Ryedale
                  gave to them, and the other Walter his son, in the territory
                  of Lilliesleaf, with the pastures belonging to them, by the
                  same boundaries which are contained in the charters of the
                  aforesaid Patrick and Walter his son. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">And I will and grant that the aforesaid monks have and hold the aforesaid lands
                     and pastures in free, pure and perpetual alms, with all
                     their easements and liberties, as freely, quitely, fully
                     and honourably as they hold and possess any alms freely,
                     quitely, fully and honourably in the kingdom of Scotland,
                     reserving to myself and my heirs the service pertaining to
                     those lands from the aforesaid Patrick and Walter and
                     their heirs.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">I and my heirs also maintain and warrant all things aforesaid to the aforesaid
                     monks, that they have and hold and use them by all means
                     which seem best and useful to them, just as the charters
                     of the aforesaid donors and confirmations of Margery my
                     mother which the aforesaid monks have thereupon bear
                     witness</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, the lord J(ohn) of Maxwell, Robert of Roos, Waldef the
                  marischal, William the latimer (interpreter), Ralph Bardolf,
                  Simon of Horsley, Robert of Airth, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>