<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/107</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 13:36:22.367529+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/107</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church both future and present, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Richard de Morville, constable of the king of the Scots</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have given, and by this my charter to have made firm, to God and to the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose, and the monks serving God in
                     that place, in free and quit and everlasting alms, the
                     freedom and licence to have at Buckholm one cow pasture
                     for sixty cows, and a suitable building for their needs,
                     within the same enclosure which was there before I had
                     given them this permission. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the aforenamed church of St Mary at Melrose and the
                     foresaid monks should have the forementioned liberty and
                     licence in free and everlasting alms, and possess it for
                     ever; as freely, quitely, and honourably as they possess
                     any alms freely, quitely, and honourably;</seg> so that it shall non remain a hindrance on account of my charter for Whitelee
                     which I had given to them previously, which shows me to
                     have granted to them that they may have only three
                     buildings in the forest, and that at the foresaid
                     Whitelee.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witness: the lady Avice of Lancaster; William de Morville our son and heir;
                  Herbert the dean of Glasgow; Master Clement, chaplain; Adam,
                  parson of the church of Lauder; Roger clerk and steward; Alan
                  of Thirlestane; Sampson son of William of Oxton.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>