<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/163</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-02-24 14:07:36.64375+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/163</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">TO ALL sons of Holy Mother Church present and future <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Isabel wife of William of Ryedale</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg></seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> to have given and granted and by this my charter to have made firm to God and to
                     the church of St Mary at Melrose and the monks serving God
                     in that place, for the salvation of the lord Patrick of
                     Ryedale, and Walter his son, and William my spouse, and
                     for my own salvation, and for the souls of all our
                     ancestors and successors, the oxgang of land in the
                     territory of Whitton that my father William, the parson of
                     Hownam, bought from Geoffrey the cook, and donated to me
                     along with the charter of the foresaid G<ex>eoffrey</ex> and the confirmation of P<ex>atrick</ex> of Ryedale together, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by these boundaries, as the same oxgang of land falls between Hardlaw and
                     Shielstockbraes, and between the fosse of Harrow and the
                     dower-land of Matilda Corbet, and as the course of the
                     ditch goes around it by the foresaid boundaries.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">I have given this whole land and whatever is contained within the foresaid
                     boundaries to the same monks in free, pure, and perpetual
                     alms and released from every earthly service, custom, and
                     secular exaction, that they may have, hold and possess it
                     for ever, as freely, quitely, fully, and honourably as
                     they hold or possess any alms freely, quitely, fully, and
                     honourably.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant this alms to the foresaid monks
                     against all men, and acquit it of every service for ever.</seg> And that this my donation should be firm and fixed I have sworn by holding the
                     holy gospels in the presence of the church before worthy
                     men; and neither I, nor any of my heirs, shall seek to
                     challenge it by art or cunning from which the house of
                     Melrose could in future incur any loss or injury in
                     respect of the same land.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, the lord Patrick of Ryedale; Walter of Ryedale, his son; William
                  my spouse; William our son; Patrick son of Walter of Ryedale;
                  Ralph of Ryedale; Robert of Barnoldby; Alexander the clerk;
                  Reginald the parson's man; Adam of Huntly; Henry de Heriz;
                  Walter son of Geoffrey Cook; Geoffrey son of Henry of
                  Newbattle; William son of Mabilla; William nephew of the lord
                  P<ex>atrick</ex> of Ryedale; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>