<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/197</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-03-30 13:59:32.360277+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/197</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of holy Mother Church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Roger Avenel, son of Gervase Avenel</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">me to have granted and by this my charter to have confirmed to God and the
                  church of Saint Mary at Melrose, and to the Monks serving God
                  in that place, the donation of Robert Avenel, my grandfather,
                  which Gervase Avenel, my father, confirmed to them; that is,
                  the land of Eskdale which the aforesiad Robert Avenel, my
                  grandfather, donated to them in everlasting alms, the most
                  pious King Malcolm first approving, and afterwards the
                  illustrious King William, his brother; to wit, Tomleuchar and
                  Watcarrick, in free, pure, and everlasting alms; for the soul
                  of the glorious King David, who had donated the same land to
                  my same [grandfather] [<ex>in copying from the earlier charter, the scribe originally wrote </ex>'patri'<ex>, but erased it, forgetting to insert </ex>'auo'] in return for his service; and for the soul of Earl Henry and of the
                     aforesaid King Malcolm, and for the soul of the said King
                     William and of Alexander, the son of the king of Scots, my
                     lord, and of all his ancestors' and successors' [souls],
                     and for my own soul and of all my ancestors' and
                     successors' [souls]. I have therefore granted this, to
                     wit, Tomleuchar and Watcarrik, to the aforesaid monks, and
                     have given and confirmed and described in a written deed
                     by this my charter, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by these boundaries, namely, as the two Esks meet, so upwards by the Black Esk
                     as far as the first stream that descends from Hartside;
                     and from that stream, upwards through the middle ridge of
                     the mountains, between them and Robert de Brus, as the
                     waters descend towards the monks themselves; and so
                     between the forest of <ex>Timeus</ex> and themselves, by the middle ridge of the mountains, as they descend towards
                        themselves; similarly between the land of Borthwick and
                        the monks themselves, by the middle ridge of the
                        mountains, as the waters descend towards them; and so
                        as far as the land of Hawick, and thence across by the
                        middle ridge of the mountains which is between myself
                        and the aforesaid monks, as the waters descend towards
                        them; this ridge encloses <ex>Harwde </ex>towards the monks, and so descends from the east side from <ex>Harwde</ex> itself, and so always descending to where the two Esks meet.</seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">And this whole aforenamed land, possession, and whatever is contained within
                     these aforesaid boundaries, in wood and plain, in meadows
                     and pastures, in waters and marshes, and in all benefits
                     and easements, I have granted and given, and made firm to
                     the aforesaid monks, in pure and everlasting alms, to be
                     held and possessed by perpetual right, free and quit from
                     me and my heirs, and released from all services, and from
                     every custom and secular exaction, as freely and quitely,
                     fully and honourably, as any alms is able to be held and
                     possessed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And if by chance anyone should wish to claim the aforesaid alms, I and my heirs
                     shall answer all claimants, and sufficiently protect and
                     warrant it for the aforesaid monks. </seg>This is also to be known: that I have retained for myself and my heirs only deer
                     and hind, swine and roebuck, within the aforenamed
                     boundaries, without harm and injury of crops, meadows,
                     hedges, livestock, animals, and all the other possessions
                     of the same monks. And although I and my heirs shall not
                     have a forester within the described boundaries,
                     nevertheless we shall have within the same boundaries
                     robbers, and eyries of hawks and sparrow-hawks, and the
                     guards to guard them, and trespassers; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">and it should be known that the aforesaid monks shall have and possess the whole
                     aforesaid land, free and quit from me and my heirs, saving
                     my aforesaid wild game, and the eyries of hawks and
                     sparrow-hawks; and the monks shall make use of all this
                     tenement according to their will and pleasure, just as it
                     shall seem to them best and most useful to be of use to
                     themselves, their brethren, their servants and livestock.</seg> With the exception that they shall not hunt there with packs of hounds and
                     ropes, nor bring others there for hunting, nor set traps
                     there, unless for catching wolves; and they shall not take
                     the eyries of hawks and sparrow-hawks within these
                     boundaries. It should be known in addition that the five
                     merks which at one time my grandfather received in ferme
                     from them, which ... his wife and also my father
                     quitclaimed to them before his death; this I likewise have
                     quitclaimed and given to them in alms and have remitted
                     for ever, and this same ... I have confirmed by charter.</seg> And that this alms should be established and firm for ever, nor could by any
                  means be declared invalid, the lord William, king of Scots,
                  by [my] petition and request, has granted and given [this]
                  alms to them, and confirmed by his charter. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Richard, abbot of Kelso, Walter Oliphant, William son of John,
                  John of Maxwell, Bernard of Howden, Roger Burnard, Gregory of
                  Rutherford, William of Cresswell, William the parson, my
                  brother, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>