<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/293</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-04-03 14:59:33.618019+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/293</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div><p>C Y R O G R A P H</p> <p>To all the sons of holy Mother Church who shall see or hear the present
               document, G<ex>ilbert</ex>, by the grace of God, bishop of Dunkeld, and J<ex>ohn</ex> and P<ex>hilip</ex>, by the same grace, humble abbots of Lindores and Scone, wish eternal salvation
                  in Christ. Inasmuch as a dispute was moved between the
                  venerable father, the lord Clement bishop of Dunblane, on the
                  one side, and the lord abbot Innocent, and the convent of
                  Inchaffray, on the other side, over the churches of
                  Aberuthven and Tullichettle, and over the teinds coming from
                  rents and all manner of perquisites of the lord earl of
                  Strathearn, which are called second teinds, all which the
                  said bishop claimed, saying that they pertained to his table
                  by reason of his church; at length, on the advice of worthy
                  men, the said bishop, for himself and his successors (with
                  the consent and assent of the whole clergy of Dunblane, to
                  whom the election of the bishop belongs, also with the assent
                  of the lord Robert, earl of Strathern, patron of the same
                  see), and the said abbot and convent, for themselves and
                  their successors, agreed to submit to our arbitration on the
                  aforesaid articles, as also on all other churches and
                  possessions at that time conferred and granted to them, with
                  the addition of the following penalty, that if the same
                  bishop or any of his successors desired to withdraw from our
                  decision, in the first place, if any advantage should come to
                  his church through our decision, he should restore it to the
                  opposite party, and also pay to the fabric of the bridge of
                  Perth two hundred pounds sterling by way of penalty before
                  entering on litigation. And if the abbot and convent or their
                  successors should wish to withdraw from our decision, they
                  shall pay to the same bridge, by way of penalty, before
                  entering on litigation three hundred pounds. The parties,
                  therefore, having appeared in our presence, and the pleadings
                  of each party having been heard and carefully considered, at
                  length, on the advice of those learned in the law, we made
                  the following ordinance, namely, that the said bishop was to
                  abandon the whole action which he was raising, and renounce
                  all right which he sought, or believed that he had, in
                  respect to the matters aforesaid; and that the said abbot and
                  convent was to assign from certain places to the said bishop
                  and his successors, in the name of the church of Dunblane, an
                  annual payment of sixteen pounds sterling, as reckoned by the
                  judgment of worthy men. The parties accepting this our award,
                  to the end that it might obtain the strength of perpetual
                  validity, asked that it might be reduced to writing in the
                  manner of a cyrograph, of which one part sealed with our
                  seals, together with the seal of the said bishop, should
                  remain at the aforesaid monastery of Inchaffray; and the
                  other part sealed similarly with our seals and the seal of
                  the chapter of the same monastery, should remain with the
                  said bishop. Given in the 1234th year since the Incarnation
                  of the Lord, in the month of August.</p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>