<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/204</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:22:03.776274+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/204</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all men as well present as future know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">I, John Avenel, son of Gervase Avenel,</seg> have given, granted, and by this my present charter have made firm, to God and
                     Saint Mary, and the gate of Melrose, for the benefit of
                     the poor who come there, for the salvation of my soul, and
                     of all my ancestors and successors, in pure and perpetual
                     alms, the half-ploughgate of land in the territory of
                     Torthorwald, which William son of Glay gave me in return
                     for my homage and service; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the aforesaid gate of Melrose to have and to hold for ever, as freely,
                     quitely and honourably, in wood, in plain, in meadows and
                     pastures, in roads and paths, in pools and mills, in moors
                     and marshes, in waters and all liberties and easements
                     that belong to that land, just as any alms is freely,
                     quitely, and honourably held and possessed in the whole
                     rekingdom of Scotland; by returning from it to the lord of
                     the feu for every service, custom, exaction and demand,
                     one pound of pepper and the Lord's Nativity, and
                     performing the forinsec service of the lord king, as much
                     as belongs to half a ploughgate of land.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant, maintain and defend the above-said half
                     ploughgate of land to the above-said gate of Melrose, with
                     all its pertinents and liberties, against all men and
                     women for ever</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter, I have cause my seal to be fixed to the present
                  writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord Richard Comyn, the lord Thomas de Normanville,
                  the lord Eymer of Maxwell, the lord Thomas son of Ranulf, the
                  lord Thomas de Chartres, Elias of Dundas, the lord Hugh
                  Mauleverer, Robert son of Elias, Robert Poydras, and many
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>