<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/98</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:18:17.527927+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/98</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts, officials,
                     and all worthy men of his entire land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> me to have granted, and by this my charter to have made firm, to God and to the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks serving God
                     there, the quitclaim which Alan son of Walter my steward
                     made to the same monks in my presence and full court, of
                     the whole claim and every right which the said Alan or his
                     heirs have had or ever could have had in the pasture on
                     the western side of the Leader. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will and instruct that the said monks of Melrose should hold the
                     named land for ever and have it free and quit from every
                     claim from the said Alan and his heirs, as freely and
                     quitly, fully and honourably, as the charter of the said
                     Alan son of Walter my steward bears witness</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Jocelin bishop of Glasgow, John bishop of Dunkeld, Earl David my
                  brother, Earl Duncan, Earl Gilbert, William de Morvillethe
                  constable, William of Lindsay, Malcolm son of Earl Duncan,
                  Walter of Berkeley, Robert of Berkeley, Henry of Graham.</seg> At Edinburgh.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>