<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/137</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:05:01.064431+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/137</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, both present and to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Anselm of Mow</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have given and by this my present charter to have made firm to God and to
                     the church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks serving
                     God in that place, for the souls of my lords, King David,
                     and Earl Henry, and King Malcolm, and for the salvation of
                     my lord William, king of the Scots, and for my own soul,
                     and my wife’s, and of all my ancestors’ and successors’ <ex>souls</ex>, with the advice and agreement of my heirs, the portion of land in the
                     territory of Mow <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">which is next to the monks’ land at Melrose, on the south side of the hill of
                     ‘Hunedune’, and on the east side the boundary is the road
                     which runs from ‘Hunedune’ to Mow, the road which lies
                     between the said land and the church-lands of Mow, as far
                     as the fountain-head of a certain stream on the west side
                     of ‘Kippemoder’, along above all the fountain-heads of the
                     streams on the same side, that is of ‘Kippemoder’, except
                     only for one spring alone towards the west, as far as
                     certain large stones of the old building which is upon a
                     small ridge, the ridge which is to the south side of the
                     land called ‘Cruche’. And afterwards the boundary descends
                     along the same ridge as far as a large stone, and
                     afterwards to another, and thus as far as the rivulet
                     which runs between the said land of ‘Cruch’, that is on
                     the south side of the same ‘Cruch’, and as it descends
                     towards the west as far as the rivulet which is the
                     boundary between the land of the toun of Hownam and Mow.</seg> This whole land and whatever is within the fore-written boundaries next to the
                     monks’ land, that is of the hill of ‘Hunedune’, I have
                     given to God and to St Mary and the whole monastic
                     community at Melrose, in return for half a ploughgate of
                     land, in pure and everlasting alms, free and released from
                     all earthly service and secular exaction, just as any alms
                     can be freely and quitely given. And my lord, King
                     William, for the love of God and the salvation of his own
                     soul and of his ancestors’ <ex>souls</ex>, at my request has granted and by his charter made firm the said land to the
                     same monks. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant to the aforementioned monks the said land for
                     ever, against all men.</seg> And I and my heirs shall discharge the same land for the same monks in respect
                     of forinsec and all earthly service and all other
                     services, by worthy and free men of the land, who are
                     named witnesses of this my charter and donation,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">that is these: Peter, parson of Morebattle; Edward, parson of Linton; Henry le
                  Nain; Ivo the deacon; John son of Orm; Ingram of Domart;
                  Walter Corbet; Robert of Wilton; Robert de Cliponville;
                  Geoffrey Ridel; Ralph le Nain, and Richard le Nain his son;
                  John of Hawick; Uhtred Grubbit, and Adam his son; Hubert and
                  Walter and Ralph, sons of Ralph le Nain; Gilbert, cousin of
                  Peter the parson of Morebattle; Adam son of Orm; Stephen son
                  of William; Richard son of Anselm.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>