<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/342</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-06 15:19:33.759042+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/342</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all, both present and future, know that <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">I, Guy de Normanville,</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">have granted, and by this my charter made firm, to the abbot and convent of
                  Melrose the donation which the lord Thomas de Normanville, my
                  brother, charitably made to the same in respect of the land
                  of Maxton. The said lord Thomas de Normanville, my brother,
                  holds this land of me in exchange for his land of Angus.
                  Wherefore I will and allow that the said abbot and convent of
                  Melrose may hold and possess of the said lord Thomas de
                  Normanville, my brother, the said land of Maxton with
                  messuage, toft, croft, liberties and easements, as it is set
                  out in the charter that the said abbot and convent have from
                  the said lord Thomas de Normanville my brother, fully,
                  quitely and honourably for ever.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter I have caused my seal to be applied to this
                  document.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Dom Ralph the abbot of Balmerino, the lord William son of Patrick
                  the earl of Dunbar, the lord Nicholas Corbet, son of the same
                  William, the lord William de Normanville the rector of the
                  church of Maxton, my brother, the lord Leo my nephew, and
                  many others.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">Enacted in the year of grace 1240 in the month of July.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>