<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/185</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-12 13:45:36.104592+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/185</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Alexander, by the grace of God king of Scots</seg>, to all worthy men of the whole of his land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting:</seg> </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> that I have given, granted, and by this my charter confirmed to God and to the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks serving God
                     there, the whole land of 'Drumteihsuiene', and of
                     'Alesburc', and of 'Auchnephur', which Roger of Skelbrooke
                     gave to them by their correct boundaries contained in the
                     charter of that same Roger, and with everything justly
                     pertaining to the aforesaid lands, to be held in free and
                     pure and perpetual alms with all their easements and just
                     pertinents, as freely and quietly, fully and honourably,
                     as the charter of the aforesaid Roger, and the
                     confirmation of Duncan son of Gilbert made thereupon for
                     the aforesaid monks bear witness, saving my service. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: William, bishop of St Andrews; William del Bois, chancellor; Earl
                  Patrick; Earl Malcolm of Fife; William Comyn, earl of Buchan;
                  Alan son of Roland, constable; Philip de Mowbray; Walter
                  Oliphant; Adam son of Gilbert; Ingram de Balliol; Alexander,
                  sheriff of Stirling; Walter of Lindsay; John of Maxwell. </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Edinburgh, on the second day of October</seg>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>