<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/215</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-01-31 03:48:05.056257+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/215</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, Robert by the grace of God humble servant of
                  the church of St Andrew, Greeting, and episcopal blessing:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Your brotherhood should know that we have by the assent of the whole of our
                  chapter conceded and by our charter affirmed all the things
                  that King David has given in perpetual alms to the church of
                  Holyrood at Edinburgh. That is, the church at the castle with
                  Saughton, and all its other dependencies; and the church of
                  St Cuthbert with everything belonging to it; and the church
                  of Corstorphine with two oxgangs and six acres of land and
                  the rest of the things belonging to it; the church of Airth
                  with its dependencies, and in the same toun two ploughgates
                  of land, and one saltpan with twenty-seven acres of land; the
                  church of Livingston with half a ploughgate of land and all
                  other things which belong to it; and the church of Whitekirk
                  with all its dependencies, and Whitekirk and Ford with their
                  correct bounds; Broughton with its correct bounds; and
                  Inverleith and Pittendriech with their correct bounds; and
                  everything, whatsoever is attested by the king’s charter, and
                  just as it is attested, these as it has been aforesaid we
                  have conceded, and by conceding we have affirmed, and all
                  other things which the aforementioned church in future might
                  justly be able to acquire, reserving the episcopal dignity
                  and authority.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Thorald the archdeacon, Aiulf the dean, William the
                  bishop’s chaplain, Waleran the chaplain, Nicholas the clerk,
                  Master Herbert the Scot, Ralph the bishop’s nephew, Roger the
                  knight and bishop’s nephew, Thurstin son of Living.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>