<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/158</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:19:28.35207+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/158</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Geoffrey son of Waldef of Lilliesleaf</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have given and granted and by this my charter to have made firm to God and
                     to the church of St Mary at Melrose and to the monks
                     serving God in that place, in free, pure, and perpetual
                     alms, four oxgangs of arable land in the territory of
                     Whitton, just as they lie in one holding above ‘Raven’s
                     Fen’, near the land of the same monks which they have from
                     the donation of Patrick of Ryedale my lord; this whole
                     land and whatever is comprised within the said boundaries
                     of the land I have given to the said monks of Melrose
                     free, quit, and loosed from every earthly service and
                     custom and secular exaction, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">that they may have, hold, and possess them for ever as freely, fully and
                     honourably as any alms can be freely, quitely, fully and
                     honourably held and possessed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant to the said monks the same land
                     against all men</seg>, and discharge for ever all forinsec service towards our lords, and all other
                     things which can be exacted for any land.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Robert, archdeacon of Glasgow; Patrick of Ryedale my lord;
                  Walter and Nicholas, his sons; Richard le Naym; Ralph of
                  Ryedale; Richard, parson of Ancrum; Robert of Barnoldby; Adam
                  of Whitton; William of Whitton; Adam of Chatto; and many
                  others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>