<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/244</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-03-30 15:50:06.203911+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/244</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex> by the grace of God king of Scots</seg> to all worthy men of the whole of his land, clerk and lay, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Let present and future know that I have granted, and by this my charter made
                  firm, to God and to the church of Holyrood at Edinburgh, and
                  to the canons serving God there, the donation that Gilbert de
                  Umfraville made to them, of one ploughgate of land in
                  Kinnaird, just as it was perambulated by the worthy men of
                  the country, with common pasture as contained in the charter
                  of the said G<ex>ilbert</ex>, and with freedom of multure and of their own men staying on their land, as
                     contained in the charter of the said G<ex>ilbert</ex>. To be held in free and quiet and perpetual alms, as freely and quietly, fully
                     and honourably as they hold and possess their other lands
                     and holdings, as the charter of the said G<ex>ilbert</ex> bears witness. Reserving my service.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Hugh my chancellor, Robert my chaplain, Jocelin the archdeacon of
                  Dunkeld, Richard de Prebenda my clerks, Philip de Valognes,
                  Walter de Berkeley the chamberlain, Richard son of Hugh,
                  William de Ramsay, Adam of Ceres.</seg> At Edinburgh.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>