<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/30</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 10:00:45.739767+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/30</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church as well present as future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Duncan son of Gilbert son of Fergus,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know that</seg> I have given and granted and by this my charter made firm to God and to the
                     church of St Mary at Melros and to the monks serving God
                     there, for the souls of my lords, the kings David and
                     Malcolm, and of Earl Henry, and for the salvation of my
                     lord King William, and David his brother, and of Earl
                     Duncan, and for my own salvation, and the souls of my
                     father and my mother, and of all my ancestors and
                     successors, in free and pure and perpetual alms, the whole
                     land of Maybole-beg, as they have and possess it in
                     perpetuity, free and quit and loosed from every earthly
                     service and exaction and secular custom, and just as any
                     alms is freely, quietly, fully and honourably possessed in
                     the Kingdom of the Scots, by the boundaries named in this
                     my charter. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">That is, from the head of the burn that descends from <ex>Crumder</ex>, and by the same burn as far as <ex>Culelungford</ex>, and as the same burn descends from <ex>Culelungford </ex>to <ex>Polnetyber</ex>, and as <ex>Polnetyber</ex> falls into the Doon, and by the Doon, upwards as far as where the <ex>Polgarroh</ex> falls into the Doon, and so upwards by <ex>Polgarroh</ex> as far as the small peat bog – it is to be noted, however, that on the southern
                        side of the same peat bog, a syke descends into the <ex>Polgarroh</ex> – and by the same syke upwards as far as the syke goes up to divide into the <ex>Polcogri</ex>, and the <ex>Polcogri</ex> goes up to the <ex>Dufah</ex>, between Maybole-beg and Maybole-mór, and from the same <ex>Dufah</ex> by a syke which goes up to another peat bog, and from the head of that syke
                        across that peat bog, and by the bog as the other syke
                        on the south side of <ex>Brokelaue</ex> goes up to the road, and by the same road upwards as far as the wooded valley
                        which ascends from the said <ex>Crubder</ex> and by the same valley as far as where the same valley descends to <ex>Crubder</ex>.</seg> In addition, I have given to them and by this my charter have made firm the
                     whole land of Beoch, in free, pure and perpetual alms, by
                     their bounds and right marches. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">That is, as the road goes to <ex>Scipsate</ex>, and by the same road as far as the syke that goes through the middle of the
                        bog as far as the head of <ex>Altecreue</ex>, and thence as far as the road that goes beyond <ex>Altecreue</ex> and from that road as far as the syke that by ascending proceeds from the north
                        side of <ex>Cragan</ex>, and by the same syke as far as that place which is called <ex>Tunregaid</ex>, where from that syke a stream which is called <ex>Polsalacharic</ex> comes forth, and thence as the same stream runs, as far as to <ex>Polnetyhered</ex>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">This whole land as well that of Maybole-beg as that of Beoch, and whatever is
                     contained within the aforenamed bounds in wood and plain,
                     in meadows and pastures, in roads and paths, in lands and
                     waters and fisheries, and in all other things and
                     easements I have given to the said monks and the church of
                     Melrose, that they may have and possess them in
                     perpetuity, freely, quietly, fully, honourably, and loosed
                     from every earthly service, just as they hold and possess
                     any alms freely, quietly, fully and honourably, provided
                     that they shall give to me and my heirs, each year, 2
                     merks of silver only, for recognition for the same land of
                     Beoch, 1 merk at Pentecost, and the other at the feast of
                     St Martin.</seg> And the monks shall use everything that is contained within the aforenamed
                     boundaries at their pleasure by all means that seem good
                     and useful to them.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant all these things to them against
                  all men in perpetuity, and we shall acquit with respect to
                  the lord king for all foreign and tenant service.</seg> And since I have wished that this my alms should be firm and established and by
                  no means could be brought to nought, I have placed the bishop
                  and the church of Glasgow as witness and security for all
                  these things, so that if at any time I or my heirs are
                  tempted to deviate from the terms of this charter, the church
                  and its bishops may recall us to correction by ecclesiastical
                  censure. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, the lord Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow, William abbot of
                  Holyrood, Earl Duncan, Earl Gilbert, Simon the archdeacon,
                  the lord Roland, Malcolm the son of Earl Duncan, Aed son of
                  the earl of Lennox, William, Walter and John, the bishop’s
                  clerks, Roger of Skelbrooke, Gilla Asaild mac Gillanders,
                  Gilla na Náem mac Colmán, Edgar my chamberlain. </seg> </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>