<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/40</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 11:35:09.155114+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/40</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div><p>C Y R O G R A P H <lb/></p> <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present as well as future know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">Robert Avenel and Gervase his heir, for the salvation of their souls, and their
                  ancestors' and successors', quitclaimed for ever the four
                  merks which the monks of Melrose at one time were accustomed
                  to render to them annually in ferme in return for the land of
                  Eskdale, to make four pittances to the convent of the same
                  place every year.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">It is also to be known that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">the abbot and the whole aforesaid convent have faithfully conceded to the same
                  Robert and Gervase his heir and to all their heirs that these
                  aforesaid pittances shall be given to the same convent four
                  times every year, on these days: that is, on the day that the
                  lord Robert himself, giving up the secular life, wholly gave
                  himself up to that haouse; and again on the day in which the
                  same lord Robert himself died; and again on the Friday before
                  the Nativity of the Lord [Christmas Day], in commemoration of
                  the soul of the lady Sibyl, wife of the same lord Robert; the
                  fourth day, then, is the day of the death of Gervase; as long
                  as Gervase survived, indeed, he was in his right mind; he
                  willed the same pittance to be given to the convent on this
                  day.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">And it is to be known that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">on these aforenamed days, in the chapterhouse of the same house, commemoration
                  and absolution of their souls shall be made in perpetuity.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">These are the witnesses, Jocelin the bishop of Glasgow, Simon the bishop of
                  Dunblane, Osbert the abbot of Kelso, Archibald the abbot of
                  Dunfermline, Richard the abbot of Jedburgh, Earl David the
                  brother of the king of Scotland, Simon the archdeacon of
                  Glasgow, Glay the nephew of the lord Robert Avenel, Robert
                  the clerk, son of Robert, Master Roger of Newport.</seg></p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>