<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/73 (1)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:14:16.161409+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/73 (1)</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of the Church who shall view or hear the present writing, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Walter son of Alan, steward of the king of Scotland,</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know, all of you, that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">I, in honour of God and for the peace of the Church, and mainly wishing to
                  provide tranquility at Melrose, have thought fit to clarify
                  doubts once contained in the charter of Walter my grandfather
                  given to the monks of Melrose, in that part of the charter,
                  that is, where my said grandfather spoke of untilled lands
                  and haughs and of forest pasture. This I also will, that
                  where there is contained less of charity and security, in
                  this instrument to describe more clearly, and to provide for
                  the monks more fully.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">I have therefore granted to the aforementioned monks all untilled lands and
                  haughs, as well in my forests as outside, on the northern
                  side of the River Ayr, and my whole forest to be used
                  according to what should seem the more useful to them, that
                  is, to be tilled and sown wherever it should seem to them to
                  be suitable, as well within the forest as outside, and for
                  the feeding and pasturing and constantly keeping their flocks
                  within the same forest, as many as they wish, according to
                  what the territory of the same forest is able to contain; and
                  it shall be in the judgment of the monks to calculate how
                  much the same land is able to support. I have also granted to
                  them the use of the same forest in all its easements and
                  benefits; to be had and possessed fully and peaceably for all
                  their own needs; this alone excepted, that [neither] the
                  monks nor the lay-brothers nor any other of their men under
                  authority shall hunt or catch sparrow-hawks in the same
                  forest; for this is not appropriate to their order, not do we
                  believe it to be beneficial for them. All these things have I
                  given, granted, and made firm by this my charter, to God and
                  the aforementioned monks. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I, and my heirs and successors all, shall warrant and defend for the
                     aforesaid monks all the above-said things</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">and we shall cause them to possess them in peace, free and quit from every
                     service and exaction and secular custom</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And so that my grant should be firm and unimpaired, I have handed over the
                  present writing confirmed with my own present seal.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: William, my chaplain; Malcolm, son of the earl of Lennox,
                  my nephew; John of Montgomery; Roger son of Glay; William of
                  Halkerston; Alan Wallace; Humphrey del Bois; John of Lindsay;
                  Hugh, son of Simon son of Bertin; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>