<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/259</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-04 14:41:10.56136+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/259</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">A<ex>lexander</ex> by the grace of God king of Scots to his sheriff and bailies of Dumfries
                     Greeting</seg>: <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Know that we have inspected the charters of the renowned kings David and Malcolm
                  our ancestors, and of the lord King William our father, in
                  which it is contained that the abbot and covnent of Holyrood
                  ought so to have free court in the land of Dunrod – which
                  they hold in Galloway of the gift of Fergus and his heirs –
                  as in the other lands that they have of the gift of our
                  ancestors, that is, in Broughton and Hamera [now Whitekirk].
                  Wherefore we command you and firmly enjoin, that you should
                  by no means permit that any of the heirs of Galloway, or
                  their bailies, obstruct the said abbot and convent, that they
                  may rather have their free court in the said land of Dunrod
                  respecting everything that ought justly to pertain to them;
                  doing as much lest because of your failure it be necessary
                  for the said abbot and convent to return to us once more to
                  complain about this matter.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Henry de Balliol, chamberlain, John de Vaux, Nicholas de Soulis,</seg> at Edinburgh on the 16th day of February, in the thirty-second year of the reign
                  of the lord king.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>