<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/231</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 12:40:45.914978+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/231</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">A<ex>lexander</ex> by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg> to all worthy men of the whole of his land.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know us</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have allowed, and by this our charter to have made firm, the sale that P<ex>atrick</ex> earl of Dunbar, by the agreement of Patrick his son and heir, made to the abbot
                     and convent of Melrose of his whole horse-stud that he had
                     in the feu of Lauder in the Year of Grace One Thousand Two
                     Hundred and Forty-Seven on the feast of the Beheading of
                     John the Baptist. And we have likewise allowed, and by
                     this our charter made firm, the concession and quitclaim
                     that the same earl, with the agreement of the said Patrick
                     his son and heir, made to the same abbot and convent for
                     the common that he had for feeding or pasturing the
                     horse-stud or any other animals within the lands and
                     pastures which the said abbot and convent held and
                     possessed on the said day in the said feu of Lauder, that
                     is, so the said earl or his heirs or anyone else in their
                     name shall in future instigate or have no claim or
                     complaint in the said lands or pastures; which very sale
                     and quitclaim we will to be observed for ever, just as the
                     charter of the foresaid Patrick earl of Dunbar which the
                     said abbot and convent have thereupon rightly bears
                     witness.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, W<ex>illiam</ex> Comyn, earl of Menteith; Alan Durward, justiciar of Scotia; Robert of Roos;
                     David of Lindsay; Thomas de Normanville; Thomas son of
                     Ranulph; Robert Menzies.</seg> At Holyrood on the twenty-eighth day of November, in the thirty-third year of
                  the reign of the lord King. [1247]</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>