<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/275</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:01:46.628849+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/275</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, as well present as future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">William of Landells</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all of you know</seg> me, for my own salvation, of my wife's, and of all my ancestors' and
                     successors', to have given, granted, and by this my
                     present charter to have made firm, to God and to the
                     church of blessed Mary at Melrose, and to the monks in
                     that place serving God and who in perpetuity will be
                     serving God there, all the land in the feu of Hownam which
                     is called 'Brunecnolleflat', <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by the correct boundaries by which the said monks hitherto have held it, viz. as
                     the lower side of 'Bruncnolleflat' on the eastern side
                     lies immediately next to the ancient boundary of Hownam,
                     and from there upwards as far as the lower hill, and from
                     there across towards the west as far as the upper hill,
                     and so by the ridge as the water descends into
                     'Haufurlangburne'.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">All this land and the land of Hownam and the land of 'Rascau', with their
                     pertinents and boundaries, and whatever is contained
                     within their boundaries, without any withholding, I have
                     given, granted and by this my present charter made firm to
                     the said monks for ever, as freely, quitly, and honourably
                     as any alms in the kingdom of Scotland is freely, quitly,
                     and honourably held and possessed; and as they full and
                     usefully held the said lands on the day of the
                     handing-over of this instrument to them.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant, maintain, and defend the said lands with their
                     pertinents to the said monks against all men for ever.</seg> Nothing from the said lands is to be exacted from the aforementioned monks,
                     except only the suffrages of devout prayers.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter, I have applied my seal to the present charter.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, William de Somerville ... Nicholas [of Rutherford],
                  knights, John of Prender[guest], Richard de [Ryedale], Walter
                  of Ryedale, William ...</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>