<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/284</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 09:08:06.271238+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/284</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church present and future <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Walter of Ryedale son of Patrick of Ryedale</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> to have granted and by this my charter to have confirmed to God and to the
                     church of St Mary at Melrose and the monks serving God in
                     that place for the souls of my lords, David, Malcolm, and
                     William, kings of the Scots, and for the soul of my father
                     and of all my ancestors and for the salvation of my lord,
                     Alexander king of the Scots, for my own salvation and of
                     all my successors, the donation of P<ex>atrick</ex> my father which he made to the same monks of a portion of his own land in the
                     territory of Lilliesleaf, in free, pure, and everlasting
                     alms, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">and is contained within these boundaries; that is, from the ford of Clarilawburn
                     on the western side of 'Caldelawe', by the road that goes
                     from Selkirk towards Jedburgh up to the Ale, and so
                     descending by the same river which is the boundary between
                     the land of Lilliesleaf and the bishop of Glasgow's land
                     as far as the syke that is the boundary between the
                     aforementioned land of Lilliesleaf and the abbot of Kelso,
                     and so by the boundaries between the aforenamed land of
                     Lilliesleaf and the same abbot as far as Clarilawburn and
                     so upwards by the same burn as far as the aforesaid ford
                     of Clarilawburn.</seg> This whole land and whatever is contained within these boundaries, except for
                     the land that William son of Alexander holds in the same
                     territory, I have granted to the said monks of Melrose; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">and I will and grant that they have, hold, and possess these things for ever, as
                     freely, quitely, fully, and honourably as any alms freely,
                     quitely, fully, and honourbaly hold and possess</seg>. In addition I have granted to the same monks pasture for twelve oxen, ten
                     cows, fifteen horses and a hundred sheep, with all other
                     common easements of the same toun, just as my father's
                     charter of donation more fully shows and bears witness. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant to the aforesaid monks all things
                     aforesaid in relation to all men and we shall discharge
                     every earthly service, custom and secular exaction for
                     ever in relation to the king and all others.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witness, Earl Patrick, Patrick his son, Robert of Roos, Robert de Muschamp,
                  William son of John, John ofMaxwell, Bernard of Howden,
                  William my son and heir, my cousin William de Ritun, William
                  son of Alexander, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>