<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/153</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:16:01.555211+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/153</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Patrick of Ryedale</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> me to have licensed and by this my charter made firm to God and to the church of
                     St Mary at Melrose and to the monks serving God in that
                     place for my soul and the souls of all my ancestors and
                     successors the donation of Robert of Barnoldby in respect
                     of twenty acres of land, namely ‘Raven’s Fen’, which he
                     made to the said church in free alms from the two
                     ploughgates of land that Robert himself and his heirs hold
                     of me and my heirs in the territory of Whitton which were
                     given to him in return for his service in feu and
                     heritage. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the said monks should hold and possess the said twenty
                     acres by the same boundaries which are contained in
                     Robert’s own charter which the monks have concerning the
                     same land, with all its liberties and pertinents, as
                     freely, quitely, fully and honourably as Robert’s own
                     charter bears witness and affirms, and just as they freely
                     and quitely hold and possess any other alms. Saving my
                     service which Robert himself and his heirs shall do for me
                     and my heirs in return for the same land.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: namely, the lord J(ocelin) bishop of Glasgow; Arnold abbot
                  of Rievaulx; Simon archdeacon of Glasgow; John of Huntingdon;
                  William son of John; Roger of Berkeley; Richard le Neym;
                  Henry of Mow; Adam of Chatto; Ralph of Ryedale; Adam . . .
                  Alexander son of Waldef of Lilliesleaf; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>