<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/249 (1)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 08:07:08.558844+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/249 (1)</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">John by the grace of God Bishop of Whithorn</seg> to all sons and faithful of Holy Mother Church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future come to know that</seg> with the agreement of the whole of our chapter in return for the salvation of
                     our soul and the salvation of the souls of all our
                     predecessors and successors, we have granted and by
                     episcopal authority confirmed by the testimony of the
                     present document, to God and to the church of Holyrood at
                     Edinburgh, and to the canons serving God there now and in
                     the future, in free and pure and perpetual alms, all the
                     churches with their lands that Fergus of good memory, and
                     his son Uhtred, and David son of Terrus, inspired by
                     divine reward, bestowed to the same canons by the
                     agreement of the diocesan bishop, and made firm by their
                     own charters. That is, from the donation of Fergus, the
                     church of Dunrod with the whole toun of Dunrod and all its
                     pertinents; and the isle of Trail; and Galtway with the
                     church of that toun and all its pertinents. From the
                     donation of Uhtred, the church of St Cuthbert of
                     Desnesmor; and the church of Tongland; and the church of
                     Twynholm; and the church of St Andrew; and the church of
                     Kelton; and the church of Kirkcormack with the chapel of
                     Barncrosh. And from the donation of David son of Terrus,
                     the church of Anwoth with the chapel of Culenes and all
                     its pertinents. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore we will and grant by episcopal authority that the aforesaid canons may
                     completely convert to their own benefit all the aforenamed
                     churches with the chapels and all their revenues, and with
                     lands and all their pertinents as they please, and hold
                     and possess them freely and quietly and released from all
                     procuration and custom and exaction in perpetuity,</seg> and they shall cause those churches to be served by chaplains agreeable to
                     themselves, presented by us or our successors, or by
                     themselves if it seems expedient to them, and may remove
                     those less suitable, in consultation with the bishop.
                     Reserving to ourself and our successors only reasonable
                     synodals and common aids from the aforesaid churches,
                     except the churches of Kirkcormack, with the chapel of
                     Barncrosh, and Kelton, which were entirely exempted from
                     synodals and the rest of the episcopal dues by our
                     predecessor of good memory, Bishop Christian, and by us.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Michael the prior of Whithorn, and the chapter of the same
                  place, the lord Alan son of Roland, constable of the lord
                  King of Scots, John the archdeacon, Matthew the dean of
                  Desnes, William the dean of Farines, Gilbert the dean of
                  Rhinns, Walter the parson, Durand the parson of Minnigaff,
                  Martin the clerk of Kirkcudbright, and very many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>