<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/41</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-06 15:19:33.934399+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/41</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Gervase Avenel, son of Robert Avenel</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me to have</seg> granted, and by this my charter to have made firm, to God and to the church of
                     St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks in that place serving
                     God, the donation of my father, to wit, the land of
                     Eskdale, which my father donated to them as everlasting
                     alms, and by his charter made firm, first by the agreement
                     of the most pious King Malcolm, and afterwards by the
                     noble King William, his brother; to wit, <ex>Tumloher </ex>and <ex>Weidkerroc</ex>, as free and pure and perpetual alms, for the soul of the glorious King David,
                     who donated the same land to my father in return for his
                     service, and for the soul of Earl Henry, and of the
                     aforesaid King Malcolm, and for the soul of the aforesaid
                     William, king of Scots, my lord, and of all their
                     ancestors and successors, and for my own soul, and of my
                     wife and all my successors. This land therefore, to wit, <ex>Thumloher</ex> and <ex>Weidkerroc</ex>, I granted to the aforesaid monks, and gave and made firm, and embodied in this
                     my charter, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by these boundaries: namely, as the two Esks meet, so upwards by the Black Esk
                     as far as the first stream that descends from Hartside;
                     and from that stream, upwards through the middle ridge of
                     the mountains, between themselves and Robert de Brus, as
                     the waters descend towards the monks themselves; and so
                     between the forest of <ex>Thimeus</ex> and themselves, by the middle ridge of the mountains, as they descend towards
                        themselves; similarly between the land of <ex>Bordewich</ex> and the monks themselves, by the middle ridge of the mountains, as the waters
                        descend towards them; and so as far as the land of <ex>Hawich</ex>, and thence across by the middle ridge of the mountains, that is, between
                        myself and the aforesaid monks, as the waters descend
                        towards them; this ridge extends from above <ex>Harewude</ex>, and so descends to where the two Esks meet.</seg> This whole land and possession, just enumerated, and whatever is contained
                     within these aforesaid boundaries, in wood and plain, in
                     meadows and pastures, in waters and marshes, and in all
                     usages and easements, I have granted and given and made
                     firm to the aforesaid monks as pure and everlasting alms, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held and possessed by everlasting right, free and quit from me and my
                     heirs, and released from all services, and from every
                     custom and secular exaction, just as freely and quietly,
                     fully and honourably as any alms can be held and
                     possessed.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And if anyone should at any time wish to claim this aforesaid land, I and my
                     heirs shall answer every claimant and sufficiently defend
                     and warrant it for the aforesaid monks.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">This is also to be known:</seg> that I retain for myself and my heirs only deer and hind, swine and roebuck,
                     within the aforenamed boundaries, without harm and injury
                     of crops, meadows, hedges, livestock, animals, and all the
                     other possessions of the same monks. Provided however that
                     I and my heirs shall not have a forester within the
                     described boundaries, nevertheless we shall have within
                     the same boundaries robbers, and eyries of hawks and
                     sparrow-hawks, and the guards to guard them, and
                     trespassers, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">and it should be known that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">the aforesaid monks shall have and possess the whole aforesaid land, free and
                     quit from me and my heirs, saving my aforesaid wild game,
                     and the eyries of hawks and sparrow-hawks;</seg> and the monks shall make use of all this tenement according to their will and
                     pleasure, just as it shall seem to them best and most
                     useful to be of use to themselves, their brethren, their
                     servants and livestock. With the exception that they shall
                     not hunt there with packs of hounds and ropes, nor bring
                     others there for hunting, nor set traps there, unless for
                     catching wolves; and they shall not take the eyries of
                     hawks and sparrow-hawks within these boundaries. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">It should be known in addition that</seg> the five merks that my father at one time received from them as ferm, and which
                     he and my mother quit claimed before their death, these I
                     likewise have quitclaimed and given to them in alms, and
                     remitted for ever, and this same I have made firm by the
                     present charter. And that this alms may be established and
                     firm for ever and not able to be brought by any means to
                     nought, my lord William, king of Scots, at my entreaty and
                     request, has conceded and given the same alms, and made it
                     firm by his own charter.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">Witnesses: Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow; Symeon, bishop of Dunblane; Archibald,
                  abbot of Dunfermline; Osbert, abbot of Kelso; Richard, abbot
                  of Jedburgh; Simon, archdeacon; Guy, prior of Kelso; Richard,
                  dean Hassendean; Master Roger of Newport; Master John of
                  Roxburgh; Master Adam of Hirsel; William the steward; … the
                  parson of Lilliesleaf; Walter, clerk; Hugh, clerk; Walter
                  Olifard; Walter Corbet; William de la Haye; Gervase, nephew
                  of Robert Avenel; Glay his nephew; Robert son of Robert
                  Avenel; … of the king of Scots.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>