<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/1</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-07-22 17:22:55.816644+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/1</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">David, by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg>, to his bishops, abbots, earls, barons, and worthy men, and to all his sworn
                     men of his entire kingdom, French, and English, and
                     Gaelic, and Galwegian, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting:</seg></seg> Know me, for the sake of my soul and the souls of my father and mother, and of
                  my brother Edgar, and of my other brothers and my sisters,
                  and of my wife Matilda, and also for the sake of the soul of
                  Henry my son and heir, and of my ancestors and successors, to
                  have granted and given to God and St Mary at Melrose, and to
                  the monks of Rievaulx serving God there, with Henry my son
                  and heir approving and consenting, and affirming by his own
                  charter, in perpetual alms, the whole land of Melrose, and
                  the whole land of Eildon, and the whole land of Darnick, by
                  their boundaries and correct divisions, in wood and plain, in
                  meadows and waters, in pastures and moors, in roads and
                  paths, and in all other things, free and quit and loosed from
                  all earthly service and worldly exaction, to possess in
                  perpetual tenure. Moreover, know me to have given to the
                  aforesaid monks, and made firm by this my charter, in my land
                  and in my forests of Selkirk and at Traquair, all their
                  easements, that is, pasture for their cattle, and wood, and
                  timber, and pannage everywhere for their own uses, as well as
                  I myself have for my own use, especially between Gala and
                  Leader. Moreover, in the waters of the Tweed, within their
                  boundaries, fishing as well on my side of the stream as
                  anywhere on their side. Besides all the things said above, I
                  have given and made firm to them, for an augmentation,
                  Gatton, and the whole land and wood of Gattonside, just as I
                  myself and Henry my son, and Abbot Richard of the same church
                  went before and around on Friday, the morrow of the Ascension
                  of the Lord, in the second year in which Stephen king of
                  England was held captive. As witnesses to this present gift,
                  John the bishop, William the king’s nephew, Hugh de Morville,
                  William de Somerville, Henry son of Swain, Gervase Ridel. I
                  therefore will that they should hold and possess all these
                  their aforesaid lands and things so freely and quitely as any
                  alms can be freely and quitely held and possessed in
                  perpetual tenure. As witness, Henry my son, John the bishop,
                  William my nephew, William the chancellor, Madad the earl,
                  Robert de Umfraville, Hugh de Morville, Walter son of Alan,
                  Hugh Brett, Osbert of Arden, Gervase Ridel, William de
                  Somerville, Richard Gernun, Richard English, William of
                  Lindsay, Ascelin the archdeacon, Jordan the clerk, Eastmund
                  the almoner. In addition, the men of the same land, Gospatic
                  the earl, Ulkil son of Æthelstan, Osulf son of Uhtred, Maccus
                  son of Undweyn, Uhtred son of Sioth, Uhtred son of Gospatric,
                  Orm son of Eilaf, Eilaf son of Gospatric, Eadwulf son of
                  Norman, Osulf son of Eadgifu, Osulf son of Ælfstan, Robert
                  Bruce meschin, Ralph son of Thurstan, Robert the bishop’s
                  nephew. At Earlston, in June.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>