<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/266</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 12:40:03.063835+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/266</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">A<ex>lexander</ex> by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg> to all worthy men, clerk and lay, of the whole of his land.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">us to have given, granted, and by this our charter made firm, for the honour of
                  God and his glorious virgin Mother, as well as for our own
                  salvation and our ancestors’ and successors’, to the monks of
                  Melrose serving God in that place and who will serve there in
                  perpetuity, the fishery on the Tweed which is called the
                  fishery of Selkirk; and seven acres of land with buildings
                  and a meadow contained within those seven acres of land, just
                  as the same seven acres of land of the same monks were
                  enclosed by a ditch and fence on the day of this conveyance;
                  and also a pasture for eight oxen and eight cows in ‘Wauhop’.
                  We have also allowed to the said monks that they, by the view
                  of our foresters at the time, may have and take timber in our
                  forest for the upkeep of their stank in the same fishery. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For them to hold and to have for ever in free, pure, and everlasting alms, as
                     freely, quitely, fully, and honourably as any alms out of
                     our gift is freely, quitely, fully and honourably held or
                     possessed by any religious men in our kingdom</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, the venerable father W<ex>illiam</ex>, bishop of Glasgow, our chancellor; Philip, abbot of Jedburgh; David of
                     Lindsay, justiciar of Lothian; Bernard of Ripley.</seg> At Jedburgh on the eighth day of February, in the thirty-third year of the reign
                  of the lord king [1247].</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>