<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/211</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 16:03:23.22088+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/211</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all the sons of holy mother Church present and to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">John, son of Michael of Methil</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let your whole community know</seg> me to have given, granted, and by this my charter to have made firm, to God and
                     the church of St Mary at Melrose, and the monks in that
                     place who serve God now and in the future, my whole land
                     at Penshiels; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">for the said monks to have and to hold of me and my heirs in pure and
                     everlasting alms for ever, as freely, quitely, fully and
                     honourably as any <supplied>alms in the kingdom</supplied> of Scotland are freely, quitely and fully held and possessed; in wood and plain,
                        in lands cultivated and uncultivated, in . . . , in
                        roads and paths, in moors, peat-bogs, and marshes, in
                        running waters and pools, fish-ponds and mills, and . .
                        . easements which can be found or exercised within the
                        foresaid land; </seg> by paying thereupon yearly at Whitsunday to the the one who is prior of Melrose
                     at the time three merks of silver, which for the salvation
                     of my soul and the souls of my heirs I have assigned for
                     purchasing a pittance annually on the day of the Holy
                     Trinity, to the monastic community of Melrose, to be
                     dispensed by the hands of the said prior. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and defend to the foresaid monks the whole
                     land aforesaid, with all its liberties and just
                     pertinents, against all men;</seg> excepting the lands which I have given to the monks of May, and excepting the
                     land which I have allowed to Henry Little and his heirs,
                     by their correct boundaries, in the territory of
                     [Pen]shiels. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">But the whole land aforesaid, as it is said, the said monks of Melrose shall
                     hold and have . . . and quit from all service, custom,
                     exaction and demand of me and my heirs for ever, doing as
                     aforesaid.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord Alan, abbot of St Edward's at Balmerino; Thomas,
                  earl of Atholl; Walter, son of Alan, steward of the lord
                  king, W., his chaplain; Thomas of Kent; Master John
                  'Abigensi'; Mastcr Ness, physician of the lord king; Malcolm,
                  son of the earl of Lennox; Geoffrey del Bois; James, son of
                  William; John Comyn; Andrew of Swinton; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>