<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/125</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:00:52.271082+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/125</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Florence by the grace of God (bishop) elect of Glasgow</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg> to all who shall see or hear these letters.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> us by the advice and consent of the chapter of Glasgow and the clergy of our
                     diocese to have granted and by this our charter to have
                     made firm to God and to St Mary and the church of Melrose
                     and to the monks serving God in that place, in free and
                     quit and everlasting alms, the church of Hassendean with
                     lands and teinds and everything belonging to it, for the
                     perpetual support of the poor and the pilgrims coming to
                     the (monastic) house of Melrose. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In addition, moved by religious compassion, we have granted to the same monks
                     and we have directed to be made firm by this our charter,
                     that when, God willing, the gift of our consecration has
                     been obtained, we shall confirm to the same the aforesaid
                     church of Hassendean with all liberties granted to them by
                     our predecessor, Jocelin of good memory, bishop of
                     Glasgow, by episcopal seal</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: R(obert) the archdeacon; John the official; Benedict the
                  chaplain; Maurice and Master Henry our clerks; Henry the
                  queen's clerk; Gregory of Stobbo; Theodore our nephew;
                  Nicholas, Ingram, Stephen, Walter, Haimo, our servants; and
                  many other persons of the diocese of Glasgow.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>