<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/152</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:15:16.379082+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/152</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church as well present as to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert of Barnoldby</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me by the consent and will of my heirs to have given and granted and by this my
                     charter to have made firm to God and to the church of St
                     Mary at Melrose and to the monks serving God in that
                     place, for the soul of my lord Ansketil of Ryedale and of
                     all his ancestors and successors, and for my own soul and
                     of all my ancestors’ and successors’ <ex>souls</ex>, twenty acres of land, namely ‘Raven’s Fen’ <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by the boundaries which I and the monks of Melrose walked around, namely, from
                     the upper head of ‘Harrowdean’, the whole sedge-bed,
                     upwards as far as the land that William of Ryedale gave to
                     Matilda Corbet his wife as a marriage-portion, and from
                     there upwards towards Whitton as the ditch is drawn
                     between the said land and ‘Raven’s Fen’, as far as the
                     trench which the monks made, and from there across towards
                     Harrow, as far as the small thornbush, and from there as
                     the the trenches have been made between the land of the
                     lord Patrick and ‘Raven’s Fen’ as far as ‘Harecar’, and
                     from there as the old fosse descends to ‘Harrowdean’.</seg> This whole land which is comprised between the said boundaries with all its
                     pertinents I have given to the said church in return for
                     twenty acres of land free, loosed and quit from every
                     earthly service and custom and secular exaction, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held and possessed as freely, quitely, fully, and honourably as it holds
                     and possesses any alms.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">For I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant to the monks the said land against
                     all men in respect of all things that can be exacted in
                     return for land.</seg></seg> And so that this my alms should be strong and established for ever, my lord
                  Patrick of Ryedale at my request has licensed it and affirmed
                  it by his charter. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And since I do not have a seal, the lord Simon, archdeacon of Glasgow, and
                  William son of John to apply their seals to the present
                  charter.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord Jocelin, bishop of Glasgow; Arnold abbot of
                  Rievaulx; Simon, archdeacon of Glasgow; Patrick of Ryedale
                  and Walter his son; William son of John; Richard le Nain;
                  Henry of Mow; Simon of Grubbit; Adam of Chatto; Adam of
                  Whitton; Ralph of Ryedale.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>