<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/155</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:16:38.104696+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/155</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall see or hear these letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Patrick of Ryedale</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have licensed and by this my charter to have made firm to God and to the
                     Church of St Mary at Melrose and to the monks serving God
                     in that place, in free, pure, and perpetual alms, the
                     donation of Robert of Barnoldby which he made to the
                     aforementioned church in respect of that portion of land
                     in the territory of Whitton which is comprised <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">within these boundaries, namely, from the head of ‘Harrowdean’ going up towards
                     the west by the syke that is the division between the same
                     land and that which is called ‘[?] the land of the Dower’,
                     as far as the thornbush opposite the meadow, and from
                     there across towards the south along the length of the
                     furrow which is the division between the same land and
                     that which William the parson of Hownam held at ferm of
                     the aforementioned Robert of Barnodlby, as far as a fosse
                     that is the division between the said lands to the south
                     side, and from there downwards towards the east as the
                     ditch goes between the aforewritten lands up to the said
                     head at ‘Harrowdean’.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the said monks of Melrose should hold and possess the said
                     land as freely and quitely, fully and honourably by all
                     means, just as the charter of the aforesaid Robert bears
                     witness and affirms;</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">so that I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant to the aforesaid monks the
                     same land against all men for ever;</seg> saving only my service from the said Robert and his heirs.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">Witness: Master John of Huntingdon; Thomas of Colville; Richard le Naym; Roger
                  Burnard; John de Perndell; William Chernun; Richard of
                  Coxwald; Michael of Makerstoun; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>