<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/281</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-03-30 12:43:08.221762+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/281</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church, Thomas of Lundin sends Greeting:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Let present and future know that I have given and granted and by this my charter
                  made firm to God and to the church of Blessed Mary at North
                  Berwick and to the monks serving God there, in free and pure
                  and perpetual alms, twelve acres of land on the north side of
                  Aithernie. Futhermore, I have given and granted to the same
                  nuns the common pasture of my land at ... which descends to
                  the head of the ‘Cnoc derenin’ on the west side; and that
                  they may take fuel for their own use and what shall be of use
                  to them within the same bounds. I have given, moreover, and
                  granted and quitclaimed for myself and my heirs in perpetuity
                  the blanch land that was in dispute, between Pratis and
                  Montrave, and towards the east as the high road falls into
                  the valley. For them and their successors to hold of me and
                  my heirs in free and pure and perpetual alms, as freely and
                  quietly, fully and honourably, as any alms is freely,
                  quietly, fully and honourably held and possessed of any baron
                  in the kingdom of the Scots.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, Earl Malcolm of Fife, Ness of Ramsay, Alexander Uviet, Thomas of
                  Kilmaron, William of Wyville, Alexander of Blair, Alexander
                  of Ceres, Richard English, Walter and Alexander, chaplains,
                  Hugh the clerk, David of Ayton, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>