<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/144</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:11:33.107085+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/144</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall see or hear this written deed, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Walter son of Alan, steward of the lord King of Scotland</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let your whole community know</seg> me to have given and granted to God and to blessed Mary at Melrose and to the
                     monks serving God in that place the whole land of Mow by
                     its correct boundaries and whatever is contained within
                     the same boundaries with all its pertinents which I held
                     in feu of the lord William de Vescy and all rights and
                     public functions which applied to me or could apply by
                     reason of the same or in the same, in free, pure, and
                     perpetual alms <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to have, possess and hold for ever, as freely, quitely, fully and honourably as
                     any alms in the kingdom of Scotland is freely, quitely,
                     fully and honourably held and possessed.</seg> Neither I nor my heirs shall in the future claim back any right in the same land
                     or in the things contained within the boundaires of the
                     same land for ever; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">but we shall warrant, defend, and maintain against all people for ever to the
                     same monks with everything mentioned before, free from
                     every exaction, service, custom and whatever other service</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">As witness of this matter I have secured the present written deed by the
                  application of my seal</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Thomas Crook, Simon son of Bertolf, Adam Wallace, William
                  of Halkerston, Robert of Kippo, knights; William Broun,
                  master of the nuns of South Berwick; William and Robert our
                  chaplains; Leon de Normanville, Richard of Musselburgh, and
                  John of Leicester, monks of Melrose; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>