<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/174</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-06-29 15:38:41.470387+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/174</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">Alexander by the grace of God king of Scots to the bishops, abbots, earls,
                  barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts, officials, and all
                  worthy men of his whole land, clerk and lay, greeting:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future know</seg> that I have granted, and by this my charter confirmed, to the church of St Mary
                     at Melrose, and to the monks serving God there, the
                     donation that Walter son of Alan made to the same church
                     and monks, of the land of Mauchline, and of pasture in his
                     forest; and of one ploughgate of land towards the land of
                     Douglas, and of a fishery at the mouth of the River Ayr,
                     and of the land of Edmonston, and of twenty acres of land
                     with a toft at Berwick. Also, the whole of the land that
                     John son of Orm gave to them in the territory of Hownam,
                     by those right bounds that are contained in the charter of
                     the aforesaid John that they have of him from the same
                     land. Also, the whole land within the feu of Hownam, from
                     the Capehope Burn upwards by that pathway to the boundary
                     between Raeshaw and Cuthberthope, and from there by the
                     same right bounds that are described in the charter of
                     William the son of John, which they have from him. Also,
                     the donation of the land of Ringwood that Osulf the son of
                     Uhtred, and Uhtred his son, bestowed to them. Also, the
                     donation that Cosptric made the same monks of the land of
                     Hartside, and Spott, and a saltpan. Also, the donation
                     that William de Bruce made to them of a fishery near the
                     church of Rainpatrick, with one acre of land and pasture
                     for four cows, and six oxen, and other easements of the
                     toun of Rainpatrick. Also, two oxgangs of land, and two
                     acres of meadow, with pasture for four hundred ewes that
                     the abbot and convent of Kelso gave to them as a token of
                     the peace made between them. Also, the whole land that
                     they have from Patrick of Ryedale in the territory of
                     Whitton, by those bounds that are contained in the charter
                     of Patrick of Ryedale, which they have from him concerning
                     the same land. Also, the donation that Richard de Morville
                     and Avicia his wife made of the chapel of Park to the same
                     monks, with the land belonging to it; and in addition, of
                     the land of Milkenesside, by its right bounds, which are
                     contained in the charter of the aforesaid Richard and
                     Avicia his wife. Also, the whole land and pasture that
                     William de Morville gave to them to enlarge the aforesaid
                     land of Milkenesside by the right bounds described in
                     Williams’s charter. Also, the whole portion of land in the
                     territory of Kilbewocistun, which Alan son of Roland gave
                     them, by the right bounds described in Alan’s charter, in
                     exchange for the land that William de Morville apportioned
                     to them in Cunningham, with common pasture and other
                     easements of the aforesaid toun, just as it is contained
                     in Alan’s charter. Also, the land that Walter Corbet, son
                     of Walter Corbet, gave them in the territory of Clifton,
                     by the right bounds described in the charter of the same
                     Walter Corbet that they have from him concerning the same
                     land. Also, that half-ploughgate of land, in land and
                     meadow, which Anselm of Whitton gave them from his feu of
                     Mow, by the same rights bounds that are contained in
                     Anslem’s charter that the monks have from him. Also, the
                     donation that Earl Patrick made to them of the whole
                     arable land called Sorrowlessfield beyond Leader from the
                     western side towards the grange of the aforesaid monks,
                     just as William Sorrowless fully held it. Also, a
                     half-ploughgate of the land that Richard of London gave
                     them in Lessudden, just as Richard’s charter to them bears
                     witness. I have also granted to them the quit claim that
                     David Oliphant and Walter his son and heir made to God and
                     the church of Melrose and the aforesaid monks, of
                     Hartside, and of Spott, just as it is contained in the
                     charter of the lord king, William my father. I have also
                     granted the friendly agreement made between Earl Patrick
                     of Dunbar and the aforesaid monks over the controversy
                     that arose between them concerning the pasture to the west
                     of the Leader, just as the writing made on the matter
                     bears witness. I have also granted them the quit claim
                     that Alan son of Walter made to them for the claim there
                     was between them on the pasture on the west side of the
                     Leader. For this reason I will and command that the
                     aforesaid monks shall have and hold all these aforesaid
                     possessions in free and perpetual alms, as freely and
                     quietly, fully and honourably, as the charters of the
                     donors and the confirmations of my predecessors bear
                     witness, saving my service.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: William del Bois my chancellor, Saer de Quincy earl of Winchester,
                  Earl Malcolm of Fife, Philip de Valgones my chamberlain,
                  William de Valognes his son, Robert my chaplain, John of
                  Maxwell, David the marischal, Thomas of Lundie my doorward,
                  Hervey the marischal, Jordan Comyn.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="dating">At Edinburgh on the third day of April.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>