<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/278</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 08:39:47.499965+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/278</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Jocelin, by the grace of God bishop of Glasgow,</seg> to all sons of Holy Mother Church, both present and future, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">Greeting in the Lord</seg>:</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">You should all know</seg> that, at the request and by the consent of Roger de Skelbrooke, we have given,
                     granted, and by this our charter made firm, to God and to
                     the church of St Mary at North Berwick, and to the nuns
                     serving God there, in free and perpetual alms, the church
                     of Kirkbride in Largs, with half a ploughgate of land, and
                     with one saltpan, and with two acres at the croft, and
                     with teinds and oblations and all other things rightfully
                     belonging to that church, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held as freely, quietly, fully and honourably as any religious house holds
                     aand possesses any church in our bishopric.</seg> We have also granted to the forementioned nuns that may at will convert all
                     revenues and profits of that church to their own use in
                     perpetuity, saving the episcopal dues.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Ralph the abbot of Melrose, Simon our archdeacon, Herbert
                  the dean of Glasgow, Christian the dean of Carrick, Elias,
                  William, canons of Glasgow, Richard, clerk of Dundonald,
                  John, Walter, Gervase, our clerks, Alexander of Cunningham,
                  chaplain.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>