<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/140</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:01:51.697184+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/140</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall see or hear this charter, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Simon Mauleverer and Gilbert Avenel</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">send greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let your whole community know</seg> us to have granted and by our present charter to have made firm to Helen
                     daughter of Simon of Lindsay the land of ‘Hungerigge’ in
                     the territory of Mow, that is, which the said Helen holds
                     in our feu of Mow of Robert of Pollok and Isabel his wife.
                     And in addition a portion <ex>of land</ex> near ‘Hederedesete’ in our land, which is called ‘Holemede’. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For the said Helen and her heirs to have and to hold of us and our heirs for
                     ever by right of heritage, freely, quitely, fully and
                     honourably, in the same way in all things and through all
                     things, just as the charter of Simon of Lindsay, her
                     father, shows, bears witness and confirms</seg>. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And that this our grant and confirmation to the same Helen and her heirs should
                     endure established and undisputed into the future, I Simon
                     Mauleverer apply my seal to this charter. And I Gilbert
                     Avenel, since I do not have my own seal, have confirmed it
                     with the seal of my father, William Avenel</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Richard of Lincoln; Ralph le Nain; Simon of Grubbit; Adam
                  of Yetholm; John of Munford; Adam son of Nicholas; Henry son
                  of Ulf; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>