<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/134</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 15:02:32.291977+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/134</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Anselm of Whitton</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg> to all sons of Holy Mother Church both present as well as to come.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present as well as future know</seg> me to have given and by this my charter to have made firm to God and to the <ex>monastic</ex> house of Melrose, and to the monks serving God in that place, in perpetual alms
                     my whole peatery which is [between] Mowhope and Berhope
                     and ‘Herdstrete’ which divides the land of Mow and Hownam,
                     for the soul of King David, and Earl Henry, and King
                     Malcolm, and for the salvation of King William, and David
                     his brother, and for my own soul and my wife’s and my
                     childrens’ <ex>souls</ex>. And so the monks of Melrose shall hold the said peatery in pure and
                     everlasting alms, quit and free from all aids and all
                     customs. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall warrant to the said monks the same peatery in respect
                     of all men for ever.</seg> In addition I have given to them in everlasting alms in my wood of Mowhope as
                     much firewood as one horse can carry to their grange of
                     Hownam each year from Easter to the Nativity of Saint
                     Mary, by the same liberty by which I gave them the
                     peatery.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Simon archdeacon of Glasgow; Richard dean of Hassendean;
                  Peter the parson of Morebattle; William the parson of Hownam;
                  John son of Orm, and William his son; William de Somerville;
                  Roger of Wilton; William of London.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>