<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/215</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 16:06:15.856821+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/215</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all the sons of holy mother Church, as well present as to come, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">John son of Michael</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> to have given and granted, and by this my present charter to have made firm, to
                     God and the church of St Mary at Melrose and the monks in
                     that place serving God, all that land which Uhtred the
                     smith and Oliver his son held in my land of Penshiel, all
                     that land, that is, which is on the eastern side of the
                     Faseny <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">within these bounds: From the ford, that is, of Faseny, by the path which is
                     called Richard's road, as far as the head of Killmad, and
                     thence by the stream which runs into Killmad, as far as
                     the Whiteadder</seg>; in pure and perpetual alms; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held and possessed of me and my heirs for ever, as freely and quitely,
                     fully and honourably, as they hold or possess any alms in
                     the whole realm of Scotland;</seg> therefore this whole land, and whatever is contained within the foresaid bounds,
                     with all easements justly pertaining to my whole land of
                     Penshiel, the foresaid monks shall hold of me and my
                     heirs, free and quit from all service pertaining to the
                     land, custom, or secular exaction. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant to the foresaid monks all the
                     foresaid land, with all the foresaid easements, and
                     discharge them from all service pertaining to the lands
                     against all men</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Master M<ex>atthew</ex>, chancellor; Master P. of Ramesay; G. and J., my chaplains; Bernard Fraser;
                     Adam of Polwarth; Henry of Abernethy; Richard Moneypenny;
                     Maurice son of Robert; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>