<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/53</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 12:26:30.846821+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/53</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex> by the grace of God king of the Scots</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg> to all worthy men of his land, French, English and Scots.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let both those to come as well as those present know</seg> me to have granted and by this my charter to have made firm to the church of St
                     Mary at Melrose and to the monks serving God in that place
                     the donation that Earl Cospatric has made to the same
                     church and monks by the agreement and permission of his
                     heir in respect of the land Hartside and Spot, and of a
                     saltpan, for the salvation of his soul and the souls of
                     his predecessors, in all things so freely and quietly in
                     everlasting alms, as freely and quietly the charter of
                     Cospatric himself for them bears witness.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">Witness Richard bishop of St Andrews, Ingram bishop of Glasgow, John abbot of
                  Kelso, Osbert abbot of Jedburgh, Nicholas the chancellor,
                  Matthew the archdeacon of St Andrews, Richard de Morville,
                  Walter son of Alan, Walter Corbet, Robert Avenel, Gilbert son
                  of Richer, Philip de Volognes, Bernard son of Brian, Robert
                  son of Guy, Ralph de Clare, William de Mortimer, Richard the
                  chaplain, Imer the clerk, William de la Haye, Ralph le Nain,
                  Walter of Barclay.</seg> At Lanark.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>