<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD45/13/283</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 09:10:49.255138+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD45/13/283</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div><p>C Y R O G R A P H</p> <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="narration">Inasmuch as there was a dispute between the prioress and convent of the nuns of
                  North Berwick on the one side, and the abbot and convent of
                  St Serf on the other, over the teinds of the earl of Fife
                  from all his ferms and profits and revenues and gifts, and
                  over the second teinds belonging to the their own house from
                  the corn, flour, hops, provender and every type of grain,
                  cheese, and butter; at last, with the noble man, Malcolm earl
                  of Fife, patron of both houses, acting as procurator, he
                  interposed an amicable agreement between them, to the end
                  that either party might be strengthened by the security of
                  perpetual peace. Willingly received from either side, both by
                  the prioress for herself and her convent concerning their
                  said mandate, and by the abbot for himself and his convent
                  for their mandate, fortified by an interposed oath, such
                  namely that the said prioress and nuns each year in
                  perpetuity, for the sake of peace, to the said abbot and
                  convent of St Serf, or to their authentic representative sent
                  by letter, shall pay twenty pounds of good sterling at the
                  monastery of North Berwick, half at the feast of St Andrew,
                  and half at the Nativity of St John the Baptist, with such a
                  condition added, that if the said money were not paid to them
                  or to their authentic representative sent by letter, at the
                  place and times stated above, from then, each month, by way
                  of penalty, one merk of silver is paid to the monk who is
                  gatekeeper of St Serf at the gate of the said monastery, to
                  be distributed by his own hand to the poor until such time as
                  the said money has been paid. And for these things faithfully
                  to be observed they bound their moveable and immoveable
                  goods. The said abbot and convent, on account of the
                  aforementioned agreements, renounced every right they used to
                  have in the aforementioned teinds, and they unsealed the
                  written instruments which they had held concerning these
                  matters, to be struck through and considered invalid for
                  ever. And lest any of the parties could at any time ever
                  protest against this agreement, either side renounced every
                  legal action, exception, cavil, both already brought and to
                  be brought, and petition of restitution in full, and every
                  remedy of civil and canon law, putting themselves under the
                  jurisdiction of the bishop of St Andrews, so that he might
                  compel the opposing party to the observance of this agreement
                  by ecclesiastical censure with the appeal withdrawn.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">And to the end that this agreement should obtain everlasting authority and
                  strength, the parties took care that the seals of the
                  venerable father, W<ex>illiam</ex>, by the grace of God bishop of St Andrews, and of the said Malcolm, their
                     patron, were applied to each part of this written deed,
                     drawn up in the manner of a cyrograph, with their own seal
                     having been applied at the same time in like manner.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, the lord Malcolm Earl of Fife, Master Peter of Ramsay,
                  Master Henry of Norham, Rober the clerk, the lord William of
                  Blair, the lord Ness of Ramsay, the lord Malcolm of Menteith,
                  Duncan of Ramsay, Duncan of Blair, Maurice the sergeand of
                  the countess of Fife, Odinel, Malcolm of Norham, Elias of
                  Cults, and many others.</seg> Done in the year of grace 1237, within the octave of the apostles Peter and
                  Paul.</p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>