<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/167</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-06 12:41:57.231279+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/167</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To All sons of Holy Mother Church present and future <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Walter of Ryedale son and heir of Patrick of Ryedale</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg></seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me</seg> to have granted and by this my charter to have made firm to God and to the
                     Church of St Mary at Melrose, and to the monks serving God
                     in that place, for the salvation of my soul and the soul
                     of my father and for the souls of all my ancestors and
                     successors all the donations that my father gave to the
                     same monks in the territory of Whitton, in perpetual alms,
                     by the borders and boundaries named in the charters of my
                     father, as freely and quitely, fully and honourably, as
                     the charters of my father more fully bear witness. I have
                     also granted to them and by this my charter have made firm
                     all the confirmations of my father and all the lands that
                     they have from Robert of Barnoldby and of Geoffrey the
                     cook, as the charters of Robert and of the same Geoffrey
                     and the confirmations of my father bear witness. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will that the foresaid monks hold and possess the whole lands
                     forenamed well and in peace with all their borders and
                     boundaries as pure alms, quit and released from every
                     earthly service and custom and secular exaction according
                     to the terms of the forenamed charters, saving the service
                     of the same Robert and Geoffrey the cook.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Richard, dean of Teviotdale and official; William son of
                  John; Thomas de Colville; Richard le Nain; Simon of Grubbit;
                  Ralph of Ryedale; John of Maxwell; Adam of Chatto; Adam of
                  Whitton; Richard of Heton; Hugh of Newbattle; William my
                  nephew; and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>