<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/288</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 08:23:22.387766+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/288</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all sons of Holy Mother Church present and future <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Margery de Vescy</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know me all of you</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">to have granted and by this my charter to have made firm to God and to the
                  church of St Mary at Melrose and the monks in that place
                  serving God for the salvation of my own soul and all my
                  ancestors' and successors' (souls), one ploughgate of land in
                  the territory of Lillliesleaf, that is, the one which Walter
                  of Ryedale son of Patrick gave with all easements and
                  liberties and by the same boundaries which are contained in
                  the charter of the aforesaid Walter. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will and grant that the aforesaid monks should have and hold the
                     aforesaid land in free, pure and everlasting alms, with
                     all easements and liberties pertaining to the same, as
                     freely, quitely, fully and honourably, without every
                     custom and secular exaction, just as they hold and possess
                     any alms freely, quietly, fully and honourably in the
                     kingdom of Scotland, reserving to myself and my heirs the
                     service pertaining to the same land from the aforesaid
                     Walter de Ryedale an his heirs.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I and my heirs shall maintain and warrant all things aforesaid to the
                     aforementioned monks, that they may have, hold, possess
                     and use them by all means which seem best and convenient
                     to them for ever.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, Roger de Merlay, Adam of Polwarth, Alexander of Seton,
                  Bernard of Howden, William de Vescy, Master William of Ednam,
                  Ralph of Ryedale, Robert of Barnoldby, and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>