<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of NRS GD55/91</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2017-02-24 13:35:55.869298+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
            <repository>National Records of Scotland</repository>
            <idno>GD55/91</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">W<ex>illiam</ex> by the grace of God king of Scots</seg> to the bishops, abbots, earls, barons, justices, sheriffs, provosts, officials,
                     and all worthy men of all his land clerk and lay <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">greeting</seg></seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let present and future</seg> know me to have granted and by this my charter to have made firm to God and to
                     the church of St Mary at Melrose and to the monks in that
                     place serving God the donation which Robert of Berkeley
                     and his spouse Cecilia the daughter of Liulf made to the
                     same monks of the ploughgate of land in the territory of
                     Maxton which the aforesaid Robert perambulated for the
                     aforementioned monks and by the same bounds which are
                     contained in the charter of the aforenamed Robert and his
                     spouse Cecilia, and with all easements of the same toun as
                     well in pastures as in easements of firewood, and stone of
                     the quarry of Alwerdene sufficient for the building of the
                     edifice of the monastery of Melrose, just as it is
                     contained in the charter of the aforesaid. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">Wherefore I will and firmly enjoin that the aforesaid monks have and possess the
                     aforementioned land with all the above-written easements
                     in free and pure and everlasting alms as freely and
                     quitely, fully and honourably, as any other alms in all my
                     kingdom is as freely and quitely, fully and honourably
                     held and possessed, and just as the charter of the
                     aforesaid Robert and his spouse Cecilia bears witness and
                     affirms; saving my service, and saving the teinds of the
                     church of Maxton</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses: Hugh my chancellor; Robert and Ralph my chaplains; Richard de
                  Prebenda my clerk; Robert of London; William of Lindsay;
                  Malcolm son of Earl Duncan; William Comyn; William de la
                  Haye; William Giffard; Walter of Berkeley, chamberlain;
                  Herbert Chalmers;</seg> AT FORFAR.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>