<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of TNA DL 25/87</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2023-03-13 15:02:37.090431+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>The National Archives</repository>
            <idno>DL 25/87</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let all present and future know that</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">I, William, son of Ralph the Lardener, and brother David, his sons, and their
                  heir</seg>, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">have quiclaimed and abjured for myself and for my heirs, and resigned by rod and
                  staff, to Robert de Brus and his heirs, or those to whom they
                  may have wished to assign, the whole land which the aforesaid
                  Ralph and the said David and my predecessors and I have held
                  of the aforesaid Robert de Brus and his predecessors, and
                  every right which belonged to us within the toun of Annan and
                  within the dependent area; in return for the account, that is
                  to say, of David my brother, who at that time was the
                  sergeand of the lord Robert de Brus in 'Herterville'; the
                  account which although I, William, undertook to settle on
                  behalf the said David my brother, I was not able to pay off;
                  and in return for the hundred shillings which the aforesaid
                  lord Robert de Brus proffered to me.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this quitclaim and abjuration I have applied my seal to this
                  writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: the lord Richard of Levington; the lord Roger Avenel;
                  William de Brus; John de Brus; William de Heriz; Humphrey de
                  Jardin; Hugh of Corrie; Robert of Crosby; Gilbert son of
                  John; Roger of Kirkpatrick; Robert of Tremore; Richard de
                  Bosco; Richard de Humez; Hugh Mauleverer; Hugh fitz Hamelin;
                  William Francis; Ingram; Thomas, clerk; and the court of the
                  aforesaid Robert de Brus of Annant.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>