<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of TNA DL 25/546</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 09:24:05.305431+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>The National Archives</repository>
            <idno>DL 25/546</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Let it be known to all</seg> ... with the consent of our heirs ... in everlasting alms for the souls ... that
                     is to say, of our ancestors and successors ... of Skeldhou
                     with all its pertinents ... <supplied>to St</supplied> Mary <supplied>and</supplied> the monks of Man ... <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">as the syke divides Godfrey's moor and the mills, and as the stream divides
                     Langliferee and the land of Mor... as the boundary is
                     known to all local inhabitants between ... and the same
                     land of Mora and descends into the sea by the Skeldhou.</seg> This land which is within these boundaries we have granted to the aforementioned
                     monks and <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">strengthened by the defence of our seal</seg>, free and quit from every earthly service which pertains to us in wood and
                     plain, in meadows and pastures, in moors, peat-bogs and
                     marshes, in saltpans and mills, in roads and pathways ...
                     can be done with easements as well named as unnamed, as an
                     evening sacrifice to God as a savour of sweetness for our
                     souls and the souls of our fathers and mothers, our wives
                     and our children, and of all our friends, as well living
                     as departed, except that the monks shall do forinsec
                     service.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Roger the prior of Furness; Ivo the dean of Copeland; Adam
                  the parson of Millum; Robert the priest of 'Punzurebi';
                  William of Esbie; John son of Pontius and William his son;
                  Edward son of Ulf and Ketill his brother; Richard son of
                  Pontius; Hugh son of Edward; Alan son of Ketill; WIlliam
                  Lubright.</seg> </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>