<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of TNA DL 36/1/240</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 09:22:03.14279+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>The National Archives</repository>
            <idno>DL 36/1/240</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all Christ's faithful who shall view or hear the present letters, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Humphrey del Bois son of the lord Thomas del Bois</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting in the Lord.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have given, granted, and by this my present charter to have made firm, and
                     for myself and my heirs to have quitclaimed to my lord,
                     the lord Robert de Brus the lord of Annandale,
                     Elshieshiels with all its pertinents, without any
                     withholding, as it is divided by my land of Eskby by the
                     ditch which my said lord had made there, in all places as
                     long and as wide as it extends towards the south, the
                     north, and east. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">For my said lord and his heirs or assigns to hold and to have freely, quitly,
                     wholly and peaceably, in woods, plains, moors, marshes,
                     and other places, with all liberties, free customs and
                     easements of whatever kind pertaining to the same place
                     within and without.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">And I Humphrey and my heirs shall warrant, acquit, and protect the aforesaid
                     land for ever, for my aforesaid lord, with its pertinents
                     as said before</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter I have applied my seal to the presents.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">As witnesses, the lords William de Brus, Humphrey of Kirkpatrick, David of
                  Torthorwald, Robert de Heriz, Roger of Kirkpatrick, John of
                  Seton, knights, Adam of Hoddom, Hugh Mauleverer, and others. </seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>