<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of TNA DL 25/88</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-04 16:29:49.581153+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>The National Archives</repository>
            <idno>DL 25/88</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all who shall view or hear this writing <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Helen the daughter of the late Roger called Porter </seg><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">wishes eternal salvation in the Lord</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition">Know me in my great need to have sold and granted to my lord Robert de Brus the
                  lord of Annandale one grange with the acre upon which it is
                  built and which stands opposite the dwelling of a certain
                  Patrick of Shelton at the head of the toun of Annan on the
                  way to the gallows in return for which the said Robert de
                  Brus has paid to me a certain amount of money as an advance
                  in my great need and in respect of which money I remain
                  satisfied and paid. For the said lord Robert de Brus and his
                  heirs or his assigns to hold and to have freely, quitly,
                  peaceably, and honourably, without any claim on me or my
                  heirs. He or his heirs are annually to render for it one
                  penny at Christmas for the lighting of St Mary’s at Annan in
                  return for every service and secular demand. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="warrandice">I and my heirs shall warrant and protect for ever against anyone the same grange
                     with the acre upon which it is built</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="sealing">In testimony of this matter I have applied my seal to this writing.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses, the lord Robert de Heriz, Ralph de Camera the constable,
                  and many others.</seg></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>