<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Translation of TNA DL 41/104</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Models of Authority edition, <date>2021-04-07 14:51:18.988047+00</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>The National Archives</repository>
            <idno>DL 41/104</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div><p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all to whom the present writing shall have come <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert de Brus</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="disposition"><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="notification">Know</seg> me to have given and granted and by this my present charter to have made firm to
                     Roger Crispin the land of 'Cnocculeran' in exchange for
                     his land of Kinmount and half a ploughgate of land which
                     he held in the feu of Moffat, that is to say, that which
                     is near Elrebec, <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="boundaries">by these named boundaries, that is, from Blakebec below Thornthwaite up to the
                     moss which is above Blakebec, and thus near that moss up
                     to Blindthwaite, and thus from Blindthwaite up to
                     Malroser, and thus along the stream from Malroser to the
                     Polraban, and thus from Polraban near the green road as
                     far as the hedge of Holthwaite, and thus by that hedge as
                     far as Threpland, and thus as far as the boundary of the
                     land of Hugh Hendeman, ans as those boundaries fall into
                     Blakebec</seg>; <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">to be held of me and my heirs by him and his heirs in feu and heritage freely
                     and quitly, fully and honourably, with common pasture of
                     Dalton, Little Dalton and Mouswald, and all other
                     easements pertaining to the aforesaid land.</seg> The aforesaid Roger and his heirs shall build and plough within the aforewritten
                     boundaries of the land, and by all means by which they are
                     able they shall assign the land within their own
                     boundaries for their own use. <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="holding">This aforesaid land shall the oft-mentioned Roger and his heirs hold of me and
                     my heirs quitly and honourably from every custom and from
                     every demand performing the twentieth part of the service
                     of one knight.</seg></seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="witnesses">With these witnesses: Richard Comyn, Henry son of Earl David; William de Heriz;
                  Robert of Crosbie; Hugh of Corrie; Richard de Houmet; John of
                  St John; Laurence of Berkeley; Robert the chaplain; and many
                  others.<lb/></seg></p> <p><seg type="diplomatic" subtype="address">To all to whom the present writing shall have come <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="intitulatio">Robert de Brus</seg> <seg type="diplomatic" subtype="salutation">sends greeting</seg>.</seg></p></div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>